<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: programming | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/programming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2018-10-22T03:52:40+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a packing spreadsheet]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/making-a-packing-spreadsheet/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/making-a-packing-spreadsheet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being the unique person I am, I love traveling. Oftentimes I end up getting deep into trying to optimize my packing methods. There are dozens of tools online designed to help with this exact thing (services like <a href="http://lighterpack.com">Lighterpack</a> or <a href="http://geargrams.com">GearGrams</a>). But, being handy with code, I decided to dabble in the subject on my own.</p>

<p>One of the most important things in packing is the overall weight of the pack, and I always want to know what type of things are the heaviest. I also want to be able to run random queries on my data, whatever it is that I&rsquo;m trying to learn. I want to have an inventory of items (backpacks, clothes, storage solutions) which I can plug in and out of a spreadsheet to see how the resulting picture changes on the go. Working with software as my day job, I’d also like for the solution to be automated whenever possible.</p>

<p>Google Spreadsheets turned out to be the perfect solution, providing the ability to quickly sum up the weight of my things and output insights about the data.</p>

<h2>Final Result</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qDhMoVmmTroM-eN0MZIU2PzE5YucsyPhbuPZPDGhemM/edit#">link to the spreadsheet</a>, I encourage the reader to copy and play around with in anyway you see fit.</p>

<p>Here’s the final result for a multi-day trip I will have for this year. As you can see, my pack weighs around 3 kilograms or a bit over 6 freedom units (not including water). My recently purchased Nintendo Switch is the heaviest item (and it’s worth every gram as it makes flying tolerable), but clothes take up most of the weight:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet.png" title="A screenshot of a packing spreadsheet." ></p>

<p>I use indentation levels to show that some items are contained within other items. This also lets me calculate the absolute and relative weights of a whole container with everything inside of it (see fields labeled “Container” and “Percentage”).</p>

<p>The “Weight” and the “Breakdown” fields indicate absolute and relative item weight respectively, which accounts for quantity of the item (quantity defaults to 1 if not explicitly set). Weight-related fields are color coded from lightest items in green to heaviest items in red.</p>

<p>Categories are used to group items and execute queries on the data and learn insights like these:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-weight-chart.png" title="A chart representing the weight of each category of items relative to a weight of the whole pack." ></p>

<p>There’s a separate sheet where I enter item names, categories, and weights, which I then use to automatically populate values above and autofill item names in the primary sheet:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-inventory.png" title="A screenshot of an inventory tab of the packing spreadsheet." ></p>

<h2>The Technical Details</h2>

<p>I haven’t worked with Google Spreadsheets (or Excel for that matter) a lot in the past, but with an access to clear documentation (and a hundred of web searches later) it was straightforward to get the hang of the it.</p>

<p>I started off by manually populating the final result sheet, manually adjusting formulas for Container/Percentage cells, as I had no idea how I would detect the indentation yet. I like when things look pretty, so I applied conditional formatting rules right away, and the looks of the sheet really haven’t changed throughout the process.</p>

<p>Next, I created an inventory sheet, which I wanted to use as a source of data in the resulting sheet. A few Google searches and some trial &amp; error resulted in a lookup formula:</p>

<pre><code>=ArrayFormula(
 IF(
   NOT(ISBLANK($B2)),
   INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($B2, InventoryItems, 0)),
   IF(
     NOT(ISBLANK($C2)),
     INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($C2, InventoryItems, 0)),
     INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($D2, InventoryItems, 0))
   )
  )
)
</code></pre>

<p><code>ArrayFormula</code> is necessary in order to create arrays on the fly without printing intermediate results in the spreadsheet. <code>InventoryItems</code> and <code>InventoryCategories</code> are named ranges referring to item names and categories in the inventory sheet. <code>MATCH</code> finds an index of a first occurrence of the item name in the sheet, and retrieves corresponding category name. An item weight is retrieved by the exact same principle.</p>

<p>Trying to find the container weight took a lot more time, and resulted in a lot more headache. Solution for handling indentation in Google Spreadsheets wasn’t as elegant as I would have hoped for, but it got the job done:</p>

<pre><code>=ArrayFormula(
     SUM(
       $I2:INDIRECT(
         CONCATENATE(
           "$I",
           ROW() + IF(
             NOT(ISBLANK($B2)),
             MATCH(FALSE, ISBLANK($B3:$B), 0),
             MATCH(FALSE, ISBLANK($C3:$C), 0)
           ) - 1
         )
       )
     )
</code></pre>

<p>The formula above finds the first non-empty cell in a column. It starts searching from the next row (for example, for an item on a second row, we look at the third row and below). After it knows which row first non-empty cell is in, the formula turns it into a string (column $I contains item weights) and use it as an upper bound of a sum of the weights. Finished formula is a bit longer (it adds sugar to only display the number when needed), and if you’re interested - you can look it up in the spreadsheet.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-indentation.png" title="A screenshot used for explaining indentation logic." ></p>

<p>For example, in the screenshot above, the formula will start looking at cells in a column right after the &ldquo;Packing cube&rdquo;. As soon as it finds a non-empty cell (&ldquo;Nintendo Switch case&rdquo;), the formula will determine this row to be an upper boundary. The formula then will sum weights starting with a &ldquo;Packing cube&rdquo; row, and up to but not including &ldquo;Nintendo Switch case&rdquo; row.</p>

<p>The rest involved many small tweaks, adding pretty colors, hiding N/A errors and zeroes, and trying to find the perfect shade for column borders.</p>

<p>And, since you made it this far, here’s how the numbers above look in the real world:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/cleveland-trip-backpack-on-off.png" title="Side by side pictures of a packed backpack: open and closed." ></p>

<p>Hopefully you found this useful, or at least somewhat entertaining. There’s a lot of room for improvement, and I aimed to provide a framework and a few basic ideas for building a spreadsheet to accommodate one’s twisted ultralight needs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Automating Octorpress Publishing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/automating-octopress-publishing/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-14T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/automating-octopress-publishing</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I really like Octopress. It builds on top of Jekyll to address certain rough edges, and provides ready to go lighting fast blogging platform. It&rsquo;s easily extendible if you know how to code (thanks to a rather clean and well organized code base), and posts are just plain Markdown files.</p>

<p>One issue though - I need to be near a computer to publish and preview the article. This becomes difficult if I&rsquo;m traveling with, say, a tablet.</p>

<p>I have a low end AWS Lightsail instance I use for writing and publishing, but it&rsquo;s not always fun to write when SSHing into a server, and I often write offline - making it even more difficult to move files between where I write and where I publish. And managing images is a nightmare. To resolve this, I set up a few directories I use in Dropbox, and wrote a few scripts to move things around when needed.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a directory structure in Dropbox:</p>

<pre><code>- blog/
  - posts/
    - 2017-11-20-automatic-octopress-publishing.markdown
  - img/
    - input/
      - a-picture-of-a-flower.jpg
    - output/
</code></pre>

<p>I put Markdown files in <code>Dropbox/blog/posts/</code> (and numerous offline editors sync with Dropbox - I&rsquo;m writing this with <a href="https://stackedit.io/app">StackEdit</a>, and I use <a href="https://ia.net/writer/">iA Writer</a> on my tablet). I add my images to <code>Dropbox/img/input/</code>. I  tend to strip metadata from my images and resize them to fit the maximum page width (I don&rsquo;t really care for high resolution pictures, speed is preferred over ability to zoom into a picture). For this, two tools are needed:</p>

<pre><code>sudo apt-get install imagemagick exiftool
</code></pre>

<p>When I&rsquo;m done writing or want to preview an article, I SSH into my AWS Lightsail instance and run <code>sync.sh</code>, a small script which moves posts to a proper directory, processes images and places them in the desired location, as well as starts Octopress instance (this way I can preview my blog on the AWS Lightsail instance). Contents of <code>sync.sh</code> (don&rsquo;t forget to <code>chmod +x</code>):</p>

<pre><code>#!/bin/bash
cd $HOME/Dropbox/blog/img/input
mogrify -resize 832x620 -quality 100 -path $HOME/Dropbox/blog/img/output *.jpg
exiftool -all= $HOME/Dropbox/blog/img/output/*.jpg
cp $HOME/Dropbox/blog/posts/*.markdown $HOME/blog/source/_posts
cp $HOME/Dropbox/blog/img/output/*.jpg $HOME/blog/source/images/posts
cd $HOME/blog
rake generate
rake preview
</code></pre>

<p>I run the above script every time I want to preview the site. I&rsquo;m sure it&rsquo;s easy to set up a daemon to watch for changes in the Dropbox folders, but I don&rsquo;t see the need for that yet. Also, I just statically resize images to a particular resolution (832x620) since all of the pictures I upload have the same aspect ratio, I&rsquo;m sure there&rsquo;s a way to calculate that number on the fly for this script to work with different aspect ratios.</p>

<p>Lastly, when I deployed and committed my changes (still commit and deploy manually out of a habit), I run <code>archive.sh</code>:</p>

<pre><code>#!/bin/bash
mv $HOME/Dropbox/blog/posts/*.markdown $HOME/Dropbox/blog/published
rm $HOME/Dropbox/blog/img/input/*
rm $HOME/Dropbox/blog/img/output/*
</code></pre>

<p>It&rsquo;s not much, but enough to save some manual labor involved in publishing to Octopress.</p>

<!--stackedit_data:
eyJoaXN0b3J5IjpbMTY3OTE1ODIzNl19
-->

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Contributing to an existing Octopress blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/contributing-to-an-existing-octopress-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-12-17T05:09:58+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/contributing-to-an-existing-octopress-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had to download my Octopress blog to a new machine today and the process of
setting up didn&rsquo;t go as smoothly as I expected. At the end of the day the setup
turned out to be simple, and here are the steps:</p>

<pre><code>git clone -b source https://github.com/username/username.github.io myblog
cd myblog
git clone https://github.com/username/username.github.io _deploy
bundle install
</code></pre>

<p>In a nutshell, you have to manually add <code>_deploy</code> folder set to track <code>master</code>
branch of your Octopress repository. Otherwise <code>rake deploy</code> command fails.</p>

<p>Happy writing!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One more argument for 80 character limit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/one-more-argument-for-80-character-limit/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T06:00:04+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/one-more-argument-for-80-character-limit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Limiting code to 80 (or 100 or 120) characters per line. It&rsquo;s a well-known
topic, and there&rsquo;s an overall consensus on the subject, not counting occasional
questions by newbies and odd cases. Most established tech companies have their
own line length guidelines. These are often dependent on a language, such as in
the case of Google with their 80 character Python and 100 character Java limits.</p>

<p>In this article, I won&rsquo;t be advocating all the usual arguments, such as easier
diff with version control software, or the ability to stack windows side by side
on wide screens. No, I believe that battle to be won quite a long time ago, the
topic is now closed. But something I didn&rsquo;t find mentioned in any of the
discussions is an interesting point from the world of writers and designers.</p>

<p>Ever since I started being interested in improving my writing skills, I found
article after article mention the importance of line length in reading.
Interestingly enough, this issue was raised in a world of literature. It had
been resolved long before programmers were fascinated with the desire to use up
rapidly expanding screen real estate.</p>

<p>I am talking about something known as &ldquo;measure&rdquo; in typography. It seems to be
the reason newspapers use narrow columns, or books leave such vast margins
around the text on a page. Here&rsquo;s an exempt from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Measure_(typography)">Wikipedia article</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Measure (or sometimes &ldquo;The Measure&rdquo;) in typography is the length of a line of
text. For a single-column design measure should ideally lie between 40 &amp; 80
characters. Many typographers consider the perfect measure to be 65
characters. If the lines are too short then the text becomes disjointed, if
they are too long the content loses rhythm as the reader searches for the
start of each line. Punctuation should preferably hang outside the measure.</p></blockquote>

<p>Most programming languages use special operators and keywords, which can be
considered &ldquo;punctuation&rdquo;. Some languages are more verbose (use more
punctuation), and some aren&rsquo;t. If you remove punctuation, the 80/100/120
character limit perfectly fits the standard time-honed &ldquo;measure&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Maybe I can use this as an additional argument the next time I have to explain
to a junior new hire why the character limits are so strictly enforced.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Export WordPress posts to plain text]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/export-wordpress-posts-to-plain-text/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-02T03:44:12+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/export-wordpress-posts-to-plain-text</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I prefer to create and edit my posts in plain text. It&rsquo;s a timeless format, and
I find it nice to have an archive of posts lying around in plain text.</p>

<p>I wrote a little Python script which I used to extract an archive of my posts
and pages into a bunch of files on my computer. In order to use it, you need to
use &ldquo;<a href="http://wordpress.org/plugins/wordpress-importer/">WordPress Importer</a>&rdquo; plugin. Export your posts and pages into a WXR
format, and feed the file to the script.</p>

<p>Source code of the script is below (link for downloading the script is at the
bottom of this post):</p>

<pre><code>#!/usr/bin/env python

"""This script converts WXR file to a number of plain text files.

WXR stands for "WordPress eXtended RSS", which basically is just a
regular XML file. This script extracts entries from the WXR file into
plain text files. Output format: article name prefixed by date for
posts, article name for pages.

Usage: wxr2txt.py filename [-o output_dir]
"""

import os
import re
import sys
from xml.etree import ElementTree

NAMESPACES = {
        'content': 'http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/',
        'wp': 'http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/',
}
USAGE_STRING = "Usage: wxr2txt.py filename [-o output_dir]"

def main(argv):
    filename, output_dir = _parse_and_validate_output(argv)
    try:
        data = ElementTree.parse(filename).getroot()
    except ElementTree.ParseError:
        _error("Invalid input file format. Can not parse the input.")
    page_counter, post_counter = 0, 0
    for post in data.find('channel').findall('item'):
        post_type = post.find('wp:post_type', namespaces=NAMESPACES).text
        if post_type not in ('post', 'page'):
            continue
        content = post.find('content:encoded', namespaces=NAMESPACES).text
        date = post.find('wp:post_date', namespaces=NAMESPACES).text
        title = post.find('title').text
        date = date.split(' ')[0].replace('-', '')
        title = re.sub(r'[_]+', '_', re.sub(r'[^a-z0-9+]', '_', title.lower()))
        if post_type == 'post':
            post_filename = date + '_' + title + '.txt'
            post_counter += 1
        else:
            post_filename = title + '.txt'
            page_counter += 1
        with open(os.path.join(output_dir, post_filename), 'w') as post_file:
            post_file.write(content.encode('utf8'))
        post_counter += 1
    print "Saved {} posts and {} pages in directory '{}'.".format(
            post_counter, page_counter, output_dir)

def _parse_and_validate_output(argv):
    if len(argv) not in (2, 4):
        _error("Wrong number of arguments.")
    filename = argv[1]
    if not os.path.isfile(filename):
        _error("Input file does not exist (or not enough permissions).")
    output_dir = argv[3] if len(argv) == 4 and argv[2] == '-o' else os.getcwd()
    if not os.path.isdir(output_dir):
        _error("Output directory does not exist (or not enough permissions).")
    return filename, output_dir

def _error(text):
    print text
    print USAGE_STRING
    sys.exit(1)

if __name__ == "__main__":
    main(sys.argv)
</code></pre>

<p>You can download the script from here: <a href="https://gist.github.com/ruslanosipov/b748a138389db2cda1e8">wxr2txt.py</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
