<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-06T13:25:22-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[High stakes email checklist]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/high-stakes-email-checklist/"/>
    <updated>2023-07-06T13:05:13-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/high-stakes-email-checklist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m making a little cheat sheet for myself. As I progress in my career, much of
my work revolves around communication, and I&rsquo;d be remiss if I don&rsquo;t share a
formal framework I use. I like checklists, spreadsheets, and anything else that
organizes the world around me, and it&rsquo;s fun to make one about communications.</p>

<h2>Checklist</h2>

<p>This is a checklist for high stakes emails, let&rsquo;s dig in:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goals</strong>

<ul>
<li>What are you trying to accomplish? Why? (It could be worth asking why
multiple times.)</li>
<li>Will this email help you accomplish the goal?</li>
<li>Can the goal be summarized in a single sentence? If not, it&rsquo;s probably not
specific enough.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Audience</strong>

<ul>
<li>Who is the audience?</li>
<li>What does the audience care about? How can you connect the subject of your
email to things they care about?</li>
<li>Does every recipient need to be there? Who&rsquo;s missing?</li>
<li>What action do you want the reader to take? Is there a clear call for
action? For executive communications (who have notoriously short attention
span), you&rsquo;ll want to both start and end with the same call for action.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Content</strong>

<ul>
<li>Is there a nuance that would be lost in email that requires face to face
conversation? Does this need to be an email?</li>
<li>Does every sentence and paragraph support your goal?</li>
<li>Does this need a TL;DR?</li>
<li>Is the narrative structure in place? Is there a clear beginning, middle, and
end? No need to write a novel, but without this the content risks being
disjoined.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Impulse</strong>

<ul>
<li>Is now the best time to send it? Friday afternoon is almost always a no-no,
unless you purposely want the reader to pay less attention to the issue.</li>
<li>If this was shared broadly, would you rephrase it? If yes - you definitely
should.

<ul>
<li>To double down, if email is about someone, write as if that someone will
eventually see it. It&rsquo;s fine to be candid, it&rsquo;s not fine to be rude.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Are you angry? Upset? I get notoriously cranky in the late afternoon, and
avoid sending anything important until the next day - or, if time sensitive,
until taking a short break or a walk.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Example</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s apply this to an example. Say, I&rsquo;m writing a book, and the editor I&rsquo;m
working with hasn&rsquo;t been responsive. I&rsquo;ve tried talking to them about it, but
they&rsquo;re not responsive. I think it&rsquo;s the time to escalate to their supervisor.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the quick, dirty, and impulsive draft I would write:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hello X,</p>

<p>Y hasn&rsquo;t been responsive when reviewing the chapters, and it&rsquo;s really
difficult to get back to chapters after a whole week passes by. By then I
don&rsquo;t even have the context! I&rsquo;ve raised this multiple times and to no avail.
Can you please get Y to be more responsive or find another editor for me to
work with? I haven&rsquo;t been able to make meaningful progress in a month!</p></blockquote>

<p>Pretty brusque, isn&rsquo;t it? I don&rsquo;t normally dissect every email like this, but
sometimes it helps to take a closer look and formalize the decision making
behind each sentence. Thankfully, much of this becomes habitual over time.</p>

<h3>Goals</h3>

<p>First things first, I want the editor to be more responsive. Why? To have a
shorter feedback loop when it comes to making changes. Why? To make it easier
to write - it&rsquo;s difficult to come back to the chapter after a long amount of
time passed. Why? This pushes back timelines for each chapter.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t really care about how to achieve this goal: the same person can be
more responsive, or maybe I get a new point of contact to work with. Maybe
there are other options I haven&rsquo;t considered.</p>

<p>To summarize in a single sentence, the goal is to &ldquo;reduce the feedback loop&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Audience</h3>

<p>The audience is the editor&rsquo;s supervisor, or maybe someone else from the
editorial team who&rsquo;ll have the incentive to escalate.</p>

<p>I know that the timelines are very important to this publisher, which is
something I can use. I can frame the concerns around impacts of the timeline -
even if it&rsquo;s not something I necessarily care about myself.</p>

<p>Since there are multiple ways to achieve my goal and I don&rsquo;t particularly care
about how, I can make the call for action open ended. I&rsquo;m doing this because I&rsquo;m
comfortable with either outcomes - like the editor not being to improve response
times, but the publisher providing more leniency around the schedule - which,
while isn&rsquo;t ideal, still helps.</p>

<h3>Content</h3>

<p>As multiple people can help me accomplish a goal, and I might not be aware of
all of relevant parties - email format works best.</p>

<p>Narrative structure here is simple - I have a problem (the beginning), here&rsquo;s why
it&rsquo;s bad (the middle), let&rsquo;s fix it (the end).</p>

<p>This email is short enough not to require a TL;DR.</p>

<h3>Impulse</h3>

<p>As my concern is about a particular person, I have to talk about them. I don&rsquo;t
want to avoid candor, but I can approach the situation with empathy and
assumption of best intentions something along the lines of: &ldquo;I understand X has
other commitments&rdquo;. Focusing on facts and leading with empathy would help here.</p>

<p>Having an unresponsive editor is definitely frustrating, so it&rsquo;s worth taking a
step back, and maybe paying extra attention - there&rsquo;s no use having frustration
show through.</p>

<h3>The result</h3>

<p>After running through the checklist, we end up with (what I hope is) a better,
more actionable, and less icky email:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hello X,</p>

<p>When working with Y, it takes up to a week for me to receive feedback on the
chapters I wrote. I understand Y is working with multiple engagements, but
I&rsquo;m concerned about the timelines for the book. If we continue as is, it&rsquo;s
likely we&rsquo;ll have to push publishing date by X months.</p>

<p>Could you help me find a resolution here?</p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s short, omits unnecessary details, and leaves the reader with a clear (but
open ended) call for action. Now, all that&rsquo;s left is to schedule send that
email in a morning, and wait for a response!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exercising online privacy rights]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/exercising-online-privacy-rights/"/>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:19:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/exercising-online-privacy-rights</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following Europe&rsquo;s 2016 General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), California passed its own California Consumer Privacy Act (CCPA) in 2020. I won&rsquo;t pretend to understand the intricacies of the law or the differences between the two, but from what I understand this gives you the right to know exactly what data of yours do businesses use, and request that this information is to not be sold or to be deleted.</p>

<p>As a California resident, I decided to dedicate a long weekend to exercising my privacy rights. The long weekend turned into a week worth of back and forth with a dozen-or-so companies, and me having a much better idea of what information about me is out there.</p>

<p>Turned out many large websites provide privacy dashboards where you&rsquo;re able to review and see information collected or inferred about you. But most of this data is hidden behind a formal request process which takes a few days to a week.</p>

<hr />

<p>First, I decided to stroll through Google&rsquo;s privacy settings. There are two ways forward: privacy dashboard, or full-on Google Takeout. Google Takeout allows you to download an archive of <strong>everything</strong> Google has on you, which took a few days to process, and is near impossible to go through while keeping your sanity. So I decided to play with the privacy dashboard instead.</p>

<p>Google Maps has location history of most places I&rsquo;ve visited for the past ten or so years (creepy, but I found it useful on more than one occasion), and YouTube and Search history stores thousands of searches. I already had Assistant history disabled, since storing audio recordings is apparently where I draw the line when it comes to privacy. Targeted ad profile was an interesting thing to look at, accurately summing up my lifestyle in 50 words or less. I ended up disabling targeted ads from Google (and all other services as I went about on my privacy crusade).</p>

<p>Google had some of the finest privacy controls compared to other services, with actionable privacy-leaning suggestions. Google&rsquo;s not known for its services playing well together, but privacy is where Google feels closer to Apple experience - everything is in a single place, surfaced in the same format, easy to control, and plays well together. Given the amount of transparency and fine grained control, I feel pretty good staying in the Google ecosystem.</p>

<hr />

<p>Next I looked at LinkedIn. Outside of the expected things &ndash; emails, phone numbers, messages, invitations, and a history of just about everything I&rsquo;ve ever clicked on, a file labeled &ldquo;inferences&rdquo; stood out. Whether LinkedIn thinks you&rsquo;re open to job seeking opportunities, or what stage of career you are in, or if you travel for businesses, or if you&rsquo;re a recruiter or maybe a senior leader in your company.</p>

<p>Since LinkedIn is a professional network, all information I share is well curated and is meant as public by default &ndash; and I found LinkedIn privacy settings in line with my expectations.</p>

<hr />

<p>As an avid gamer, I went through Steam, Good Old Games, Ubisoft, Epic Games, and Origin privacy details. Unsurprisingly, the services tracked every time I launched every game, shopping preferences, and so on. Thankfully the data seemed confined to the world of gaming &ndash; which made this level of being creepy somewhat okay in my book.</p>

<p>I also looked at random websites I use somewhat frequently &ndash; Reddit, StackOverflow, PayPal, Venmo, AirBnB, and some others &ndash; not too many surprises there, although I did end up tightening privacy settings and opting out of personal data sharing and ad tracking for every service.</p>

<p>Last year I requested deletion of all my data on Mint, Personal Capital, and YNAB (You Need a Budget), and to be honest I&rsquo;m a little relived that I didn&rsquo;t have to look at the data these companies had on me.</p>

<hr />

<p>Amazon data sharing turned out to be the scariest finding. Until now I didn&rsquo;t really self-identify as a heavy Amazon user, but that turned out to be a lie: Prime shopping, Kindle, Audible, Prime Video.</p>

<p>The amount of data Amazon kept on me was overwhelming: Kindle and Audible track every time I read, play, or pause books, the Amazon website keeps full track of browsing habits, and Prime Video has detailed watch times and history. Most of this data ties back into real world &ndash; including nearly every address I ever lived at or phone numbers I had.</p>

<p>Even scarier, despite never using Alexa, I found numerous recordings of my voice from close to a decade ago &ndash; me checking status of the packages, but a few of me just breathing and walking around. I found no way of deleting these, as they didn&rsquo;t show up in any privacy settings (including me installing an Alexa app just to get into privacy settings).</p>

<p>All of this gave me pause. It feels like the privacy controls are either lacking, hidden, or spread out thin across Amazon&rsquo;s various apps. And I&rsquo;ve only briefly scanned through the data Amazon had on me.</p>

<hr />

<p>That&rsquo;s where I had to take a break.</p>

<p>I have accounts with hundreds of services, and I have no idea how my personal data is used, and what it&rsquo;s joined with. As I&rsquo;m go on about my daily life, I&rsquo;ll start tightening privacy controls, and maybe deleting services and their data where possible.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s just too creepy for my taste.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Experience with financial planners]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/experience-with-financial-planners/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-17T12:07:33-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/experience-with-financial-planners</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I&rsquo;m starting to write more about early retirement, I think more and more about financial planners and advisors I&rsquo;ve talked to along the way. The first financial planner I ever talked to (who&rsquo;s been now fired from a role of my financial advisor and promoted into a position of friendship) reminded me about the beginning of the journey after reading one of the FIRE articles I&rsquo;ve posted earlier this month.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve talked to half a dozen financial planners over the past 5-or-so years. Some of those conversations have been very influential, and some have been more aggravating than anything else &ndash; but it was a net positive experience for me.</p>

<p>The aforementioned financial advisor I&rsquo;ve had the pleasure to talk to was a colleague&rsquo;s spouse. I&rsquo;ve voiced my interest in early retirement, and we decided to sit down and run through a financial overview.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve learned a lot from this meeting, and the advisor helped me frame my knowledge, and fill in the gaps for everything I&rsquo;ve learned on the Internets. The biggest value came from leveraging tax-advantaged accounts and employment benefits: maximizing 401(k), IRA, and HSA contributions, leveraging IRA backdoor and 401(k) megabackdoor (I just talked about these in detail in &ldquo;<a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/accessing-retirement-funds-early/">Accessing retirement funds early</a>&rdquo;). We discussed fund selections, risk profiles, and even touched on housing. It was great to have an opportunity to have someone who knows what they&rsquo;re talking about answer all the questions that built up over the years.</p>

<p>The conversation had profound impact on my initial portfolio and investment strategy, and set pace for early retirement planning. With the confidence of having my plan and assumptions validated, I went on with my investments (employing the &ldquo;slow, boring and steady&rdquo; strategy, if you&rsquo;re interested).</p>

<p>After some time said colleague and his spouse became our family friends: and I don&rsquo;t much care for doing business with friends.</p>

<p>After that experience, I struggled to find the person I would work with for a prolonged amount of time.</p>

<p>At some point I thought I found &ldquo;my guy&rdquo;: a financial planner who was familiar with early retirement, and was eager to do additional research for just about any topic I could ask. Unfortunately for me it didn&rsquo;t take long for &ldquo;my guy&rdquo; to soar through corporate ranks and get promoted past working with individual clients.</p>

<p>This is where the cracks started to show. For many financial planners, early retirement refers to age 55. And that makes sense &ndash; retirement in your 30s is such a niche topic! Most financial planning tools don&rsquo;t account for this. Things like tapping into 401(k) or IRA balances before age 59 &frac12; is not something supported by the rigid financial projection tooling.</p>

<p>Your typical financial planner will not be intimately familiar with the intricacies of early retirement &ndash; or any other niche topics for that matter. And that&rsquo;s okay. Because financial professionals still know their shit &ndash; and it&rsquo;s much easier for them to make professional judgement about things your smart ass found online.</p>

<p>The best financial planners I talked to were willing to listen and put in work outside of our calls. Those folks would understand my concerns, supplement their answers with research, and come back with educated opinions.</p>

<p>A model that works for me is providing my questions and concerns in advance of the call, giving the advisor time to research niche and domain specific questions.</p>

<p>Financial planners worked for me especially well for two purposes:</p>

<ol>
<li>Confirm that my understanding of something is correct.</li>
<li>Tell me about things I don&rsquo;t know or haven&rsquo;t thought about.</li>
</ol>


<p>This is where a financial planner pointed out that I misunderstood 401(k) contribution limits, or didn&rsquo;t consider implications of varied cost of health insurance in retirement. This is the person I bombarded with an hour worth of questions about my auto insurance or the need for umbrella policy.</p>

<p>One time fee advisors worked best for me. I know some folks who moved assets under management for a certain percentage of those assets in fees, and are now trying to get out. This worked okay for them early on, but ended up not being what they want as they became more financially savvy. And it turned out to be oh-so-expensive in the long run.</p>

<p>And there are many things I had to watch out for along the road. Some advisors I&rsquo;ve talked to seem to have no idea what they&rsquo;re talking about, and just sound misguided. And it&rsquo;s not solely my opinion - sometimes I would write down something a person would say, ask for independent opinion, and get back &ldquo;What drugs are they on? I would like some of that!&rdquo;</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also the question of their interest.</p>

<p>Some financial advisors might be inclined to sell things like lucrative whole term life insurance, and while in certain cases it&rsquo;s appropriate, it might not always work for all individuals. But it sure as hell pays well for those advisors, so it&rsquo;s hard to fault them for peddling the insurance.</p>

<p>The United States has a fiduciary system that&rsquo;s supposedly requires a planner to work in your best interest (I personally learned about it from <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gvZSpET11ZY">this Last Week Tonight show episode</a>).</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve done a lot of your own research (and especially if you haven&rsquo;t) &ndash; it certainly wouldn&rsquo;t hurt to talk to professional and review your decisions. Someone who has an idea of what they&rsquo;re doing can go a long way in making sure you&rsquo;re not heading down the wrong path &ndash; and if you are &ndash; you&rsquo;re doing it with full awareness of the trade offs you&rsquo;re making. Just be mindful of pitfalls when doing so.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Journaling for work-life balance]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/journaling-for-work-life-balance/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-12T13:32:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/journaling-for-work-life-balance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When writing about <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets/">snippets at Google</a> earlier this week, I omitted a fairly important bit: how lists and journaling help me create distance between work and life. This became especially <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-at-work/">relevant in the pandemic</a>, as I had to work with my therapist on being able to mentally disconnect.</p>

<p>I wrote about my strained relationship with ToDo lists <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/why-i-threw-away-my-to-do-list/">before</a>: all the way back in 2014. Back then I focused on moving away from a monolithic ToDo list, and focusing on just a few major things I&rsquo;d like to accomplish each day. I continued to do this, but with some changes to my philosophy.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m back to keeping a ToDo list, but it&rsquo;s a bit more complex than a single list I used to keep. I split things I care about by days, weeks, and months, and I review these lists regularly.</p>

<p>Last year I learned about <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/pages/learn">bullet journaling</a>, often shortened to &ldquo;BuJo&rdquo;. Akin to artisan coffee and avocado toast, this hipster friendly and highly marketable approach has a solid foundation. At its core bullet journaling consists of two parts. First is a consistent and simple notation for tasks, notes, and events: some simple guidelines on how to document what happened, what will happen, and what you need to remember. Second part is a rule set on organizing these lists: daily and monthly notes, custom logs, and so on.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/bullet-journal.png" title="Picture of a bullet journal with a few sample tasks, notes, and events." ></p>

<p>I rigorously keep daily notes about work, meeting annotations, records of important thoughts and ideas, and things I need to do (or have already done). This helps me leave work at work &ndash; or more precisely leave work in a journal. Once it&rsquo;s closed - I&rsquo;m done for the day. Everything I need to think about is written down, and there&rsquo;s no need for my mind to wonder back.</p>

<p>Some weeks I omit note taking, and the contrast in my well-being is jarring. My mind wonders back to the events of the week, and I even have trouble sleeping some days. And no one wants to dream about work &ndash; I&rsquo;m sure as hell not paid enough for that.</p>

<p>Another technique I picked up from the bullet journal keeps me from getting overwhelmed and keeping focus. BuJo advocates for regular migration of ToDo items &ndash; meaning that you should be crossing out and rewriting the same thing over and over again, day by day, week by week. At some point it becomes either to either do something about those ToDos, or choose not to do them altogether. Either way, it&rsquo;s a huge weight off my shoulders.</p>

<p>And this is where the <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets/">aforementioned snippets</a> come in. At the end of the week, all I have to do is go through the weekly set of notes, and transcribe noteworthy bullet points. That&rsquo;s the time I take to look back at my week, migrate tasks I choose to revisit at a later date, or cross off tasks I choose not to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Communicating via snippets]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-07T16:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve learned a lot of cool things during my tenure at Google.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/i-have-approximate-knowledge-of-many-things.gif" title="I have approximate knowledge of many things..." ></p>

<p>One of those things are snippets. Google (and from what I hear other Silicon Valley giants as well) utilizes a system of snippets: a transparent and widely accessible set of weekly notes. It&rsquo;s not mandatory, and some groups use it more often then others. Sounds ordinary, but I think it&rsquo;s a lot more interesting then that.</p>

<p>Communication and visibility is one of the major challenges in any paid creative work, but it&rsquo;s especially important in software engineering. Engineers often settle on tasks they know nothing about: tasks are hard to measure and estimate. This makes it even harder to communicate progress broadly.</p>

<p>There are ways around this communication barrier &ndash; regular standups or periodic reviews come to mind. But there&rsquo;s a better (although not necessarily exclusive), more asynchronous way to communicate and increase visibility. Enter snippets - a condensed list of what happened with you and your colleagues last week, delivered straight to your inbox.</p>

<p>Every Friday, an email notification reminds you to fill in weekly snippets. These snippets might look something like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Project X

<ul>
<li>Authored a design doc (link), sent for a review</li>
<li>Discussed roadmap with stakeholders A and B (notes)</li>
<li>Debugged issue Z, to no avail (link)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Project Y

<ul>
<li>Cleared backlog for the past 6 months</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Attended a summit about G</li>
<li>Had 1:1s with C, D, E, and F</li>
</ul>


<p>On Monday, an email goes out compiling our team&rsquo;s snippets in a single digest. Skimming through snippets covers any communication gaps from the past week, and raises visibility on what everyone is working on.</p>

<p>This system has many benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Transparency: you know what everyone around you (including higher ups) is up to.</li>
<li>You actually remember what you&rsquo;ve done a month from now.</li>
<li>All the important documents, events, and notes are linked from snippets. Snippets are are time bound, which makes these documents easy to find.</li>
<li>Teammates and managers can always check snippets to get an idea of progress on certain efforts.</li>
<li>You manager (who&rsquo;s hopefully your biggest ally when it comes to career development) has a great idea of what you&rsquo;re up to.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s easy to find artifacts and proof during performance reviews.</li>
<li>Higher visibility of glue work (all the little things you do to keep the place running).</li>
</ul>


<p>This doesn&rsquo;t have to be a particularly complex system. A running doc with notes could suffice, although email notifications remove a lot of the overhead needed. Even if the organization doesn&rsquo;t follow the model, I find it worthwhile to keep snippets, and to share them with my manager and team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Accessing retirement funds early]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/accessing-retirement-funds-early/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-03T09:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/accessing-retirement-funds-early</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I&rsquo;m reentering a society after the pandemic, I had the pleasure to chat with a family friend about early retirement strategies. One of the many topics that popped up was about accessing age-locked retirement funds - namely 401(k)s and IRAs. Conventional wisdom is that these account stay locked until you hit a certain age, but funds from these accounts are accessible as long as you&rsquo;re ready to jump through some hoops.</p>

<p>I put together this post to test my understanding of the subject, so please let me know if there&rsquo;s something I misunderstand. I used the <a href="https://www.irs.gov/">IRS</a> and the <a href="https://uscode.house.gov">United States Code</a> websites as the sources of truth, and I link to each throughout this piece. The links are likely to get out of date within a few months to a year though, so don&rsquo;t hold your breath for those.</p>

<p>This article is for retirement accounts in the United States only.</p>

<h2>Tax-advantaged accounts</h2>

<p>There are 5 tax-advantaged retirement vessels that I&rsquo;m somewhat familiar with:</p>

<ul>
<li>Traditional 401(k)</li>
<li>Roth 401(k)</li>
<li>Traditional IRA</li>
<li>Roth IRA</li>
<li>HSA</li>
</ul>


<p>These are not the only tax-advantaged accounts out there for different employment situations, but I think these are fairly common. Here&rsquo;s a quick reference for each with some stats as of June 2021:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>                               </th>
<th> 401(k)          </th>
<th> Roth 401(k)     </th>
<th> IRA      </th>
<th> Roth IRA          </th>
<th> HSA          </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Employer-sponsored?           </td>
<td> Yes             </td>
<td> Yes             </td>
<td> No       </td>
<td> No                </td>
<td> Sometimes    </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Allows for employer match?    </td>
<td> Yes             </td>
<td> Yes             </td>
<td> No       </td>
<td> No                </td>
<td> Yes          </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Tax-advantaged contrib. limit </td>
<td> $19,500 + match </td>
<td> $19,500 + match </td>
<td> $6,000   </td>
<td> $6,000            </td>
<td> $3,600       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Total contrib. limit          </td>
<td> $58,000         </td>
<td> $58,000         </td>
<td> $6,000   </td>
<td> $6,000            </td>
<td> $3,600       </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Contrib. increase at age 50+  </td>
<td> $6,500          </td>
<td> $6,500          </td>
<td> $1,000   </td>
<td> $1,000            </td>
<td> $1,000 (55+) </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Taxation                      </td>
<td> Deferred        </td>
<td> Exempt          </td>
<td> Deferred </td>
<td> Exempt            </td>
<td> Exempt/free  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Withdrawal timeline           </td>
<td> 59 &frac12;          </td>
<td> 59 &frac12;          </td>
<td> 59 &frac12;   </td>
<td> 59 &frac12; or 5 years </td>
<td> Qualified/65 </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Mandatory withdrawal          </td>
<td> 70              </td>
<td> 70              </td>
<td> 72       </td>
<td> N/A               </td>
<td> N/A          </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Early withdrawal penalty      </td>
<td> 10%             </td>
<td> 10%             </td>
<td> 10%      </td>
<td> 10%               </td>
<td> 20%          </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>I dig into each a little bit more below.</p>

<h3>Traditional and Roth 401(k)</h3>

<p>401(k) is an employer sponsored plan: it allows you to invest in a choice of funds selected by your employer. 401(k) often comes with an employer match, which allows the employer to contribute additional amount on top of the tax-advantaged contribution limit. At age 50, you can contribute additional amount in &ldquo;catch-up contributions&rdquo;.</p>

<p>There are two limits for 401(k) plans: the tax-advantaged contribution limit (at $19,500/year in 2021, not including employer match), and the total contribution limit (at $58,000) (<a href="https://www.irs.gov/retirement-plans/plan-participant-employee/retirement-topics-401k-and-profit-sharing-plan-contribution-limits">IRS website</a>). You don&rsquo;t get any tax benefits from contributing to your total contribution limit, but it&rsquo;s primarily used for &ldquo;401(k) megabackdoor&rdquo; - to funnel money into a tax-advantaged Roth IRA. The limits are shared across Traditional and Roth 401(k).</p>

<p>From what I understand, Roth 401(k) also requires the employer match to be contributed to a Traditional 401(k) account.</p>

<p>Traditional 401(k) is tax-deferred, meaning you don&rsquo;t pay taxes on the amount contributed, but you pay taxes on withdrawal &ndash; this includes paying taxes on the principal (the investment income). In contrast, Roth 401(k) is tax-exempt. You pay your taxes in advance, and investment income or withdrawals are not taxed.</p>

<p>Early withdrawal penalty of 10% applies if you attempt the funds before age 59 &frac12;, but keep on reading to learn how to get around that. You must begin withdrawing from your 401(k) by age 70.</p>

<h3>Traditional and Roth IRA</h3>

<p>IRA is an individual plan which allows for tax-advantaged investments. Direct contribution limit is at $6,000, however rollovers are not capped. Meaning the above mentioned 401 megabackdoor funds don&rsquo;t follow the limit. At age 50, you can contribute additional $1,000 a year. The limits are shared across Traditional and Roth IRAs.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s technically an income limit on Roth IRA contributions (MAGI of $140,000 single or $208,000 married), but Traditional IRA contributions can be rolled over into Roth IRA (<a href="https://www.irs.gov/publications/p590a#en_US_2020_publink1000230662">IRS.gov</a>), effectively nullifying the limit. This is referred to as &ldquo;IRA backdoor&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Just like with 401(k), Traditional IRA is tax-deferred: you get a tax refund for contributing to it, but you&rsquo;ll have to pay back those taxes on withdrawal. Roth IRA front loads the taxes, making earnings and withdrawals tax free.</p>

<p>Traditional IRA can be accessed at age 59 &frac12;. Roth IRA can be accessed either immediately upon reaching age 59 &frac12;, or after holding IRA account for 5 years. There&rsquo;s a 10% withdrawal penalty otherwise, and you must begin withdrawing Traditional IRA contributions by age 72 (Roth IRA doesn&rsquo;t have the mandatory withdrawal period).</p>

<h3>HSA</h3>

<p>Health Savings Account is another tax-advantaged investment, but it&rsquo;s not tied to the employer (however employers might choose to offer an HSA plan). HSA contribution limit is at $3,600 for 2021, which includes employer match if employer offers any. This can be increased by $1,000 if you&rsquo;re over the age of 55.</p>

<p>HSA is effectively tax-free, meaning that you don&rsquo;t pay when you contribute, nor do you pay when you withdraw (but there are caveats). HSA can be withdrawn to pay for qualified medical expenses without a penalty. Reimbursing for expenses does not have an expiration date, as long as the expense was incurred after your HSA was established. You can also withdraw HSA without qualified reasons once you hit the age 65 (which is higher than 59 &frac12; used for 401(k) and IRA).</p>

<h2>Early withdrawals</h2>

<p>Now that the basics are out of the way, let&rsquo;s discuss early withdrawals from each of these accounts.</p>

<h3>Traditional and Roth IRA</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look into IRAs first, since the most common way to access 401(k) funds early leverages IRA peculiarities.</p>

<h4>5-year rule</h4>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also heard the 5-year rule referred to as a &ldquo;Roth conversion ladder&rdquo;.</p>

<p>The most obvious candidate for early access is Roth IRA. Roth IRA contributions (money you put in), can be accessed at any time without a penalty or paying additional taxes. Roth IRA distributions (aka the principle, or the money you&rsquo;ve earned) can be accessed using what&rsquo;s referred to as a &ldquo;5-year rule&rdquo;.</p>

<p>There are confusingly three 5-year rules when it comes to IRAs, and even more confusingly we care about two of them (the <a href="https://www.irs.gov/publications/p590b#en_US_2020_publink100035552">third rule deals with beneficiaries</a>).</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.irs.gov/publications/p590b#en_US_2020_publink1000231061">first 5-year rule</a> lets us access Roth IRA distributions within 5 years of owning the Roth IRA account. Simply enough, if you&rsquo;ve had Roth IRA account for more than 5 years, you can access both the money you put in, and the money you&rsquo;ve earned.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.irs.gov/publications/p590b#en_US_2020_publink1000231065">second 5-year rule</a> covers rollovers. Rollovers from Traditional IRA or Roth 401(k) need to marinate for 5 years (per transaction) before being accessible. So if you converted between your Traditional IRA and Roth IRA twice &ndash; in 2021 and 2022 &ndash; you&rsquo;ll be able to access the money in 2026 and 2027 respectively.</p>

<p>This means that Roth IRA can be accessed if you hold the account for at least 5 years, and Traditional IRA can be converted to Roth IRA (a taxable event) and accessed penalty-free after 5 years.</p>

<p>For example, if you opened a Roth IRA account in 2015, and it&rsquo;s now 2021 &ndash; you can access all the funds at any time without paying taxes.</p>

<p>In a more complex example, you&rsquo;d convert the Traditional IRA to Roth IRA, and access the resulting money after 5 years:</p>

<ol>
<li>Convert a certain amount from Traditional IRA to Roth IRA</li>
<li>Pay taxes on the transaction</li>
<li>Wait 5 years (for each transaction)</li>
<li>Withdraw transaction amount + earnings</li>
</ol>


<p>This works out similarly for Roth 401(k) to Roth IRA conversion (but with less steps and without taxes):</p>

<ol>
<li>Convert any amount from Roth 401(k)</li>
<li>Wait 5 years</li>
<li>Withdraw transaction amount + earnings</li>
</ol>


<h4>72(t) SEPP</h4>

<p><a href="https://uscode.house.gov/view.xhtml?req=(title:26%20section:72%20edition:prelim)%20OR%20(granuleid:USC-prelim-title26-section72)&amp;f=treesort&amp;edition=prelim&amp;num=0&amp;jumpTo=true#substructure-location_t">72(t) SEPP</a> (Substantially Equal Periodic Payments) can be used to sign up for a payment plan from your Traditional IRA (technically you&rsquo;re able to use SEPP for your Roth IRA as well, but this will incur double taxes). This is quite a commitment, and you&rsquo;ll be receiving periodic payments from your IRA until you hit the age 59 &frac12; (or for 5 years, whichever is longest).</p>

<p>For a Traditional IRA example, you can sign up for SEPP to receive $5,000 annually. This means that each year (until you turn 59 &frac12; or 5 years passes &ndash; whichever is longest) you will pay taxes on those $5,000, and withdraw the difference.</p>

<p>Additionally, IRA can be used to pay for large medical expenses (within the same year), high education expenses, home-related expenses ($10,000 lifetime limit), and a few more niche cases.</p>

<h4>10% penalty</h4>

<p>10% penalty sounds large, but it&rsquo;s really not a terrible choice if the other options don&rsquo;t work (although I don&rsquo;t see why they wouldn&rsquo;t). Given the tax-advantage growth that these assets have been enjoying, 10% penalty is not a steep price to pay. Although understandably loss aversion kicks in, and either a 5-year rule or the 72(t) SEPP sound preferable to paying the penalty.</p>

<p>In case with the Traditional IRA, the penalty would have to be paid in addition to paying taxes on withdrawn amount. Roth IRA only imposes a penalty if you didn&rsquo;t wait for 5 years since the account creation or the rollover transaction.</p>

<h3>Traditional and Roth 401(k)</h3>

<p>401(k) can be accessed early (before the required 59 &frac12; age) in multiple ways. Both the 5-year rule (aka the Roth conversion ladder) and the 72(t) SEPP can be used to access 401(k) funds.</p>

<p>Roth conversion ladder leverages the ability to rollover Traditional 401(k) to Traditional IRA, and subsequently convert Traditional IRA to Roth IRA (a taxable event). Within the 5 years of that second conversion, you should be able to access the money.</p>

<p>For example, when getting ready for retirement, you may convert all your Traditional 401(k) balance to Traditional IRA. Then each year, you could do the following (this may look familiar from the above):</p>

<ol>
<li>Convert $5,000 from Traditional IRA to Roth IRA</li>
<li>Pay taxes on the transaction ($5,000)</li>
<li>Wait 5 years (for each transaction)</li>
<li>Withdraw transaction amount ($5,000)</li>
</ol>


<p>This works with Roth 401(k) to Roth IRA as well. It&rsquo;s simpler too, as Roth 401(k) to Roth IRA conversion is non-taxable. Convert Roth 401(k) to Roth IRA, wait 5 years, and withdraw at your own leisure.</p>

<h3>HSA</h3>

<p>As you may have guessed, HSA balance can also be accessed before the age 65. But it does come with a caveat.</p>

<p>You see, HSA allows you to pay for qualified medical expenses tax-free. No taxes on withdrawal, tax-free growth, and no taxes when paying out. However, these qualified medical expenses don&rsquo;t expire. As long as you had an HSA account at a time of medical expense occurring, you can get a refund on that medical payment.</p>

<p>This is something that we&rsquo;re doing &ndash; banking medical receipts (which isn&rsquo;t hard, given the overpriced American healthcare system) to cash in at a later date.</p>

<hr />

<p>There&rsquo;s a number of ways to access retirement accounts in the United States. Be it through Roth conversion ladder, 72(t) SEPP, or even by using old medical receipts. And now I have somewhere to look back to once I inevitably forget how any of this works.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How I write]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/how-i-write/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-30T16:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/how-i-write</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I don&rsquo;t blog consistently, and I&rsquo;m still struggling to find my voice. I find writing difficult for many reasons, especially when it comes to identifying topics worth writing about. I want to bring a combination of passion, expertise, and a fresh perspective into a topic &ndash; which makes finding a theme to cover challenging. To top it all off, English is my third language. Getting the content to flow well is difficult, and I don&rsquo;t always have the ear for it.</p>

<p>In contrast, I find it straightforward to write once I know what to write about. In part due to the volume of writing I have to do for work: as a technical lead at Google I routinely use extensive design documents to communicate my ideas. I also <a href="https://amzn.to/3fRV1OV">wrote a book</a> once.</p>

<p>I found a set of techniques that work well for me. I don&rsquo;t know if these techniques help me write higher quality material &ndash; you&rsquo;ll be the judge of that. But these techniques help me express ideas from my head and onto paper. Hopefully in a digestible and entertaining format.</p>

<hr />

<p>I never took journalism 101. Like with many things in live, I found my own way of doing things: why take an easy path, when a difficult one could work just as well?</p>

<p>I break down writing process into a set of distinct steps. I start with some preliminary research, write an outline, do my in-depth research, write a wine draft, turn that into a coffee draft, and finally proofread the result. I try to take breaks and get some distance from whatever I&rsquo;m working on in between these steps.</p>

<h2>Preliminary research</h2>

<p>This is a step zero, although it might not apply to everything I write about. This is a breadth-first, &ldquo;open as many tabs as computer can handle&rdquo; type of research. There&rsquo;s no in-depth reading at this point, and only high level information is consumed.</p>

<p>I picked up this approach from my wife, who is an indisputable queen of online research. I find it tempting to dig into the first source I find. Stopping myself from digging too deep helps me understand the information landscape.</p>

<p>For instance, when writing about <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/fire-in-a-developing-economy/">financial independence in Cote d&#8217;Ivoire</a> (a topic I know nothing about) my preliminary research consisted of: a brief review of country&rsquo;s history, a list of major geopolitical events, investment landscape, and identifying trustworthy sources which could tell me more about currency stability or tax situation.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve also looked for existing sources on the subject, but there wasn&rsquo;t any.</p>

<h2>Outline</h2>

<p>This post started with an outline. An outline is crucial to pacing and identifying areas of focus. Chapter summaries in a book, outlining headings in technical documents, or putting together a bulleted list for a blog post &ndash; you name it.</p>

<p>Outline only needs to make sense to you, and you don&rsquo;t have to use complete sentences. I started with the following outline for this post:</p>

<ul>
<li>I write a lot

<ul>
<li>Quantity doesn&rsquo;t mean quality</li>
<li>I don&rsquo;t publish most things I write</li>
<li>A lot of practice with technical docs</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Outline</li>
<li>Wine draft</li>
<li>Coffee draft</li>
</ul>


<p>An outline is not final, and it evolves as I write. For instance, by the time I wrote the bulk of this post, an outline evolved &ndash; something was removed, and a whole lot of things were added:</p>

<ul>
<li>I write a lot

<ul>
<li>Double down on how bad I am at writing

<ul>
<li>Quantity doesn&rsquo;t mean quality</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><del>I don&rsquo;t publish most things I write</del></li>
<li>A lot of practice with technical docs</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Preliminary research</li>
<li>Write an outline (you&rsquo;re here now!)</li>
<li>In-depth research</li>
<li>Write wine draft</li>
<li>Write coffee draft</li>
<li>Proofread the result</li>
</ul>


<p>I like to keep an outline on the screen as I write, as it reminds me to write in context. I often jot down a brief outline when I have ideas about writing something: this way I don&rsquo;t have to start from scratch when I sit down to write.</p>

<h2>In-depth research</h2>

<p>This is where I actually read through dozens of tabs I opened during the preliminary research. This is where I spend the most of my time for topics I don&rsquo;t feel particularly comfortable with.</p>

<p>I make a point to time box research tasks. It&rsquo;s easy to go down a rabbit hole when researching a topic, and there&rsquo;s always more to learn the more you understand the subject. Putting a time limit on each research topic helps me stay on track.</p>

<h2>Wine draft</h2>

<p>Step 4 out of 6: this is when I start writing.</p>

<p>I found it near impossible to write without separating creative stream of conciousness from the editing process. The &ldquo;wine draft&rdquo; is the first attempt at filling in the blanks. The grammar can be all wrong, and the sentences don&rsquo;t always have to make sense. It&rsquo;s not necessary for the content to flow or read nicely.</p>

<p>This is where the outline really helps, because writing top to bottom is generally very difficult. Filling in the blanks under the outline however is much easier. I often find myself jumping between different headings and writing a little bit here and there under each heading.</p>

<p>Prioritizing cadence during this step helps, as a stable writing rhythm helps me enter the state of flow. To stay in the flow, I have a wine draft authoring rule: no sentence-level editing. Moving paragraphs or headings around is fine, but changing sentences is generally not.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s the goal - get as much content out as possible, no matter how much the language rules get abused. I find it easier to edit down a boatload of content, rather than struggle to come up with the missing pieces when editing.</p>

<p>This is the stage when I decide if the content is not worth publishing &ndash; many of my wine drafts never see the light of day.</p>

<p>I find accompanying wine mandatory, but whiskey or tea works in a pinch.</p>

<h2>Coffee draft</h2>

<p>After the wine draft is complete, I take a break. Often couple of hours is enough to create a distance between me and the text. A coffee draft requires more focus and attention. This is when the messy draft takes shape and becomes (hopefully) readable. You tell me.</p>

<p>I make my way down, sentence by sentence, turning ramblings of a madman into a coherent narrative. I rearrange sentences, correct syntactic and grammatical errors, and liberally remove what doesn&rsquo;t contribute to the narrative. If the wine draft is particularly incoherent, I simply rewrite each paragraph one by one.</p>

<p>This is when I add illustrations if need be. A coffee draft is nearly the final result, barring typos and minor mistakes.</p>

<p>Coffee helps here, but, unlike with a wine draft, is not required.</p>

<h2>Proofreading</h2>

<p>The final step involves good old proofreading (unless you have a proofreader: it was great having one when working with a publisher).</p>

<p>I try to proofread in a different software suite, or with different fonts and colors: it helps create further distance between the content and I. For instance, I write this post in Vim using Markdown, but I proofread by reading the final preview using my blog&rsquo;s visual theme.</p>

<p>It often helps to read things out loud too: anything you can do to change up the way you perceive the text.</p>

<hr />

<p>And finally it&rsquo;s ready to be published: ta-da! This method hasn&rsquo;t failed me yet, be it for writing <a href="https://amzn.to/3fRV1OV">Mastering Vim</a>, technical design docs at Google, or blog posts like this one. Fingers crossed it&rsquo;ll continue working well for me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Abandoned project showcase: Hikaya]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/abandoned-project-showcase-hikaya/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-24T09:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/abandoned-project-showcase-hikaya</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Roguelikes are once niche, but an increasing mainstream video game genre. The genre is named after 1980 &ldquo;Rogue&rdquo; - a procedurally generated dungeon crawler. Rogue and games inspired by it often include simple ASCII graphics, feature procedural generation of the world, and include &ldquo;permadeath&rdquo;: the game is over once you die.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/rogue-1980.png" title="A screenshot of 1980 &amp;#34;Rogue&amp;#34; video game." alt="A screenshot of 1980 &amp;#34;Rogue&amp;#34; video game."></p>

<p>Many games were heavily inspired by it - like Ancient Domains of Mystery and Nethack, or more recent Cataclysm: DDA and Caves of Qud. Modern games bring a lot of fantastic fusion into the genre too with like The Binding of Isaac or Hades. But I digress.</p>

<p>A few months ago I was struck by a bout of inspiration. I&rsquo;ve tried countless times before, but never produced a complete video game &ndash; this was meant to be the time! I&rsquo;ve significantly reduced the scope, came up with a plan of action, and started coding!</p>

<p>I codenamed the game &ldquo;Hikaya&rdquo;, which means &ldquo;a fairy tale&rdquo; in Tatar - my native language (although I think the word itself has been borrowed from Arabic). I planned to make a fairly straightforward roguelike, without too many bells and whistles.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/hikaya-splash-screen.png" title="A screenshot of the main menu of Hikaya." ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve found a wonderful tutorial on rogueliketutorials.com, which introduces <code>libtcod</code> &ndash; a library to simplify the mundane: drawing on screen, handling input, field of view and lighting, pathfinding. I&rsquo;ve struggled through all of the above before, and knew that getting deep into the mechanical details would slow me down.</p>

<p>Alas, I didn&rsquo;t finish the game. I&rsquo;ve gotten maybe half way there, before my focus slipped away from the project. But not before getting some screenshots and documenting some interesting ideas I had!</p>

<p>The only contains a dozen dungeon levels, with a short story being told through item descriptions. The player is an adventurer who&rsquo;s sent by their village to a nearby cave to retrieve the last flame - a placeholder MacGuffin.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/hikaya-inventory.png" title="An inventory screen of Hikaya." ></p>

<p>Every item and monster posses a fantasy-sounding name, contrasted with a short, but colorful description hinting at a science fiction nature of the objects. Think magic scrolls with touch screens, or injectable health potions.</p>

<p>Each monster type has a unique behavior - with goblins running away and regrouping, ogres snacking on goblins to restore health, and so on.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/hikaya-goblin.png" title="A goblin running away for backup." ></p>

<p>As the player descends down the dungeon, they encounter multiple bosses guarding the staircases. The bosses drop unique armor pieces, which tell a story of a group of adventurers descending into the dungeon, but succumbing to traps, greed, and treachery.</p>

<p>Finally, a dragon guards the last light on the final floor. The game ends with the player becoming a dragon, and a cycle becomes anew.</p>

<p>I know, I know: edgy, uninspired &ndash; but I enjoyed the premise.</p>

<p>The combat is focused on tactical movement and avoiding damage, and the player unlocks new moves &ndash; like kicks, jumps, or faints &ndash; as they progress through the dungeon.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/hikaya-stunts.png" title="A screenshots of a stunt selector in Hikaya." ></p>

<p>I wanted to experiment with the health system. Inspired by FATE tabletop roleplaying system, I attempted to use health pools. The system was meant to keep combat dangerous and entertaining throughout the game by making even the goblins dangerous throughout the game.</p>

<p>My biggest experiment came from a health system. Inspired by FATE tabletop roleplaying ruleset, the health consists of multiple pools (as opposed to a single bar). The goal of the system is to make combat deadly, and create a sense of danger even for trivial encounters, while still leaving room for error.</p>

<p>Let me try to explain. For example, a player might have three health pools - for 1, 2, and 3 hit points each. Each time a player takes damage, the smallest pool is used to absorb that damage. For instance, a 2 damage hit voids the 2 hit point pool. A second 2 damage hit clears out the 3 hit point pool. A third 2 damage hit is fatal.</p>

<p>You can see the voided health pools marked as red on the screenshot below, and the full health pools in green:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/hikaya-damage.png" title="A screenshots of a player taking damage in Hikaya." ></p>

<p>To complicate thing further, I give players some leeway by slowly draining partially damaged pools over time. For instance, if the player uses their 5 hit point pool to absorb 2 points of damage, I&rsquo;ll slowly drain that pool over the next three turns. This would let the player take another 2 damage hit (or a few 1 damage hits) &ldquo;for free&rdquo; immediately after being hit. You can see those hearts marked as yellow on the screenshot above.</p>

<p>Needless to say, the system turned out to be very convoluted to explain in game (and on paper too &ndash; I don&rsquo;t think the above is clear enough). I still think it&rsquo;s a great idea, but it desperately needs better user experience design to make it accessible. In fact, FATE itself got rid of confusing health pools in it&rsquo;s latest &ldquo;FATE Condensed&rdquo; release, simplifying health down to binary hit markers.</p>

<p>Despite not finishing it, putting together Hikaya was a fun experience. I&rsquo;ve had a great time working on the prototype: I&rsquo;ve learned a lot, and maybe I&rsquo;ll lead my next video game project to completion given everything I&rsquo;ve learned!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FIRE in a developing economy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/fire-in-a-developing-economy/"/>
    <updated>2021-05-07T14:18:06-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/fire-in-a-developing-economy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My wife&rsquo;s cousin recently moved to Cote d&#8217;Ivoire, and our latest conversation centered around financial independence and early retirement. The topic is also known under the trendy term &ldquo;FIRE&rdquo;. You may have heard about it as &ldquo;those darn milenials retiring in their 30s&rdquo;.</p>

<p>A lot of the advice I&rsquo;m familiar with is US-centric (or covering Canada, Australia, EU countries, and so on). I couldn&rsquo;t find adequate resources for pursuing financial independence in emergent economies. I tried to research this subject, and here&rsquo;s what I came up with.</p>

<p>This one&rsquo;s mostly for you, Myriam &ndash; as a follow-up to our conversation.</p>

<h2>A pre-disclaimer</h2>

<p>I refer to &ldquo;developing&rdquo; economies in this article. I&rsquo;m using this term interchangeably with low and middle-income countries, countries with emerging markets, or pre-industrialized countries. None of those classifiers are strictly defined either. This can be a controversial term, but I hope the reader will bear with me and focus on the primary goal of this article - financial independence outside of countries like the United States, Canada, Australia, UK, and others.</p>

<h2>&ldquo;The&rdquo; disclaimer</h2>

<p>Before I dig in, I want to shine light on my credentials for this article: I don&rsquo;t have any. I immigrated to the US at age 18. Before that I lived in Russia (which is often considered a developing economy). However I&rsquo;ve never gotten a chance to become financially savvy in the country. Never held a full-time job outside of the USA.</p>

<p>My wife an I diversify into developing markets (and it&rsquo;s less than 20% of our portfolio). We don&rsquo;t have any inherent knowledge or in-depth understanding of emerging markets.</p>

<p>And I sure as hell don&rsquo;t know what it&rsquo;s like to live in a pre-industrialized country.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m bringing a perspective of a person who&rsquo;s familiar with financial independence and early retirement in the United States (and vaguely Canada). This piece is a compilation of about 10 hours of research (give or take), with my own context applied to it.</p>

<p>This is not a professional financial advice, and I&rsquo;ll be making culturally or economically ignorant statements about many countries. Read while having a tub filled with salt nearby.</p>

<h2>Working to death</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s a strong reason why the United States is a birthplace of FIRE movement as a media phenomenon. Limited worker protections, no government mandated vacation days or holidays, no maternity leave, low social security pension &ndash; you name it.</p>

<p>In fact, according to <a href="https://respect.international/ituc-global-rights-index-2018-the-worlds-worst-countries-for-workers-map/">2018 ITUC worker rights index</a>, the United States is placed in &ldquo;Systematic violations of rights&rdquo; category. But this is where the first caveat comes in. A major chunk of emerging economies hold a &ldquo;No guarantee of rights&rdquo; or a &ldquo;No guarantee of rights due to breakdown of the law&rdquo; rating. Make of that what you will.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s the cultural aspect to an overwhelming desire to escape workforce: it&rsquo;s common to live for the weekend in the States. Culturally life is often put on pause Monday through Friday. Enjoying life two days out of seven can be draining.</p>

<p>In the EU, one might take two months off (okay, not quite: 28 legally mandated days off + 7 weekends in between = 42 days). In the States (Canada, Australia, etc) you work to death, and getting out of the rat race is a priority.</p>

<p>This is where I need another disclaimer: I quite like living in the United States. I just think it&rsquo;s worker protections are shit and should be improved.</p>

<p>Of course the United States and the likes don&rsquo;t have a patent on working long hours or having workers protection. But there&rsquo;s a reason why FIRE is prevalent in the industrialized world (in contrast to developing nations). One word: &ldquo;stability&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Stability</h2>

<p>Despite the popularity of FIRE in the United States, similar formula applies for achieving financial independence in the rest of the industrialized nations. And there&rsquo;s a constant across those countries: stability.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s as simple as that. To ensure your financial future you need to plot and plan ahead. You can&rsquo;t plan effectively in an unstable landscape. Currency hyperinflation or hyperdeflation, risk of regime and major law changes, corruption and nepotism.</p>

<p>When considering financial independence within developing nations, it&rsquo;s important to acknowledge and asses the stability of the economy, currency, and political regime. These constants are treated as somewhat of a given in many FIRE conversations, but most recommendations and arguments quickly fall apart when faced with a lack of stability.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no recipe for dealing with a lack of stability, but hedging against it would likely have to be a key part of one&rsquo;s financial independence strategy. I found a few things that are worth considering &ndash; and I&rsquo;m sure there are many more aspects that escaped my surface-level investigation.</p>

<h2>The FIRE recipe</h2>

<p>In it&rsquo;s core FIRE comes down to three principles: increase income, decrease expenses, and invest the difference.</p>

<p>Decreasing expenses is simple, but not easy. Increasing income is hard work that pays off if successful: drastic income increase helps speed FIRE along. Investing the difference carries significant risks due to aforementioned lack of stability.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m going to dive into all three principles, but regardless of plans for retirement, building up an emergency fund is always the first priority in nearly every financial conversation. Let&rsquo;s talk about that first.</p>

<h2>Parking cash</h2>

<p>The first question you might get asked when talking about FIRE is &ldquo;do you have an emergency fund?&rdquo;. There&rsquo;s always a straightforward recommendation of having N months worth of living expenses in a savings account. Of course this blanket advice breaks down the moment we discuss developing economies.</p>

<p>Lack of faith in the currency or the government puts savings accounts under question. Granted, banks in the developing nations are quick to offer high interest accounts. You might get a 20% return on investment, only to realize that the currency lost 25% of its value in a year.</p>

<p>If the country allows for holding foreign currency, foreign currency could be used to hedge against that. The United States dollar is the most widely held reserve currency. Euro is pegged by 19 countries, making it a relatively stable bet as well. Japanese Yen (JPY) is the third most commonly used reserve currency.</p>

<h3>Real estate</h3>

<p>I titled this section &ldquo;Parking cash&rdquo; and not &ldquo;Emergency fund&rdquo; because I wanted to mention an alternative to savings accounts often used in developing economies. Real estate.</p>

<p>While not a place for storing emergency funds, longer term reserves are often held in what&rsquo;s perceived as the most stable asset &ndash; real estate. Due to a significantly lower cost of labor it&rsquo;s common (and is often sensible) to purchase land, and then build on that land.</p>

<p>Although lower risk than other asset classes, it&rsquo;s worth examining potential for asset seizure. 1980&rsquo;s land redistribution in Zimbabwe is the prime example of this. Less stable political systems are at a higher risk for similar events.</p>

<p>Non-primary residence (that is: a house you don&rsquo;t live in) can be used as an investment &ndash; either through having tenants, or through an act of reselling. Investment through real estate is work, and it&rsquo;s the type of work I don&rsquo;t think I would enjoy. I haven&rsquo;t researched anything on the subject and will zoom past real estate and  onto another topic.</p>

<h2>Earn more</h2>

<p>Increased income is an important pillar of reaching financial independence. This is where you say:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/what-an-idea.png" title="A screenshot from &amp;#34;The Simpsons&amp;#34; of a man smacking his forehead. The text reads &amp;#34;My goodness, what an idea! Why didn't I think of that&amp;#34;." alt="A screenshot from &amp;#34;The Simpsons&amp;#34; of a man smacking his forehead. The text reads &amp;#34;My goodness, what an idea! Why didn't I think of that&amp;#34;."></p>

<p>I work in a highly specialized (and therefore well paid) field. I can talk all I want about saving and investment, but without the high earner salary, stock grants, and financial benefits my job provides - it would take me decades to get where it takes me years.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s possible to ensure your financial future with a lower income. It&rsquo;s much, much harder.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s a significant luck element involved, and I&rsquo;m not interested in peddling the &ldquo;work hard and you&rsquo;ll be rich&rdquo; narrative. Load of bullshit if you ask me. There are however concrete steps one can take. These steps could open up the right opportunities.</p>

<p>Increasing earning potential is a massive boon in the FIRE world. Directing energy towards this goal might be a higher priority step compared to everything else I wrote about.</p>

<p>The most straightforward way to increase earning potential is through education (either formal or informal). College, university, books, online courses. If formal education is problematic, some industries (e.g. software engineering) are more open to self-taught professionals than others. Yours truly is a good example of that.</p>

<p>Networking is another avenue to pursue. It might be more difficult in certain nations due to inherent nepotism and lack of opportunities.</p>

<p>In fact, many developing countries make vertical mobility problematic due to corruption. In an increasingly connected world, earning internationally could be a feasible way forward to increasing income. That is if you have skills that are worth paying for.</p>

<h2>Spend less</h2>

<p>Another &ldquo;duh&rdquo; topic, reducing your spending in proportion to income is crucial in achieving any type of financial freedom.</p>

<p>Expense reduction is very much a country-specific topic. In fact, it&rsquo;s highly specific to individuals. Analyzing expenses and putting together a budget is a strong first step. Thankfully, reducing expenses is something commonly covered in media, with plenty of literature available around the globe. That, and this is something financial professionals frequently focus on.</p>

<p>A blanket advice I heard for expatriates living in another country is to avoid expat-friendly stores. Those often come with a premium, and shopping locally might reduce expenses significantly. That&rsquo;s an extent of my knowledge on the subject.</p>

<h2>Invest</h2>

<p>&ldquo;Earn more, spend less, invest the difference&rdquo;. Generally &ldquo;invest the difference&rdquo; portion of the advice implies investing in mutual funds &ndash; a mix of stocks and bonds for a set of companies. But as you&rsquo;ve come to expect in this piece, this advice comes with caveats when living in a developing nation.</p>

<p>General advice for investment into mutual funds is holding a 60/40 split of US/international assets. This represents the weight of the US-based stock and bond market in respect to the rest of the world.</p>

<p>But some countries might not allow for international investments. Some countries might introduce additional taxes on foreign investments. Or investments into certain markets could be made difficult due to local regulations. US in particular makes it more difficult for non-Americans to invest, introducing a number of hoops to jump through for identity verification.</p>

<p>To dig deeper, let&rsquo;s investigate Cote d&#8217;Ivoire as an example - a country Myriam is living in.</p>

<p>Quick history recap of Cote d&#8217;Ivoire, a former French colony in West Africa. After gaining independence in 1960, the country enjoyed relative stability until 1999. A military coup led to an economic downturn, and two civil wars followed in 2002 and 2011. 2020 presidential election has resulted in unrest.</p>

<p>From those dates alone, political stability in the region at the moment seems problematic.</p>

<p>On the flip side of the coin, Cote d&#8217;Ivoire has the benefit of being a member of ECOWAS: Economic Community of West African States. This increases economic stability of the country, by pegging it&rsquo;s economy (and currency) against it&rsquo;s neighbors.</p>

<p>This is a nice bonus to economical stability of the region.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve established that blanket investment advice might not exactly work with developing economies. A few questions come to mind:</p>

<ul>
<li>What are the restrictions on holding foreign currency or investments?</li>
<li>How stable is the currency?</li>
<li>What is the tax situation like?</li>
</ul>


<p>Let&rsquo;s dig into each one.</p>

<h3>Foreign assets</h3>

<p>For financial independence, we&rsquo;ll want to reduce risks where possible. This means hedging against a single country&rsquo;s economy.Supporting local economy by investing in a regional stock market is responsible (please do!), but diversification is the name of the game. For a complete portfolio you&rsquo;ll likely want to hold international stocks and bonds.</p>

<p>Certain countries either might not allow, or make it extremely difficult to hold foreign investments.</p>

<p>In Cote d&#8217;Ivoire, there doesn&rsquo;t seem to be any restrictions on holding foreign assets. That&rsquo;s a plus. Quick online search didn&rsquo;t bring up a history of restrictions on ownership of foreign assets either.</p>

<p>Finding a broker that operates in the country of choice (or allows for investment from said country) would be a next step here.</p>

<h3>Local currency</h3>

<p>Cote d&#8217;Ivoire uses West African CFA franc &ndash; a French treasury backed currency with a fixed CFA/Euro exchange rate. Political controversy aside, Euro pegged currency offers stability that many developing countries might lack.</p>

<p>To look at currency stability, we can look at an inflation rate or an exchange rate against other currencies. For instance here&rsquo;s how many CFA a single USD would buy (from 2003 to 2021):</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/usd-to-cfa.png" title="A chart with a USD to CFA exchange rate chart with exchange rate per 1 USD staying roughly within 400-600 CFA." ></p>

<p>In contrast to that, some quick research surfaces official discussions for introducing &ldquo;Eco&rdquo; &ndash; a non-French backed currency for the West African region. While this could result in higher economical growth potential for the region, it comes with more risk.</p>

<h3>Taxation</h3>

<p>Tax laws change how you invest. Our FIRE strategy is carefully crafted to leverage every tax-advantaged account possible: a good third of our assets is held in tax-advantaged accounts. And of course tax laws vary by country.</p>

<p>This is definitely the place where you want to bring in a professional. A quick search (and that&rsquo;s the keyword: &ldquo;quick&rdquo;) indicates that Cote d&#8217;Ivoire has 1.5% salary tax, and 1.5% - 10% &ldquo;national contribution&rdquo;. Cote d&#8217;Ivoire taxes capital gains, dividends and securities. There&rsquo;s pension both your employer and you pay into, which is nice.</p>

<p>There are likely country-specific tax law peculiarities one can take advantage of to optimize asset growth. This would require much more in-depth research.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Financial independence becomes a completely different beast in developing nations. Whatever little financial knowledge I have is challenged if not outright rendered useless when applied to emerging markets.</p>

<p>Yet there are a lot of directions for future research, and this piece only presents a view through a very much United-States-tinted lens. It could be that FIRE in developing countries might leverage creating a business and using more active forms of income generation.</p>

<p>Many of my findings are superficial, and I touched on a lot of different topics without going in-depth into any one of them. I can dedicate more time to this topic if there&rsquo;s interest - let me know in the comments.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Savings rate plotted over 8 years]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/savings-rate-plotted-over-8-years/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-30T09:31:17-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/savings-rate-plotted-over-8-years</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just found my financial records going back to 2013!</p>

<p>I know that doesn&rsquo;t sound exciting, but for someone who loves putting together spreadsheets this is a treasure trove of information! Well, maybe not a trove, but a sizable chunk of data. I only have two numbers for each month &ndash; income and expenses. But that&rsquo;s just enough to calculate my savings rate!</p>

<p><code>(income - expenses) / income = savings rate</code></p>

<p>With this number I can trace a broad outline through the past 8 years of my financial life! I present my savings rate charted over the past 8 years:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/savings-rate-1.png" title="A trend of my savings rate from August 2013 to February 2021. It shows a steady growth from effectively a 0% savings rate in 2013, 75% in early 2017, dips to 50% throughout 2017, and a steady 75% savings rate from 2018 onward." ></p>

<p><em>It&rsquo;s smoothed out using a 6 period rolling window, as it&rsquo;s near impossible to see trends when plotting raw numbers.</em></p>

<p>This chart tells a life story: starting with a near 0% savings rate in early 2014, a dip in 2017, and a steady 75% from 2018 onward. Let&rsquo;s trace my major life events!</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/savings-rate-2.png" title="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;Silicon Valley job&amp;#34; label hovering over January 2013 mark, with a savings rate at 0% preceding a climb to 25%." alt="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;Silicon Valley job&amp;#34; label hovering over January 2013 mark, with a savings rate at 0% preceding a climb to 25%."></p>

<p>By the end of 2013 I lived in downtown Philly and was working as a freelance software developer. Per-project pay was decent, but the gaps between contracts reduced the overall income. That, and being a sole breadwinner for a family of two &ndash; the funds were running dry and we were living paycheck-to-paycheck.</p>

<p>My then-SO and I had different financial upbringing. My ex-wife and I were both young when we got married, and we&rsquo;ve never sat down and talked about finance &ndash; so I could only guess as to what her relationship with money was. I came from a household of a frugal single mother &ndash; we were never short on cash, but the expenses were low. In a rural community food was grown in a large garden, milk bartered from a neighbor, sweaters knitted.</p>

<p>I distinctly remember my partner  not having more than a couple of hundred dollars in a bank account when we moved in together. On the other hand, by the time we got married I amassed a nest egg - nearly $20,000. Granted, it&rsquo;s small in the grand scheme of things &ndash; but these were the savings I put together from working low wage jobs &ndash; before I learned software development.</p>

<p>You can see us deplete that fund by the end of 2013 and into early 2014. And paycheck-to-paycheck we lived.</p>

<p>In January 2014 I was offered a position with a software company in the Silicon Valley. Things were looking up for our financial life! My then-wife and I moved to a Bay Area suburb.</p>

<p>It took some adjusting after living in downtown Philly. Both our income and expenses increased. Thankfully with the new job we found it harder to keep up with the increasing income: that&rsquo;s where we settled for the 25% savings rate. A balance between frugality and spending habits.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/savings-rate-3.png" title="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;divorce, raise, car living&amp;#34; label hovering over October 2015 mark, with a savings rate at 25% preceding a climb to 75%." alt="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;divorce, raise, car living&amp;#34; label hovering over October 2015 mark, with a savings rate at 25% preceding a climb to 75%."></p>

<p>A marital disaster struck at the end of 2015: my now ex-wife and I split up. What was a downturn in life turned out to be a financial upturn for me. My ex moved back with her parents, and I stayed in the apartment we were renting.</p>

<p>In a bout of coincidental timing, the apartment complex I lived in was scheduled for demolition. I had to move out and look for a new place. Instead, I decided to move into my car. <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-in-a-car-for-5000-miles/">I wrote about that in detail before</a>, if you&rsquo;d like to read about that.</p>

<p>This is when I became interested in the FIRE movement. If you&rsquo;re not familiar, &ldquo;FIRE&rdquo; stands for &ldquo;Financial Independence, Retire Early&rdquo; (I like to think everyone is aware that this is a terrible acronym). The idea is to increase income, drastically decrease expenses, and invest the difference into index funds to live off of indefinitely.</p>

<p>Now that I had an idea where my money can work best, I had an easier time justifying increasing my savings rate. FIRE also turned increasing savings rate into somewhat of a game.</p>

<p>Finally, I negotiated a chunky raise at work. I was underpaid by the Silicon Valley standards, and &ldquo;I like working here, but I need to be paid X or I quit&rdquo; tactics worked. Having a reputation for being a high performer no doubt helped.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not surprising that as a culmination of those events, this is where you can see my savings rate beginning it&rsquo;s climb to a respectable 75%. Occasional spousal support would bump up the expenses, but not having rent to pay and a higher salary made it easy to absorb those expenses.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/savings-rate-4.png" title="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;new place&amp;#34; label hovering over November 2016 mark, with a savings rate at 75% preceding a dip into 50%. A &amp;#34;FIRE reignited&amp;#34; label hovers over August 2017 mark, preceding savings rate climb to 75%." alt="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;new place&amp;#34; label hovering over November 2016 mark, with a savings rate at 75% preceding a dip into 50%. A &amp;#34;FIRE reignited&amp;#34; label hovers over August 2017 mark, preceding savings rate climb to 75%."></p>

<p>By the end of 2016 I got my dream job at Google, and moved into a new studio apartment. No, the big dip isn&rsquo;t just a new place, but it&rsquo;s strongly connected. I decided to make up for a year of living out of a single suitcase. There&rsquo;s furnishing the new place from scratch, top of the line gaming PC, a VR headset, and so many things I didn&rsquo;t need! I definitely went on a bender.</p>

<p>It took me a year to slow down. This is also where my then-girlfriend and now-forever-housemate became more open with me financially: I happened to meet another FIRE enthusiast out in the wild, completely by chance. She reignited my desire to live frugally. End of 2017 was marked by me donating and selling an ungodly amount of things I accumulated over this year, and returning to comfortable living within (or below, depending on how you look at it) my needs.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/savings-rate-5.png" title="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;moving in&amp;#34; label hovering over August 2018 mark, with a steady 75% savings rate onward. A &amp;#34;marriage&amp;#34; label hovers over September 2020 mark." alt="The same image as described above, with a &amp;#34;moving in&amp;#34; label hovering over August 2018 mark, with a steady 75% savings rate onward. A &amp;#34;marriage&amp;#34; label hovers over September 2020 mark."></p>

<p>We moved in together by the end of 2018 and married in 2020. We still keep separate accounts for ease of accounting, and this chart only displays my data for the sake of my partner&rsquo;s privacy (it&rsquo;s less work to chart too). Overlaying my SO&rsquo;s data after combining our finances doesn&rsquo;t meaningfully change the numbers you see above.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s not realistic for us to push the savings rate higher without sacrificing the luxuries we enjoy - like travel or occasional high end dining. So here we are, at a comfortable 75% to 80% savings rate.</p>

<p>My wife and I earn 7 times more than I did when I was a sole breadwinner. Our joint expenses are 60% higher than what my ex wife and I spent 8 years ago. Both my wife and I are in a priviliged position to be high earners in a high paying industry. We&rsquo;ve gotten extremely lucky where many wouldn&rsquo;t have.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s no real purpose to this post other than sharing my journey. Hope you found something of interest!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living at work]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-at-work/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-13T09:34:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-at-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first remote work experience coincided with my self-employment as a contractor. I was building a copyright enforcement service for a client in a year 2013. I lived in a one bedroom apartment in Philadelphia with my now ex-wife &ndash; a few blocks away from the city hall. I worked at a small standing desk (trendy!) in a corner of our little bedroom - by the closet.</p>

<p>I worked from the early morning and deep into the night at that desk. Sometimes I would look out of the window behind me. I would see an uninspired urban picture of roof tops of other four story colonial homes. And after a moment of respite it was back to work for me.</p>

<p>This was my first major foray into the world of self-accountability: I meticulously tracked the time spent working, billed the client per hour, provided in-depth breakdowns. The more I worked, the more I could bill the client &ndash; I had the incentive to put in as much time into work as possible.</p>

<p>So I did. I clocked in 80 to 90 hours of billable time a week. The checks with a before unheard of hourly rate kept coming, so I kept putting in the hours. Neither I nor my significant other had major professional experience. (To be completely honest we didn&rsquo;t have much in the realm of like experience either). We kept on keeping on.</p>

<p>I thought about work during lunch. I was agonizing over the details when walking through the neighboring Rittenhouse Square. I would jump into late night coding sessions. As a young professional, I didn&rsquo;t see the need to draw lines between my work and my life &ndash; my life was my work. There was no &ldquo;me&rdquo; without work.</p>

<p>That is until I burnt out. I woke up one morning, and something inside me snapped. I realized that I couldn&rsquo;t spend another minute in front of the screen. I took a day off, and the feeling wouldn&rsquo;t pass. I felt numb and overwhelmed at the same time. A day filled with my favorite video games - and I still felt that way. A day at a museum - nothing. I didn&rsquo;t get better.</p>

<p>I invoked a force majeure clause in my contract. I transferred all the materials, sent the final invoice, and stepped away from the project.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t talk here about the ways to fight burnout, because I didn&rsquo;t know how to. I quit, took a break, and eventually moved onto another job. By the virtue of this happening early in my career, and me being rather young - I managed to &ldquo;snap out of it&rdquo; between jobs.</p>

<p>I wish I could share &ldquo;the one thing&rdquo; I did that helped - but there wasn&rsquo;t one. I don&rsquo;t remember how I took care of myself, and how I managed to get my head straight. All I remember that I felt discombobulated for weeks. And at some point the feeling went away. I couldn&rsquo;t work during that time.</p>

<p>Time passed. I moved across the country to the San Francisco Bay area for a job with Google. My now ex-wife and I split up &ndash; it was a civil, but nonetheless a difficult divorce.</p>

<p>Around that time, I spent a year traveling across the United States. I lived out of my car and stayed in hotels while working remotely on my own terms. I established strict working hours and routines.</p>

<p>I would start my work around 8 am, without paying mind to the timezone I&rsquo;d be in. I&rsquo;d work out of coffee shops, coworking spaces, or even campgrounds. I&rsquo;d always take a break for lunch. I&rsquo;d wrap up work at 4 pm, and not a minute longer. Constant travel and change of scenery encouraged me to keep to my work hours. I had to weigh in staying past my end of workday versus going out and sight seeing a new city. The wanderlust always won.</p>

<p>The work was out of my mind after 4 pm. That was easy to do with an adventure afoot, but years later and the habit stuck with me. I don&rsquo;t let thoughts about work slip into my day to day. My mind is my own outside of work.</p>

<p>That was a transformative experience, and it changed the way I see work. I know it&rsquo;s trendy to say this, but I don&rsquo;t live to work: I work to live.</p>

<p>Today, I work with some people who have never worked remotely before the pandemic. And I often hear a similar sounding sentiment: &ldquo;never again&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It makes me think about the time I was self-employed for the first time. Putting in 80 hour work weeks, and not having the awareness to understand how I was affecting myself and people around me. It created distance between me and my partner. I let the work spill into the time I had. In a way it made me less of an employee and less of person.</p>

<p>When the pandemic started I looked back to these memories. Google moved to continuous work from home model in March 2020. And I made a conscious effort not to slip into my early remote work days. I established a strict routine. Breakfast and lunch with my significant other (here&rsquo;s some closure to my divorce). No deviation from &ldquo;9 to 5&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I established an area for myself to work in &ndash; I bought a sturdy desk and a chair from a used office furniture reseller. I make an effort to create not only mental, but physical separation from work. I wear office clothes during the day, and change once I&rsquo;m done with work. I cook to distress after a long day. My partner and I adhere to scheduled date nights (we do leave room for spontaneity too).</p>

<p>That isn&rsquo;t to say I didn&rsquo;t slip over the past year: many times I stayed past an established time. I often started earlier than planned. And some days I would let work occupy my mind space as I&rsquo;m relaxing with my better half. We&rsquo;ve spent the past year working out of a one bedroom apartment. A bigger one than I worked out of 7 years ago, but still a one bedroom. It was difficult, and some days it still is.</p>

<p>But time and time again, I corrected the course and resumed my routine. During my soul searching adventure remote work was fun. Because this time working remotely is much harder. There are no sights to see. No new places to stay in. No novelty to look towards at the end of the day. Working from home in the middle of a pandemic is oh-so-difficult.</p>

<p>To be honest I can&rsquo;t wait to be back in the office. But I&rsquo;m also excited to work from home on my own terms. Because this isn&rsquo;t what remote work is like.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How much does writing a book earn?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/how-much-does-writing-a-book-earn/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-07T18:30:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/how-much-does-writing-a-book-earn</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I write about Vim &ndash; a modal text editor &ndash; <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/vim">a lot</a>. In fact, in early 2018
I was approached by <a href="https://packtpub.com">Packt Publishing</a> &ndash; what I&rsquo;ve later learned to be a
&ldquo;quantity over quality&rdquo; publishing house. Over the next 6 to 9 months I wrote a
300-page <a href="https://amzn.to/3wBeTx4">&ldquo;Mastering Vim&rdquo;</a>.</p>

<p>It was a stressful endeavour, with a publisher rushing to meet internal
deadlines and eventually sending an unfinished draft to print. There were many
highlights too, like actually cranking out 300 pages of material, or getting to
work with Bram Moolenaar &ndash; the creator of Vim himself. Now that a few years
have passed and the book is at its 3rd edition, complete, and re-released &ndash;
I&rsquo;m a lot more happy with the result.</p>

<p>I can write a whole other essay about my experience working with the publisher,
but that&rsquo;s a horror story for another time.</p>

<p>I didn&rsquo;t write to make money, but it&rsquo;s nice seeing a couple of hundred dollars
trickling in every quarter. Putting together spreadhseets is my favorite past
time, so here&rsquo;s a breakdown of my earnings from the time I wrote a book with
Packt.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/mastering-vim-amazon.png" title="A screenshot of &amp;#34;Mastering Vim&amp;#34; on Amazon.com." alt="A screenshot of &amp;#34;Mastering Vim&amp;#34; on Amazon.com."></p>

<p>As of April 2021, the English version of my book has 14 reviews on Amazon
averaging at 5 stars (that&rsquo;s more than I would hope for), which likely helps
keep the sales at a somewhat of a steady level.</p>

<p>I was signed into a default &ldquo;16% of net receipts&rdquo; contract, with a $2,000
advance given out to me. The advance was split into 5 milestone-based
installments: the first preliminary draft, 6 preliminary drafts, the remaining
preliminary drafts, the final drafts, and the publication. Although I didn&rsquo;t
urgently need the money, and the publisher may have just sent it as a bulk
$2,000 payment after the publication.</p>

<p>Eventually I received a PDF for the first quarter of my book being sold&hellip; And
here are the financials for Q4 2018:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Print # </th>
<th> Print $ </th>
<th> E-books # </th>
<th> E-books $ </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 10      </td>
<td> $55.50  </td>
<td> 274       </td>
<td> $307.70   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>A whopping 363 dollars and 20 cents in royalties! I didn&rsquo;t really think anyone
would be interested to read the book, so seeing 284 copies sold I was pretty
ecstatic!</p>

<p>Selling printed books seems to pay $5.55 per copy, while e-books only bring me
$1.12.</p>

<p>Now I didn&rsquo;t see any of that money, since I would have to &ldquo;pay back&rdquo; the
advance. I know it&rsquo;s called &ldquo;the advance&rdquo;, and I knew that I won&rsquo;t be getting
that first check in the mail &ndash; but it sucked a bit nonetheless.</p>

<p>After that I received some great news &ndash; my book was going to get
<a href="https://amzn.to/3fN7mFz">translated to Japanese</a>! During my last trip to Tokyo I made some friends
who were interested in Vim as much as I was, and one of them - Masafumi Okura -
decided to translate &ldquo;Mastering Vim&rdquo; into his native language. The legend found
close to three dozen mistakes in my book too, and is solely responsible for the
third edition of Mastering Vim!</p>

<p>Turns out the translation rights are expensive, and I&rsquo;m getting my cut as well
&ndash; $1,586.26! That&rsquo;s more than the first quarter of sales!</p>

<p>Packt advertised my book for a few months or so, but they seemed to have
quickly lost interest. I received my first 5 star review on Amazon though,
which was great! I spent the next month refreshing Amazon reviews daily, after
realizing that to be a path to acquiring a mental illness.</p>

<p>2019 came, and here are my next 4 quarterly statements:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Quarter      </th>
<th> Print # </th>
<th> Print $ </th>
<th> E-books # </th>
<th> E-books $ </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 2019 Q1      </td>
<td> 29      </td>
<td> $141.89 </td>
<td> 202       </td>
<td> $337.49   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2019 Q2      </td>
<td> 15      </td>
<td> $77.53  </td>
<td> 71        </td>
<td> $194.26   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2019 Q3      </td>
<td> 19      </td>
<td> $100.09 </td>
<td> 57        </td>
<td> $207.68   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2019 Q4      </td>
<td> 23      </td>
<td> $118.55 </td>
<td> 117       </td>
<td> $255.17   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>I sold 86 print books and 447 e-books in 2019. You can see the higher numbers
correspond to seasonal sales. Notice the prices for Q3 and Q4. E-books sold in
Q3 pay me as much as $3.64 per copy, while in Q1 it&rsquo;s a meager $1.67 per book.
Print edition payout stays much more consistent.</p>

<p>Altogether, I earned $1432.66 from my first full year of selling &ldquo;Mastering
Vim&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Here are my 2020 earnings:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Quarter      </th>
<th> Print # </th>
<th> Print $ </th>
<th> E-books # </th>
<th> E-books $ </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> 2020 Q1      </td>
<td> 26      </td>
<td> $131.61 </td>
<td> 112       </td>
<td> $414.12   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2020 Q2      </td>
<td> 22      </td>
<td> $106.67 </td>
<td> 77        </td>
<td> $379.61   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2020 Q3      </td>
<td> 26      </td>
<td> $141.17 </td>
<td> 74        </td>
<td> $325.97   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> 2020 Q4      </td>
<td> 45      </td>
<td> $236.69 </td>
<td> 166       </td>
<td> $458.07   </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>That&rsquo;s $1,533.38, a $100 more than in 2019. The patterns seem rather
predictable, with Q2 and Q3 being slow, and Q1 and Q4 displaying a noticeable
spike.</p>

<p>Finally, Packt offers service subscriptions &ndash; I believe the subscription is for
the courses they offer, but I can&rsquo;t say for sure. Payout per subscription is
small, and I&rsquo;ve earned $158.10 over the 9 quarters since publishing &ldquo;Mastering
Vim&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Across $3,329.24 in book sales, $1,586.26 in translation fees, and $158.10 in
subscriptions, this adds up to $5,073.60 over the 2+ years the book has been in
print. Looks like it can make for a decent supplemental income if you write
enough books, but I&rsquo;m saying that based on a sample size of one.</p>

<p>Throughout this time, my earnings per copy average at $5.16 for a print, and
$1.93 for an e-book (using weighted averages for quarterly sales).</p>

<p>And here&rsquo;s the last number in this post &ndash; this one purely for fun. Based on
the 16% royalty rate, Packt probably earned $31,710 from &ldquo;Mastering Vim&rdquo; so
far.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The feedback fallacy]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-feedback-fallacy/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-05T18:32:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-feedback-fallacy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After learning about <a href="https://amzn.to/3ukVvm5">&ldquo;Radical Candor&rdquo;</a>, I became obsessed with providing candid and compassionate feedback. I&rsquo;ve been especially focused on the ability to communicate areas of growth for individual on my team.</p>

<p>And then a colleague of mine shared <a href="https://hbr.org/2019/03/the-feedback-fallacy">&ldquo;The Feedback Fallacy&rdquo;</a> (published in the Harvard Business Review), which points to some research and outlines a few key problems why focusing on negative feedback might not be the best choice. Research shows that:</p>

<ul>
<li>people are bad at assessing other people</li>
<li>we learn best with positive reinforcement</li>
<li>focusing on shortcomings impairs learning</li>
<li>excellence is specific to an individual</li>
</ul>


<p>Like many pieces of business literature, it reads like an &ldquo;all-or-nothing&rdquo; approach (&ldquo;negative feedback - bad, positive feedback - good&rdquo;), and the most effective approach is likely somewhere in the middle. There&rsquo;s a place for positive and negative feedback, and it&rsquo;s the focus on positive reinforcement that I see as a primary takeaway from this article.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve noticed that my assessment of others&#8217; performance changes over time. It often depends on what self-help book I&rsquo;m reading at the moment if I&rsquo;m being entirely honest.</p>

<p>This piece made me think of the portrayal of successful people in media: there&rsquo;s an inherent cultural belief that successful people know what makes them successful, and all you need to do is to follow in their steps! What is often omitted is a mix of luck, some talent or hard work, topped with another serving of being in the right place at the right time. Warren Buffet can probably tell you what&rsquo;s the smartest thing to do with ten thousand dollars you have in your savings account. It&rsquo;s unlikely that his advice alone will get you to his <a href="https://www.google.com/search?q=warren+buffett+net+worth">98.2 billion dollar net worth</a>.</p>

<p>It seems like once you get past basic competency, success identifiers seem unpredictable.</p>

<p>I attribute part of my professional success to having a reputation of a person who &ldquo;gets shit done&rdquo;. I naturally value qualities associated with that style of work. It&rsquo;s only natural that I prioritize on communication and organizational skills when assessing the performance of others.</p>

<p>In fact, the article made me think about how I landed with the reputation as a problem solver. Every time I accomplished a project on time, owned the problem space, involved the right parties, or raised alarms early &ndash; I received positive reinforcement. People I worked with valued those qualities, and years working with those people shaped what I perceive as an effective work style.</p>

<p>Yet, this work style is effective for me, and is not a solution for my peers.</p>

<p>Since reading <a href="https://hbr.org/2019/03/the-feedback-fallacy">&ldquo;The Feedback Fallacy&rdquo;</a>, I started focusing on the outcomes I like, as opposed to qualities I believe are valuable. Where before I would say &ldquo;Great comms on project X!&rdquo;, now I focus on specifics: &ldquo;I know what you&rsquo;re up to on project X, which helps me communicate with stakeholder Y and plan resources for the project Z&rdquo;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Take a pause before that email]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/take-a-pause-before-that-email/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-28T11:12:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/take-a-pause-before-that-email</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not an ill tempered person, and it takes quite a lot to get me riled up. In
the pandemic however getting frustrated has been oh so much easier!</p>

<p>For once, there are less face to face interactions, which makes me feel removed
from whomever I&rsquo;m talking to. The interactions that happen over video chat feel
a lot less personal, and despite regular deliberately scheduled 1:1 time it&rsquo;s
harder to connect with colleagues on a personal level.</p>

<p>Then there&rsquo;s the lack of water cooler interactions between meetings. A colleague
of mine correctly pointed out that before the era of video chat meetings, we&rsquo;d
have the time to decompress and process content between meetings with those
micro-interactions. Having just a minute or two &ldquo;off the record&rdquo; after a large
call helps process, frame, and align prior interaction. And just sharing a laugh
or being able to say &ldquo;well that was stressful&rdquo; helps reduce the inevitable daily
stress buildup.</p>

<p>Finally, all of the above is true for everyone else - and we&rsquo;re already in a
melting pot of individuals with different communication styles. People are
getting frustrated, making other people even more frustrated. It&rsquo;s a frustration
chain reaction!</p>

<p>All of this led to me into a cycle of sending some snappy responses, feeling
terrible after time would pass, setting up time to profusely apologize face to
face, and wowing to never overreact to work stress sources again&hellip; Until the
next encounter that is. It all culminated with me getting entirely too
frustrated between 8:00 and 8:05 am last Thursday and taking a day just to
decompress.</p>

<p>And that reminded of something I&rsquo;ve learned years ago, and I something I would
practice with rigour - until the background frustration level rose that is.</p>

<p>Early in my career I&rsquo;ve been taught to cool down before sending that angry ping
or an email &ndash; type it up, leave it in my drafts - come back to it an hour or
two later.</p>

<p>In 9 out of 10 cases I end up deleting the message feeling relieved that an
incoherent stream of hatred never saw the light of day. Most of the time when
I&rsquo;m angry I don&rsquo;t really have a goal I&rsquo;m trying to accomplish (other than inform
all the parties involved of my feelings), and that&rsquo;s not a great basis for
professional communication.</p>

<p>In the remaining case, I would end up completely rewriting that email to remove
the hostile tone and focus on the source of the issue instead. There are
problems that are worth addressing with candor &ndash; but candor is too often
conflated for the lack of tact.</p>

<p>And it&rsquo;s hard to take a break at work - because there are often so many things
to do, and so little time to do them. Which makes taking a minute to breather
feel like a waste of time, when it&rsquo;s one of the most productive things you can
do in the long run.</p>

<p>So here I am, putting these thoughts into writing to remember to take a break
before initiating aggressive communications &ndash; hopefully the more I think about
this, the easier it gets to remember to pause, self-assess, and disconnect.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On mentorship]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/on-mentorship/"/>
    <updated>2021-03-27T05:08:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/on-mentorship</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months ago I had a conversation with a fellow employee &ndash; let&rsquo;s call
him Balgruuf &ndash; who decided to quit the grind and become a career coach.
Shortly after I&rsquo;ve witnessed them interact with our mutual acquaintance &ndash;
Farengar &ndash; who was in a difficult spot in their career. Balgruuf was
enthusiastically instructing on what are the exact steps Farengar must take, and
in what order. It generally felt like Balgruuf had this whole career thing
figured out, and Farengar just stumbled along. Needless to say, Farengar quickly
changed the topic.</p>

<p>I haven&rsquo;t stopped thinking about mentorship since that day. In the 10 or so
years of my career so far, I&rsquo;ve had a number of mentors - both formal and
informal. I also get the opportunity to mentor people around me &ndash; both sides of
the relationship really fascinate me.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had some mentors who worked really well for me - and some who didn&rsquo;t. I
also had more different level of success with mentoring people myself. And one
of the defining factors in a successful experience was this: people conflate
mentorship with giving advice &ndash; two different, but oh-so-close feeling things.
Let me elaborate on the difference with a tangentially related example.</p>

<p>Sometimes my wife comes home and shares frustrations that inevitably arise after
a long day at work. There&rsquo;s little to no room for my input, because she needs
somebody to just listen, or maybe a rubber duck to talk at. And sometimes my
better half wants to hear my thoughts on the subject. Needing to vent and asking
for advice are two completely distinct scenarios in this case.</p>

<p>Just like in my home life, sometimes people come looking for an advice. But more
often than not, they&rsquo;re looking for mentorship.</p>

<p>Giving advice is prescriptive, while mentorship is more nuanced, and takes more
finesse from both parties.</p>

<p>In <a href="https://amzn.to/2NYlWPb">Relationomics</a>, Randy Ross discusses a role that
relationships play in personal growth. He talks about the harmful &ldquo;self help&rdquo;
culture which discounts the value of human element in self-development.</p>

<p>This is the gap where mentorship fits in. There&rsquo;s one huge &ldquo;but&rdquo; though, and
that&rsquo;s the fact that the person needs to be ready for the specific feedback they
might be getting.</p>

<p>Mentor is there to guide the internal conversation, encourage insight, and
suggest a direction. Mentor is there to identify when someone who&rsquo;s being
mentored is heading in a completely wrong direction, or not addressing the
elephant in the room.</p>

<p>In fact, I&rsquo;ve been noticing a trend at Google to avoid trying to use the word
&ldquo;mentorship&rdquo; overall, to avoid the go-to advice slinging attitude of your
everyday Balgruuf. And it&rsquo;s been a helpful trend - since framing mentorship
relationship around guidance and reminding mentors to let those who are mentored
to drive the growth is crucial for healthy peer to peer learning.</p>

<p>Even if so-called mentor has some aspect of life completely figured out for
themselves, the person who&rsquo;s mentored must drive the whole journey. Otherwise
there&rsquo;s really no room for growth in that relationship.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing for fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/writing-for-fun/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-11T02:13:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/writing-for-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve had this blog since 2012, and I&rsquo;m only now getting close to my 100th post. All because I&rsquo;m a perfectionist, which sure as hell didn&rsquo;t make me a better writer.</p>

<p>I love writing, and I feel like I&rsquo;m getting better after every piece I write - be it publishing blog posts, journaling, countless design docs, navigating email politics, or writing a book. I write a lot, about many different topics - if I&rsquo;m interested in the topic for at least a few hours - you can bet I&rsquo;ll write about it.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/journal.jpg" title="A picture of journal on a table." ></p>

<p>Then how come this blog barely gets one post per month?</p>

<p>I meticulously research and edit, generously discard drafts, and it often takes me days strung across weeks to put something together. Something that I feel is worthy of being displayed next to my name. Perfectionism at its core, attached to hobbyist web content.</p>

<p>I struggled with this when writing <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-book-has-been-published/">Mastering Vim</a> too - the first edition was rushed out by the publisher long before it was ready, with various errors and inconsistencies in it, and a few downright unfinished bits. It took over a year of me avoiding even thinking about the book and two more editions to become comfortable with merely sharing that I published a book.</p>

<p>And all of this sucks the joy out of writing. I&rsquo;m not a for-profit writer. It&rsquo;s not part of my career path, and I obviously didn&rsquo;t go to school for it (not that I went to school for anything else). And it sure as hell shouldn&rsquo;t be grueling to have to come up with what to write.</p>

<p>This blog has a rather modest following - it brings in around 3,000 readers a month, with a few regulars sprinkled here and there (honestly - I would love to meet at least one of you weirdos someday). I don&rsquo;t target a particular market niche, I don&rsquo;t have a content or SEO strategy, and I opportunistically monetize to cover the website running costs.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s crazy is that nearly half of that traffic is organic search for a quick note I jotted down back in 2013! I could spend weeks putting together a literary love child and not even get a fraction of attention this back of the napkin screenshot received.</p>

<p>Back in 2012 I used this blog as a way to categorize my discoveries about developing software, and later what I&rsquo;ve learned about working with people. Over the years I gradually expanded to travel (including that time I lived in my car for a year), and general things I like - like keyboards or tabletop role playing games.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m putting this together to remind myself that I love writing and why I started this blog. That not every piece of content requires hours of research, or even have a clear audience in mind for that matter.</p>

<p>I wouldn&rsquo;t have blinked an eye flooding this blog with unfiltered thoughts, perspectives, and experiences if it wasn&rsquo;t attached to my real world persona. It&rsquo;s easy to throw out something I perceive as &ldquo;unworthy&rdquo; anonymously. It&rsquo;s mortifying to publish such a piece at my-first-name-last-name-dot-com.</p>

<p>So here it is, the first post I wrote purely for fun! I&rsquo;m still taking a light editing pass on it, and drastically cutting it down in size - I&rsquo;m not a savage! But unlike in my usual writing, there&rsquo;s no clear value I&rsquo;m providing or a skill I&rsquo;m trying to teach - and that&rsquo;s a huge step for me. Feels good!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vortex Core 40% keyboard]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/vortex-core-keyboard/"/>
    <updated>2020-09-13T10:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/vortex-core-keyboard</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This review is written entirely using Vortex Core, in Markdown, and using Vim.</em></p>

<p>Earlier this week I purchased <a href="https://amzn.to/3ivzMCK">Vortex Core</a> - a 40% keyboard from a Taiwanese company Vortex, makers of the ever popular <a href="https://mechanicalkeyboards.com/shop/index.php?l=product_detail&amp;p=3633">Pok3r</a> keyboard (which I happen to use as my daily driver). This is a keyboard with only 47 keys: it drops the numpad (what&rsquo;s called 80%), function row (now we&rsquo;re down to 60%), and the dedicated number row (bringing us to the 40% keyboard realm).</p>

<p>Words don&rsquo;t do justice to how small a 40% keyboard is. So here is a picture of Vortex Core next to Pok3r, which is an already a small keyboard.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/vortex-core-and-pok3r.jpg" title="A picture of Vortex Core 40% keyboard next to a Pok3r 60% keyboard." ></p>

<p>At around a <a href="https://amzn.to/3ivzMCK">$100 on Amazon</a> it&rsquo;s one of the cheaper 40% options, but Vortex did not skimp on quality. The case is sturdy, is made of beautiful anodized aluminum, and has some weight to it. The keycaps this keyboard comes with feel fantastic (including slight dips on <code>F</code> and <code>J</code> keys), and I`m a huge fan of the look.</p>

<p>I hooked it up to my Microsoft Surface Go as a toy more than anything else. And now I think I may have discovered the perfect writing machine! Small form factor of the keyboard really compliments the already small Surface Go screen, and there&rsquo;s just enough screen real estate to comfortably write and edit text.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/vortex-core-and-surface-go.jpg" title="A picture of Vortex Core 40% keyboard plugged into Microsoft Surface Go screen." ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve used Vortex Core on and off for the past few days, and I feel like I have a solid feel for it. Let&rsquo;s dig in!</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s different about it?</h2>

<p>First, the keycap size and distance between keys are standard: it&rsquo;s a standard staggered layout most people are used to. This means that when typing words, there is no noticeable speed drop. In fact I find myself typing a tiny bit faster using this keyboard than my daily driver - but that could just be my enthusiasm shining through. I hover at around 80 words per minute on both keyboards.</p>

<p>That is until it&rsquo;s time to type &ldquo;you&rsquo;re&rdquo;, or use any punctuation outside of the <code>:;,.&lt;&gt;</code> symbols. That&rsquo;s right, the normally easily accessible apostrophe is hidden under the function layer (<code>Fn1 + b</code>), and so is the question mark (<code>Fn1 + Shift + Tab</code>). <code>-</code>, <code>=</code>, <code>/</code>, <code>\</code>, <code>[</code>, and <code>]</code> are gone too, and I&rsquo;ll cover those in due time.</p>

<p>On a first day this immediately dropped my typing speed to around 50 words per minute, as it&rsquo;s completely unintuitive at first! In fact, I just now stopped hitting <code>Enter</code> every time I tried to place an apostrophe! But only after a few hours of sparingly using Vortex Core I&rsquo;m up to 65 WPM, and it feels like I would regain my regular typing speed within a week.</p>

<p>Despite what you might think, it&rsquo;s relatively easy to get used to odd key placement like this.</p>

<p>Keys have 4 layers (not to be confused with programming layers), and that&rsquo;s how the numbers, symbols, and some of the more rarely used keys are accessed. For example, here&rsquo;s what the key <code>L</code> contains:</p>

<ul>
<li>Default layer (no modifiers): <code>L</code></li>
<li><code>Fn1</code> layer: <code>0</code></li>
<li><code>Fn1 + Shift</code> layer: <code>)</code></li>
<li><code>Fn</code> layer: <code>right arrow key</code></li>
</ul>


<p>The good news is that unlike many 40% keyboards on the market (and it&rsquo;s a rather esoteric market), Vortex Core has key inscriptions for each layer. Something like <a href="https://mechanicalkeyboards.com/shop/index.php?l=product_detail&amp;p=3633https://olkb.com/collections/planck">Planck</a> would require you to print out layout cheatsheets while you get used to the function layers.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/vortex-core-left-half.jpg" title="Left side of the Vortex Core keyboard, demonstrating numbers and special characters." ></p>

<p>As I continue attempting to type, numbers always take me by surprise: the whole number row is a function layer on top of the home row (where your fingers normally rest). After initially hitting the empty air when attempting to type numbers, I began to get used to using the home row instead.</p>

<p>The placement mimics the order the keys would be in on the number row (<code>1234567890-=</code>), but <code>1</code> is placed on the <code>Tab</code> key, while <code>=</code> is on the <code>Enter</code>. While I was able to find the numbers relatively easily due to similar placement, I would often be off-by-one due to row starting on a <code>Tab</code> key.</p>

<p>Things get a lot more complicated when it comes to special symbols. These are already normally gated behind a <code>Shift</code>-press on a regular keyboard, and Vortex Core requires some Emacs-level gymnastics! E.g. you need to press <code>Fn1 + Shift + F</code> to conjure <code>%</code>.</p>

<p>Such complex keypresses are beyond counter-intuitive at first. Yet after a few hours, I began to get used to some of the more frequently used keys: <code>!</code> is <code>Fn1 + Shift + Tab</code>, <code>-</code> is <code>Fn1 + Shift + 1</code>, <code>$</code> (end of line in Vim) is <code>Fn1 + Shift + D</code>, and so on. Combining symbols quickly becomes problematic.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s fairly easy to get used to inserting a lone symbol here and there, but the problems start when having to combine multiple symbols at once. E.g. writing an expression like <code>'Fn1 + Shift + D' = '$'</code> above involves the following keypresses: <code>&lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Esc&gt; F N &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Tab&gt; &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Shift&gt;&lt;Enter&gt; S H I F T &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Shift&gt;&lt;Enter&gt; D &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Esc&gt; &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Enter&gt; &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Esc&gt; &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Shift&gt;D &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Esc&gt;</code>. Could you image how long it took me to write that up?</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/vortex-core-right-half.jpg" title="Right side of the Vortex Core keyboard, demonstrating special characters placed on `bnm,.` keys." ></p>

<p>The most difficult part of getting used to the keyboard is the fact that a few keys on the right side are chopped off: <code>'/[]\</code> are placed in the bottom right of the keyboard, to <code>bnm,.</code> keys. While the rest of the layout attempts to mimic the existing convention and only shifting the rows down, the aforementioned keys are placed arbitrarily (as there&rsquo;s no logical way to place them otherwise).</p>

<p>This probably won&rsquo;t worry you if you don&rsquo;t write a lot of code or math, but I do, and it`s muscle memory I&rsquo;ll have to develop.</p>

<p>There are dedicated <code>Del</code> and <code>Backspace</code> keys, which is a bit of an odd choice, likely influenced by needing somewhere to place the <code>F12</code> key - function row is right above the home row, and is hidden behind the <code>Fn1</code> layer.</p>

<p>Spacebar is split into two (for ease of finding keycaps I hear), and it doesn&rsquo;t affect me whatsoever. I mostly hit spacebar with my left thumb and it&rsquo;s convenient.</p>

<p><code>Tab</code> is placed where the <code>Caps Lock</code> is, which feels like a good choice. After accidentally hitting <code>Esc</code> a few times, I got used to the position. Do make sure to get <a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/vortex3.asp">latest firmware</a> for your Vortex Core - I believe earlier firmware versions hides Tab behind a function layer, defaulting the key to <code>Caps Lock</code> (although my keycaps reflected the updated firmware).</p>

<p>So I&rsquo;d say the numbers and the function row take the least amount of time to get used to. It&rsquo;s the special characters that take time.</p>

<h2>Can you use it with Vim?</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;m a huge fan of Vim, and I even wrote <a href="https://amzn.to/3htsTjK">a book</a> on the subject. In fact, I&rsquo;m writing this very review in Vim.</p>

<p>And I must say, it&rsquo;s difficult. My productivity took a hit. I use curly braces to move between paragraphs, I regularly search with <code>/</code>, <code>?</code>, and <code>*</code>, move within a line with <code>_</code> and <code>$</code>, and use numbers in my commands like <code>c2w</code> (change two words) as well as other special characters, e.g. <code>da"</code> (delete around double quotes).</p>

<p>The most difficult combination being spelling correction: <code>z=</code> followed by a number to select the correct spelling. I consistency break the flow by having to press <code>Z &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Enter&gt; &lt;Fn1&gt;&lt;Tab&gt;</code> or something similar to quickly fix a misspelling.</p>

<p>My Vim productivity certainly took a massive hit. Yet, after a few days it&rsquo;s starting to slowly climb back up, and I find myself remembering the right key combinations as the muscle memory kicks in.</p>

<p>I assume my Vim experience translates well into programming. Even though I write code for a living, I haven&rsquo;t used Vortex Core to crank out code.</p>

<h2>Speaking of programming</h2>

<p>The whole keyboard is fully programmable (as long as you update it to the <a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/vortex3.asp">latest firmware</a>).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an easy process - a <a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/vortex3.asp">three page manual</a> covers everything that&rsquo;s needed like using different keyboard layers or remapping regular and function keys.</p>

<p>The manual also mentions using right <code>Win</code>, <code>Pn</code>, <code>Ctrl</code>, and <code>Shift</code> keys as arrow keys by hitting left <code>Win</code>, left <code>Alt</code>, and right spacebar. Vortex keyboards nowadays always come with this feature, but due to small form factor of the keys (especially Shift), impromptu arrow keys on Vortex Core are nearly indistinguishable from individual arrow keys.</p>

<p>Remapping is helpful, since I&rsquo;m used to having <code>Ctrl</code> where <code>Caps Lock</code> is (even though this means I have to hide Tab behind a function layer), or using <code>hjkl</code> as arrow keys (as opposed to the default <code>ijkl</code>).</p>

<p>It took me only a few minutes to adjust the keyboard to my needs, but I imagine I will come back for tweaks - I&rsquo;m not so sure if I&rsquo;ll be able to get used to special symbols hidden behind <code>Fn1</code> + <code>Shift</code> + key layer. Regularly pressing three keys at the time (with two of these keys being on the edge of the keyboard) feels unnatural and inconvenient right now. But I&rsquo;m only a few hours in, and stenographers manager to do it.</p>

<h2>Living in the command line</h2>

<p>The absence of certain special characters is especially felt when using the command line. Not having a forward slash available with a single keypress makes typing paths more difficult. I also use <code>Ctrl + \</code> as a modifier key for tmux, and as you could imagine it&rsquo;s just as problematic.</p>

<p>Despite so many difficulties, I&rsquo;m loving my time with Vortex Core! To be honest with myself, I don&rsquo;t buy new keyboards to be productive, or increase my typing speed. I buy them because they look great and are fun to type on. And Vortex Core looks fantastic, and being able to cover most of the keyboard with both hands is amazing.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s just something special about having such a small board under my fingertips.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One page TTRPG prep]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/one-page-ttrpg-prep/"/>
    <updated>2020-08-08T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/one-page-ttrpg-prep</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been running table top role playing games for over a decade on and off, and I&rsquo;ve settled into a prep routine. It&rsquo;s heavily borrowed, if not outright stolen from other GMs on the Internets, and I encourage you to steal and adapt what I&rsquo;m doing as well. If I had to guess, this way of preparation is stolen directly from the <a href="https://slyflourish.com/lazydm/">Lazy GM</a>&rsquo;s table.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve learned that in order to run a successful session, I need to prepare the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Discoveries: What my players need to discover.</li>
<li>Scenes: Where things happen.</li>
<li>Clues: Some thoughts on how to expose the discoveries.</li>
<li>Key NPCs: Some names and primary aspects of non player characters.</li>
<li>Enemies: A few stat blocks or references to enemies.</li>
</ul>


<p>And all of the above fits on a single page: I find it enough to run the session while providing player freedom without having to completely invent everything on the fly.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s an example for a Numenera game I ran a few weeks ago, where I adopted the idea behind the &ldquo;Mother Machine&rdquo; module from <a href="https://www.montecookgames.com/explorers-keys/">&ldquo;Explorer&rsquo;s Keys: Ten Instant Adventures for Numenera&rdquo;</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/ttrpg-game-prep.jpeg" title="A picture of a journal I use to prepare for tabletop role playing games." ></p>

<p>In this example, the village under players&#8217; protection is attacked by &ldquo;tarza&rdquo;, never before seen monsters. For historical reasons, my players are initially expected to blame a neighboring tribe of abhumans for the attack. The monsters are in fact part of a defense mechanism which is attempting to exterminate so-called &ldquo;cinomar&rdquo;: doppelgangers who are impersonating some of the villagers.</p>

<h2>Discoveries</h2>

<p>This section cover key information and plot twists, and it&rsquo;s the one I start with. I use it as a tool to outline the adventure, and it&rsquo;s helpful to refer to if I get stuck.</p>

<p>These are the details players should unravel throughout the session, and I usually check them off as the players find them. In fact, you&rsquo;ll see I check off most bullet points on the page as the session plays out.</p>

<p>Although, now that I&rsquo;m looking at the example I provided, the discoveries are not marked. I guess I&rsquo;m not very consistent.</p>

<h2>Scenes</h2>

<p>This is the primary tool I use during the game. Scenes outline encounters - be they social, exploratory, or combat related. Scenes help me form a general idea about locations the adventure will be taking a place in, as well as some of the key action sequences.</p>

<p>I often use scenes to help me control pacing: If I&rsquo;m running a 3 hour game with roughly 5 scenes planned, I know to hurry up if I haven&rsquo;t gotten to any of them at a one hour mark. It&rsquo;s often a good time to narrate a time skip, tie up an ongoing investigation, or suggest a direction for the party to move in.</p>

<p>Now this doesn&rsquo;t mean that the adventure is limited to these scenes. If (or more accurately &ldquo;when&rdquo;) the adventure goes off rails, I reskin these scenes or use them for an inspiration to quickly throw together a new scene.</p>

<h2>Clues</h2>

<p>Clues are ideas for how to surface discoveries. These are not strictly necessary if you&rsquo;re really creative, but if you&rsquo;re anything like me - these are a godsend.</p>

<p>Clues are concrete ways for players to discover plot points outlined in &ldquo;Discoveries&rdquo;. <em>&ldquo;The assassin had a letter signed by the big bad&rdquo;</em>, or <em>&ldquo;The drunken sailor lets slip about a cult in the town&rdquo;</em>. I aim for one clue per discovery, but it&rsquo;s not a hard rule.</p>

<p>The list should not be exhaustive, and should not be strictly followed - I treat this section as an exercise in creativity. I find it more impactful to try to come up with clues as I play &ndash; players often search in places I haven&rsquo;t thought of - so I place the clue to a discovery wherever the players are looking.</p>

<h2>Key NPCs</h2>

<p>This is a list of key non player characters relevant to the game. I try to keep number of named NPCs low to help my players remember them better, and I try to use as many recurring NPCs as humanly possible.</p>

<p>I usually add an aspect for each of the NPCs - a short description in a few words, something that makes them stand out in some way.</p>

<p>This list doesn&rsquo;t have to be exhaustive &ndash; you&rsquo;ll probably want to use the running list of NPCs for your campaign as a supplement for unexpected recurring characters, and a list of pre-generated names for unexpected encounters.</p>

<h2>Enemies</h2>

<p>The last thing is enemy stat blocks for quickly referencing if (again, &ldquo;when&rdquo;) a combat breaks out.</p>

<p>For Numenera, these are not particularly complex - most enemies are described by a single number and a few key things about them. I&rsquo;d imagine for D&amp;D and other combat focused systems you&rsquo;d want to put a bit more effort in making sure you&rsquo;re building balanced combat encounters, so that would warrant a section of its own.</p>

<p>I tend to spend a little under 20 minutes on all of the above, and I get to use it in three out of four games &ndash; the fourth one tends to go off the rails completely, and I&rsquo;m okay with it. Without investing as much time into prep, it&rsquo;s easy to be taken on a ride by the players.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numenera for D&D DMs]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/numenera-for-dnd-dms/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-25T18:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/numenera-for-dnd-dms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We&rsquo;ll be having our 12th Numenera game later this week, and ultimately Numenera proved to be easier to run compared to Dungeons and Dragons. I just wrote about <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/numenera-for-dnd-players">teaching Numenera to my D&amp;D Players</a>, and it&rsquo;s worth sharing my own experience getting familiar with the system as a GM.</p>

<h2>Story is the king</h2>

<p>As a soft tabletop role playing system, Numenera focuses on storytelling over the rules. Every dozen pages or so the rulebook tirelessly reminds the reader: &ldquo;if rules get in the way of having fun or creating an interesting story, change them&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/numenera-and-dnd-books.jpg" title="Numenera rulebooks stacked next to Dungeons and Dragons rulebooks." ></p>

<p>Depending on your DMing style and party&rsquo;s needs you can get away with a lackluster D&amp;D story: even if the party is saving the world from the evil wizard for the umpteenth time, there are decently fun board game mechanics to fall back to. Monster Manual and Dungeon Master&rsquo;s Guide provide hundreds of fun creatures and straightforward rules for building balanced encounters, and there&rsquo;s plenty of clearly laid out tactical choices and fun abilities to play with in combat. Take out the story telling, and you&rsquo;ll have a pretty fun tactical game (isn&rsquo;t that what <a href="https://amzn.to/2zla2HW">Gloomhaven</a> did?).</p>

<p>But there really aren&rsquo;t enough rules in Numenera to make combat engaging without additional emotional investment from the players. This makes building something people care about paramount to having fun with Numenera. The usual storytelling rules apply: build a compelling story and let the players take you for a ride if their story is better (and it often is).</p>

<h2>You don&rsquo;t <em>need</em> combat encounters</h2>

<p>Numenera supports a breadth of combat options only limited by players&#8217; imagination, but many of them are not immediately obvious, and newer players will struggle to utilize the full spectrum of abilities available to them. Combat uses the same rules as the rest of the game, and is not more mechanically complicated (you decide what you want to do, you try to beat certain difficulty, you fail spectacularly).</p>

<p>Because of this combat is completely optional in Numenera. Don&rsquo;t force the players into combat if they find a way to avoid it. Make them feel great about their cunning victory! We&rsquo;ve had great and satisfying sessions without a single thrown punch.</p>

<p>That being said, it does not mean Numenera combat can&rsquo;t be fun. One of the most engaging sessions we had consisted of a single battle &ndash; when a monster hunter delve decided to hunt a morigo &ndash; an enormous beast whose entire purpose was to scare the players from entering an area. The fight was deadly and arduous, but the characters triumphed against all odds.</p>

<h2>You still need to know all the rules</h2>

<p>Latest edition of Numenera consists of two books, titled <a href="https://amzn.to/36FZvmV">Discovery</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/2AbgeSx">Destiny</a> &ndash; both targeted at the game master. The two tomes combined clock in at a whopping 800 pages of reading material. However only 29 of the lavishly illustrated pages outline the rules. The rest provide supplemental material: character customization options, the setting, realizing the world, building compelling narrative, and so on.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/numenera-discovery-and-destiny.jpg" title="Numenera Discovery and Destiny core rulebooks." ></p>

<p>But because of this it&rsquo;s even more important for the GM to be intimately familiar with the rules. Since there was so little to learn, the group of players I&rsquo;m GMing for decided that it&rsquo;s not worth reading the rules. Thankfully Numenera rules are easy to teach, but you still need to know the rules.</p>

<h2>A lesson in assertiveness</h2>

<p>When playing D&amp;D, I&rsquo;d often outsource dealing with the rules by designating a rules arbiter from the player ranks. This doesn&rsquo;t seem to work in Numenera. There rules are guidelines, and logic dictates how each situation is resolved. GM has the fullest picture of the situation in their head, making it crucial for them to adjudicate.</p>

<p>It certainly took me time to get used to putting my foot down, even if the players might not always agree with the decision. I found myself frequently making snap judgements, and following up with any adjustments after the session &ndash; <a href="https://rpg.stackexchange.com/questions/tagged/numenera">rpg.stackexchange.com</a> turned out to be a great resource for asking questions about the spirit of the rules.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t dungeon crawl</h2>

<p>&ldquo;And then you enter another room which contains X, Y, and Z&rdquo;. That&rsquo;s the line I kept repeating during our weakest session to date. Numenera does not land itself well to a typical dungeon crawl.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/numenera-rulebooks-stack.jpg" title="Numenera rulebooks stacked on top of each other." ></p>

<p>Monte Cook published a few sets of fantastic adventures which require little to no prep to run. <a href="https://amzn.to/2Adkdht">Weird Discoveries</a> and <a href="https://amzn.to/3gphdPE">Explorer&rsquo;s Keys</a> let you run adventures with minimal prep. But it doesn&rsquo;t help that these come with standard dungeon-style maps.</p>

<p>Turned out a more engaging way to describe locations is: &ldquo;Over the next few hours you explore the obelisk, and within the maze of the corridors you note a number of places of interest. There are&hellip;&rdquo;. The rulebook has my back on this too.</p>

<h2>Bring out the weird</h2>

<p>The most difficult part of running Numenera games was highlighting how weird the Ninth World truly is. My players kept falling back into thinking of Steadfast as a standard medieval fantasy setting, and that&rsquo;s in many ways because I kept forgetting to tell them how weird everything is.</p>

<p>How a mountain in the background is a machine from the prior world. How the water in the swamp was a conduit for some unimaginable device. And how none of it should make sense.</p>

<p>In earlier games, I had explanations ready for everything odd occurring in the world. I&rsquo;ve been slowly making an effort to make the world more mysterious, more unexplainable, and more weird. This seems to be the key to running a successful Numenera game, and I&rsquo;m still trying to find the balance between a consistent, but weird world characters live in.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Numenera for D&D players]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/numenera-for-dnd-players/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-22T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/numenera-for-dnd-players</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before COVID-19 shelter-in-place order came to be, I played Dungeons and Dragons on and off for the past 10 or so years. I unfortunately don&rsquo;t have the patience to be a great player, but I enjoy running the game &ndash; being a Game Master constantly engages me, and I love seeing players have fun and overcome obstacles together.</p>

<p>Having to stay inside I had a prime opportunity to try something new, exciting, and less rule heavy than D&amp;D: that&rsquo;s how I discovered Numenera. Well, I&rsquo;ve been familiar with the concept for some time: I played Planescape: Torment &ndash; with Planescape being an inspiration for the setting of Numenera, and I&rsquo;ve recently completed Torment: Tides of Numenera &ndash; a spiritual successor to Planescape, which used the Cypher System rules&hellip; I&rsquo;m getting ahead of myself, let me back up.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.rosipov.com/images/posts/numenera-keiran-yanner.jpg" title="Numenera game system, image property of Monte Cook games." ></p>

<p>Numenera is a science fantasy tabletop role-playing game set in the (oh so) distant future. The &ldquo;Cypher System&rdquo; is a tabletop game engine which Numenera runs on. The system is notorious for emphasizing storytelling over rules, and for usage of &ldquo;cyphers&rdquo; - a one time abilities meant to shake up gameplay. Want to teleport? You don&rsquo;t have to be a level 10 wizard to that. Find the right cypher, and you can teleport, but only once. This keeps gameplay from getting stale, and provides players with exciting abilities from the get-go.</p>

<p>For the past few months I&rsquo;ve been running Numenera campaign for a group of friends, and we&rsquo;ve had a blast so far! We&rsquo;ve been playing over Google Hangouts, without miniatures or services like Roll20: and the game held up well.</p>

<p>It took some time for players to get used to the differences between the systems &ndash; and some picked up the new mindset faster than others. Here are the key concepts one had to learn to get used to Numenera. This overview is not complete, but I think it helps.</p>

<h2>Numenera, cyphers, and artifacts</h2>

<p>Numenera is just a catch-all term for weird devices and phenomenon. Now you don&rsquo;t have to say &ldquo;that device and/or contraption&rdquo; and say &ldquo;numenera&rdquo; instead. You&rsquo;re welcome!</p>

<p>Cyphers are items that give characters fun and unique one-off powers. Cyphers are plentiful, and using them like they&rsquo;re going out of fashion is the key to having fun in Numenera. It&rsquo;s called &ldquo;Cypher System&rdquo; for this exact reason.</p>

<p>Artifacts are a lot more rare, and can be used multiple times (often requiring a die roll to check if they deplete).</p>

<h2>Actions, skills, assets, and effort</h2>

<p>Every task in Numenera has a difficulty rated on a scale from 0 to 10. Be it sprinting on the battlefield, picking a lock, convincing a city guard you&rsquo;re innocent, or hitting that guard on the back of her head with a club. 0 is a routine action, like you sitting right now and reading this, or maybe going over to the fridge to grab a beer. Difficulty 10 is getting the Israeli prime minister to abandon his post, fly over to wherever you live, and serve you that beer. Oh and you&rsquo;re in charge of Israel now too, your majesty.</p>

<p>Your GM will tell you the difficulty of the task.</p>

<p>The only die players use in Numenera is d20 - the trusty 20-sided die (and that&rsquo;s already a lie - in a few cases d6 is also used). Multiply difficulty by 3, and that&rsquo;s the number you&rsquo;ll have to reach with your d20 roll. Juggling is a difficulty 4 task. This means you&rsquo;ll have to roll 12 (4 * 3) or higher to succeed.</p>

<p>But what if I&rsquo;m an experienced juggler you say? I&rsquo;m glad you asked: you can be either trained or specialized in a skill, reducing the difficulty by 1 and 2 respectively. Juggling for someone who is specialized in juggling is a difficulty 2 (4 - 2) task. You can reduce difficulty by up to 2 levels using skills. There is no definitive list of skills in Numenera, and you can choose to be skilled in anything you want, be it mathematics, dancing, or magic tricks.</p>

<p>Are you juggling well balanced pins? That&rsquo;s an asset, further reducing the difficulty by 1. You can apply up to 2 levels of assets to reduce task difficulty. Just like with skills, there&rsquo;s no strict definition of what constitutes an asset. Be creative!</p>

<p>Finally, you can apply effort to a task. Expand effort, and the task becomes more manageable. Effort is limited by how advanced the character is, and starting characters can&rsquo;t apply more than 1 level of effort.</p>

<p>Hence, a specialized juggler (-2) juggling well balanced pins (-1) and applying effort (-1) reduces task difficulty from level 4 to 0, making it a trivial task &ndash; no need to roll to succeed!</p>

<h2>Stat pools, edge, and more about effort</h2>

<p>Characters have three primary stats - might, speed, and intellect. There&rsquo;s no health or other resources to track, but your stat pools do deplete. Did you get punched in the face? Deduct damage from your might pool. Exerted effort to concentrate on juggling? Pay the price through your speed pool. Trying to figure out how something works? Reduce your intellect pool.</p>

<p>You use the same resource to exert yourself and to take damage. As your pools deplete, your character becomes debilitated, and once all 3 pools drop to 0 - your character dies. There&rsquo;s nothing more to it.</p>

<p>The stat pools replenish by resting, and you can rest 4 times a day - for a few seconds, 10 minutes, 1 hour, and 10 hours. When you rest - restore 1d6 + tier (1 for beginning character) points spread across pools of your choice.</p>

<p>Each character also has &ldquo;edge&rdquo;. Edge is an affinity in a particular stat, and reduces all resource cost in that pool. If you have edge 2 in might, each time you expand that resource, you reduce the cost by 2. Bashing with your shield costs 1 might? That&rsquo;s dropped to 0 for you. Moving a tree blocking the road all by yourself will cost 5 might points? That&rsquo;s now dropped down to 3.</p>

<p>This becomes particularly relevant when applying effort. Applying effort makes tasks easier, but costs points from a stat pool. First level of effort costs 3 points, and any subsequent levels cost 2. Say if you&rsquo;re trying to climb a tree (difficulty 3) and want to expand 2 levels of effort to make the task easier. That would cost you 5 points from your might pool, and your edge 1 in might drops the cost to 4.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t overthink it for now.</p>

<h2>Tiers, experience, and GM intrusions</h2>

<p>Every Numenera character has a tier, which is akin to levels in D&amp;D. There are 6 tiers, with each more advanced than the last. However, unlike in Dungeons and Dragons, the tiers are not detrimental to character advancement: characters get just as much if not more utility from cyphers, artifacts, and the way they interact with the world.</p>

<p>Experience is given out by the Game Master for accomplishing narrative milestones. Experience is also given during GM intrusions, Cypher System&rsquo;s signature narrative mechanic. At any point throughout the session, GM introduces unexpected consequences for player actions: a rope snaps, poisoned villain has an antidote, or a previously hidden enemy attacks a passing player. Each time an intrusion happens, the affected player gets 2 experience points - 1 for themselves, and 1 to give away to another player.</p>

<p>GM intrusions allow to adjust the difficulty of the game and introduce fun challenges on the fly. Many GMs already do this in their games, but the Cypher System awards the players experience when this happens, associating unexpected events with positive stimulus.</p>

<p>In Numenera, experience points are a narrative currency, and a way for players to influence direction of the story. Experience is often counted in single digits, and can be spent in various ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>1 XP: re-roll a die, or resist GM intrusion</li>
<li>2 XP: gain a short term benefit, like learn a local dialect, or become trained in a narrowly applicable skill</li>
<li>3 XP: gain a long term benefit: make an ally, establish base of operations, or gain an artifact</li>
<li>4 XP: increase your pools, learn a skill, gain an edge, increase amount of effort you can expend, get an additional ability, improve pool recovery rolls, or reduce armor penalty</li>
</ul>


<p>Once you&rsquo;ve spent 4 XP to advance your character 4 times, you advance to the next tier. All of the above benefits are equally valuable for character progression - as a die re-roll at the right time, or an ally&rsquo;s help can make all the difference in a tough situation.</p>

<h2>A word about combat</h2>

<p>You might notice that I still haven&rsquo;t brought up combat. And that&rsquo;s because there aren&rsquo;t a lot of additional rules.</p>

<p>Just like in D&amp;D, there are rounds. Combat initiative is a speed task, and turns are taken with as much structure as the group would desire. There&rsquo;s often no need for precise turn order outside of who goes first &ndash; the players or the enemies.</p>

<p>Attacking is a task against GM-given difficulty. So is defending. Effort can be expanded to make hitting a target easier. Characters can expand effort to get +3 damage on their attacks per level of effort instead.</p>

<p>Distances are measured as immediate (up to 10 ft), short (up to 50 ft), long (up to 100 ft), and very long. Melee attacks happen within an immediate distance, traveling short distance takes an action, and traveling long distance within a round is a level 4 athletics task.</p>

<p>Combat-related tasks are only limited by imagination. You can distract your enemies, assist your comrades, or swing into battle on a rope yelling &ldquo;Huzzah&rdquo;!</p>

<h2>Special rolls - natural 1, 19, and 20</h2>

<p>To keep dice rolls exciting, Numenera extends the idea of critical success and critical failure.</p>

<p>Natural 1 allows for a free GM intrusion. Something unexpected happens, and you don&rsquo;t get any experience for it.</p>

<p>Natural 17 and 18 provide +1 and +2 damage respectively when attacking.</p>

<p>Natural 19 gives the player an opportunity to come up with a minor effect (or inflict +3 damage): some minor advantage which usually persists for a round. Maybe an enemy is knocked back, or a merchant impressed by your bartering skills gives you an extra discount.</p>

<p>Natural 20 provides the player with a major effect of their choice (or up the damage to +4). The cutthroats in a bar spill the location of their next heist, or a enemy gets stunned in battle.</p>

<h2>Stories, rules, and common sense</h2>

<p>Finally, Numenera and Cypher System are focused on telling great stories, and many rules are deliberately vague and are left up to GM&rsquo;s discretion. In Numenera, if you wonder if you can attempt some task &ndash; you most definitely can try, and good GM will help you fail in spectacular and most importantly entertaining ways.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
