<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gamedev | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/gamedev/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-08-09T02:42:09+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mob level distribution]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/mob-level-distribution/"/>
    <updated>2016-10-02T00:15:12+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/mob-level-distribution</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Distributing mobs in a dungeon based on player&rsquo;s level (or some dungeon level
difficulty factor) was somewhat straightforward, but I would still like to
document the progress. I needed to place a mob that&rsquo;s somewhat within the
difficulty level I want, plus minus a few difficulty levels to spice it up.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/roguelike-leveled-mob-distribution.png" title="Random mob distribution in roguelike dungeon." ></p>

<p>Above you can see three rats, three cats, a dog (<code>r</code>, <code>c</code>, <code>d</code>, all level 1), a
farmer (<code>f</code>, level 2), and a lonely bandit (<code>b</code>, level 3) in a level 1 dungeon.</p>

<p>Without going straight into measure theory, I generated intervals for each mob
based on the diff of desired level and their level, and then randomly selected a
point within the boundaries. Here&rsquo;s the abstract code:</p>

<pre><code>import bisect
import random


def get_random_element(data, target, chance):
    """Get random element from data set skewing towards target.

    Args:
        data   -- A dictionary with keys as elements and values as weights.
                  Duplicates are allowed.
        target -- Target weight, results will be skewed towards target
                  weight.
        chance -- A float 0..1, a factor by which chance of picking adjacent
                  elements decreases (i.e, with chance 0 we will always
                  select target element, with chance 0.5 probability of
                  selecting elements adjacent to target are halved with each
                  step).

    Returns:
        A random key from data with distribution respective of the target
        weight.
    """
    intervals = []  # We insert in order, no overlaps.
    next_i = 0
    for element, v in data.iteritems():
        d = max(target, v) - min(target, v)
        size = 100
        while d &gt; 0:  # Decrease chunk size for each step of `d`.
            size *= chance
            d -= 1
        if size == 0:
            continue
        size = int(size)
        intervals.append((next_i, next_i + size, element))
        next_i += size + 1
    fst, _, _ = zip(*intervals)
    rnd = random.randint(0, next_i - 1)
    idx = bisect.bisect(fst, rnd)  # This part is O(log n).
    return intervals[idx - 1][2]
</code></pre>

<p>Now, if I test the above for, say, a 1000000 iterations, with a chance of 0.5
(halving probability of selecting adjacent elements with each step), and 2 as a
target, here&rsquo;s the distribution I end up with:</p>

<pre><code>target, chance, iterations = 2, 0.5, 1000000

data = collections.OrderedDict([  # Ordered to make histogram prettier.
    ('A', 0), ('B-0', 1), ('B-1', 1), ('C', 2), ('D', 3), ('E', 4),
    ('F', 5), ('G', 6), ('H', 7), ('I', 8), ('J', 9),
])

res = collections.OrderedDict([(k, 0) for k, _ in data.iteritems()])

# This is just a test, so there's no need to optimize this for now.
for _ in xrange(iterations):
    res[get_random_element(data, target, chance)] += 1

pyplot.bar(
    range(len(res)), res.values(), width=0.7, align='center', color='green')
pyplot.xticks(range(len(res)), res.keys())
pyplot.title(
    'iterations={}, target={}, chance={}'.format(
        iterations, target, chance))
pyplot.show()
</code></pre>

<p><img src="/images/posts/roguelike-mob-distribution-chance-05.png" title="Distribution histogram: 1000000 iterations, 0.5 chance, and 2 as a target." ></p>

<p>You can see elements B-0 and B-1 having roughly the same distribution, since
they have the same weight.</p>

<p>Now, if I decrease the <code>chance</code>, likelihood of target being selected increases,
while likelihood of surrounding elements being selected decreases:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/roguelike-mob-distribution-chance-033.png" title="Distribution histogram: 1000000 iterations, 0.33 chance, and 2 as a target." ></p>

<p>I works the opposite way as well, increasing the <code>chance</code> decreases likelihood
of the target being selected and increases the probability for surrounding
elements.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/roguelike-mob-distribution-chance-09.png" title="Distribution histogram: 1000000 iterations, 0.9 chance, and 2 as a target." ></p>

<p>For the sake of completeness, it works with 0 chance of surrounding elements being picked:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/roguelike-mob-distribution-chance-0.png" title="Distribution histogram: 1000000 iterations, 0 chance, and 2 as a target." ></p>

<p>And an equal chance of picking surrounding elements:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/roguelike-mob-distribution-chance-1.png" title="Distribution histogram: 1000000 iterations, 1 chance, and 2 as a target." ></p>

<p>After playing around with the configuration in Jupyter Notebook, I cleaned up
the algorithm above and included it into mob placement routine.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spawning evenly distributed mobs]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/spawning-evenly-distributed-mobs/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-30T18:06:16+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/spawning-evenly-distributed-mobs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After generating a few <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/randomly-generated-dungeons/">good looking random dungeons</a>, I was puzzled with
randomly placing mobs on resulting maps. To make it fair (and fun) for the
player mobs should be evenly distributed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/dungeon-mob-placement.png" title="Dungeon with randomly placed mobs." ></p>

<p>The obvious idea was to pick coordinates randomly within the rectangular map
boundaries, and then place mobs if they have floor underneath them. But this way
I lose control of the number of mobs and risk having a chance of not placing any
mobs at all. Plus, dungeons with bigger surface area would get more mobs - which
sounds somewhat realistic, but not entirely what I was aiming for.</p>

<p>I could improve on the above by rerunning enemy placement multiple times and
select the most favorable outcome - but the solution would be rather naive.</p>

<p>To have control over the number of mobs I decided to place them as I generate
the rooms of the dungeon. There&rsquo;s a trick one can use to get a random element
with equal probability distribution from a sequence of an unknown size:</p>

<pre><code>import random


def get_random_element(sequence):
    """Select a random element from a sequence of an unknown size."""
    selected = None
    for k, element in enumerate(sequence):
        if random.randint(0, k) == 0:
            selected = element
    return selected
</code></pre>

<p>With each iteration the chance of the current element to become a selected item
is 1 divided by number of elements seen so far. Indeed, a probability of an
element being selected out of a 4-item sequence:</p>

<pre><code>1 * (1 - 1/2) * (1 - 1/3) * (1 - 1/4) = 1/2 * 2/3 * 3/4 = 6/30 = 1/4 
</code></pre>

<p>Now all I had to do is to modify this to account for multiple mob placement.
Here&rsquo;s a generalized function above which accounts for selecting <code>n</code> elements
from the sequence with even distribution.</p>

<pre><code>import random


def get_random_element(sequence, n):
    """Select n random elements from a sequence of an unknown size."""
    selected = [None for _ in range(n)]
    for k, element in enumerate(sequence):
        for i in range(n):
            if random.randint(0, k) == 0:
                selected[i] = element
    return selected
</code></pre>

<p>I incorporated logic above into the room generation code, accounted for
duplicates, and ended up with decent distribution results.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Randomly generated dungeons]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/randomly-generated-dungeons/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-29T23:26:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/randomly-generated-dungeons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>After playing with random dungeon generation for a bit, I seem to be satisfied
with the results:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/random-dungeon-1.png" title="A randomly generated ASCII-dungeon." ></p>

<p>The above is displayed using ADOM notation - <code>#</code> represents a wall, <code>.</code> is a
floor tile, and <code>+</code> is meant to be a closed door. After fiddling about with a
few random dungeon generation ideas, I settled with the following.</p>

<h2>The algorithm</h2>

<ol>
<li>Start with a random point on a canvas.</li>
<li>Create a room with random width and height. Don&rsquo;t worry about walls yet.</li>
<li>Select a few points on the sides of the room, put those in a stack. Save the
direction in which the potential doors would point.</li>
<li>Go through the stack, and try to add a room or a corridor (corridor is just a
room with a width or a height of 1). Higher chance of corridors seems to look
better and results in those wiggly passageways.

<ol>
<li>Try to add a room a few dozen times with different random configurations.
If no luck - give up and grab a new item from the stack. If couldn&rsquo;t
generate a continuation to the corridor - mark it as a loose end, we&rsquo;ll
clean those up later.</li>
<li>If a room was added successfully - add a door where it connects to the
previous room/corridor. Add a floor section if it&rsquo;s a corridor connecting
to another corridor.</li>
<li>At this point one ends up with quite a few interconnected corridors,
merged rooms, and all kinds of fun surroundings (my desired goal).</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Do the above until the stack is empty or a desired number of rooms has been
generated.</li>
<li>Clean up the loose ends from step 4.1. Remove loose corridor segments one by
one until intersection with another room/corridor is detected.</li>
<li>Add walls around the rooms and corridors, while also cleaning up any extra
doors we may have left behind when creating merged corridors or rooms.

<ol>
<li>I simply used slightly modified depth first search starting inside any
room and drawing walls wherever I could find floor/door not connected to
anything.</li>
<li>When encountering a door - check if it&rsquo;s surrounded by walls or doors from
the opposite sides. If not - remove the door and replace it with a floor
tile. If any doors were adjucent to the removed door - requeue the door
check on them.</li>
</ol>
</li>
<li>Perform steps 1-7 a few hundred times, saving the resulting dungeons each
time. Pick the best candidate with the most desired features - like a number
of rooms, breadth, square footage, longest corridors, etc.</li>
</ol>


<p>A more detailed explanation of the steps is below. For now, here are a few more
dungeons generated using this method:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/random-dungeon-2.png" title="A randomly generated ASCII-dungeon." ></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/random-dungeon-3.png" title="A randomly generated ASCII-dungeon." ></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/random-dungeon-4.png" title="A randomly generated ASCII-dungeon." ></p>

<p>I think dungeon generation is far more art than science, and I had a lot of fun
tweaking all the different input parameters:</p>

<ul>
<li>Room size boundaries.</li>
<li>Corridor lengths.</li>
<li>Frequency of corridor occurrences.</li>
<li>Number of exits from the room.</li>
<li>Number of room generation attempts.</li>
<li>Number of dungeon generation attempts.</li>
<li>Final dungeon picking heuristics.</li>
</ul>


<p>Last item on the list is the most interesting one - with few hundred dungeons as
an input, picking the right one is rather important. I ended up settling on
using max priority queue with a rough surface area of the dungeon as a key
(it&rsquo;s more of a breadth, really - how wide and tall it is). Then I&rsquo;d sift
through some top results and pick the one with the most rooms available. This
results in the most fun-looking map which feels up most of the screen, while
still usually not being too cluttered.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a breakdown of a simple scenario:</p>

<h3>Steps 1 and 2</h3>

<p>Pick a random spot on a canvas and generate a room of random size (4 x 3):</p>

<pre><code>....
....
....
</code></pre>

<h3>Step 3</h3>

<p>Select potential spots for doors, let&rsquo;s label them 1, 2, 3.</p>

<pre><code>....2
....
....1
  3
</code></pre>

<p>I went for a uniform distribution by unfolding the rectangle and folding it back
in to get a proper coordinate on the perimeter. Now, stack contains coordinates
of <code>[1, 2, 3]</code> (along with the directions in which they are pointing).</p>

<h3>Steps 4 and 5</h3>

<p>Add a room or a corridor to a connector number 3. We&rsquo;ll be adding the room to
the right of number 3. Let&rsquo;s assume random sends a corridor of length 5 our way.
We&rsquo;re happy with the corridor pointing either up, down, or right - so we let the
random decide again: up.</p>

<pre><code>     4
     .
     .
....2.
.... .
....3.
  1
</code></pre>

<p>We add the end of the corridor to the stack as number 4 (now <code>[1, 2, 4]</code>). We
also mark 4 as a loose end, in case we end up not adding a room to it. Dangling
corridors are never pretty.</p>

<p>Now, to replace number 3 with a door:</p>

<pre><code>     4
     .
     .
....2.
.... .
....+.
  1
</code></pre>

<p>Adding another random corridor of length 2 to the point 4, pointing right.
Replace number 4 with a floor segment, since point 4 was the end of another
corridor. Remove point 4 from loose ends, add point 5.</p>

<pre><code>     ...5
     .
     .
....2.
.... .
....+.
  1
</code></pre>

<p>Take point 5, generate a room of size 3 x 6. 5 becomes a door. Loose ends list
is empty.</p>

<pre><code>     ...+...
     .   ...
     .   ...
....2.   ...
.... .   ...
....+.   ...
  1
</code></pre>

<p>For simplicity&rsquo;s sake, let&rsquo;s assume we don&rsquo;t want any more exits from this room.
Back to the stack of <code>[1, 2]</code>. Point 2 seem to not have much room for growth.
After a few unsuccessful attempts to place a room or a corridor there, we give
up:</p>

<pre><code>     ...+...
     .   ...
     .   ...
.... .   ...
.... .   ...
....+.   ...
  1
</code></pre>

<p>Now for point 1: we get another corridor of length 3. Point 6 is now added to
the loose ends list.</p>

<pre><code>     ...+...
     .   ...
     .   ...
.... .   ...
.... .   ...
....+.   ...
  +
  .
  .
  .
  6
</code></pre>

<p>Let&rsquo;s assume we run out of space and can&rsquo;t add anything to the end of 6. We&rsquo;re
done generating the dungeon. Our stack is empty, and our loose ends contains
coordinates of <code>6</code>.</p>

<h3>Step 6</h3>

<p>Start with the loose end, and remove items one by one until a tile with multiple
neighbors is encountered:</p>

<pre><code>     ...+...
     .   ...
     .   ...
.... .   ...
.... .   ...
....+.   ...
  X
  X
  X
  X
  X
</code></pre>

<p>Viola:</p>

<pre><code>     ...+...
     .   ...
     .   ...
.... .   ...
.... .   ...
....+.   ...
</code></pre>

<h3>Steps 7 and 8</h3>

<p>There are no rogue doors in this scenario, so all we need to do is add  the
walls:</p>

<pre><code>     #########
     #...+...#
     #.###...#
######.# #...#
#....#.# #...#
#....#.# #...#
#....+.# #...#
######## #####
</code></pre>

<p>All of the steps above should be repeated a few hundred times with different
dungeons, and then the best dungeon should be picked as a final one.</p>

<p>Did I miss anything? Was cleaning up &ldquo;loose ends&rdquo; too much of a hack? What
should have I done differently?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
