<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: travel | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2021-05-24T07:41:36-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a packing spreadsheet]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/making-a-packing-spreadsheet/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/making-a-packing-spreadsheet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being the unique person I am, I love traveling. Oftentimes I end up getting deep into trying to optimize my packing methods. There are dozens of tools online designed to help with this exact thing (services like <a href="http://lighterpack.com">Lighterpack</a> or <a href="http://geargrams.com">GearGrams</a>). But, being handy with code, I decided to dabble in the subject on my own.</p>

<p>One of the most important things in packing is the overall weight of the pack, and I always want to know what type of things are the heaviest. I also want to be able to run random queries on my data, whatever it is that I&rsquo;m trying to learn. I want to have an inventory of items (backpacks, clothes, storage solutions) which I can plug in and out of a spreadsheet to see how the resulting picture changes on the go. Working with software as my day job, I’d also like for the solution to be automated whenever possible.</p>

<p>Google Spreadsheets turned out to be the perfect solution, providing the ability to quickly sum up the weight of my things and output insights about the data.</p>

<h2>Final Result</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qDhMoVmmTroM-eN0MZIU2PzE5YucsyPhbuPZPDGhemM/edit#">link to the spreadsheet</a>, I encourage the reader to copy and play around with in anyway you see fit.</p>

<p>Here’s the final result for a multi-day trip I will have for this year. As you can see, my pack weighs around 3 kilograms or a bit over 6 freedom units (not including water). My recently purchased Nintendo Switch is the heaviest item (and it’s worth every gram as it makes flying tolerable), but clothes take up most of the weight:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet.png" title="A screenshot of a packing spreadsheet." ></p>

<p>I use indentation levels to show that some items are contained within other items. This also lets me calculate the absolute and relative weights of a whole container with everything inside of it (see fields labeled “Container” and “Percentage”).</p>

<p>The “Weight” and the “Breakdown” fields indicate absolute and relative item weight respectively, which accounts for quantity of the item (quantity defaults to 1 if not explicitly set). Weight-related fields are color coded from lightest items in green to heaviest items in red.</p>

<p>Categories are used to group items and execute queries on the data and learn insights like these:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-weight-chart.png" title="A chart representing the weight of each category of items relative to a weight of the whole pack." ></p>

<p>There’s a separate sheet where I enter item names, categories, and weights, which I then use to automatically populate values above and autofill item names in the primary sheet:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-inventory.png" title="A screenshot of an inventory tab of the packing spreadsheet." ></p>

<h2>The Technical Details</h2>

<p>I haven’t worked with Google Spreadsheets (or Excel for that matter) a lot in the past, but with an access to clear documentation (and a hundred of web searches later) it was straightforward to get the hang of the it.</p>

<p>I started off by manually populating the final result sheet, manually adjusting formulas for Container/Percentage cells, as I had no idea how I would detect the indentation yet. I like when things look pretty, so I applied conditional formatting rules right away, and the looks of the sheet really haven’t changed throughout the process.</p>

<p>Next, I created an inventory sheet, which I wanted to use as a source of data in the resulting sheet. A few Google searches and some trial &amp; error resulted in a lookup formula:</p>

<pre><code>=ArrayFormula(
 IF(
   NOT(ISBLANK($B2)),
   INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($B2, InventoryItems, 0)),
   IF(
     NOT(ISBLANK($C2)),
     INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($C2, InventoryItems, 0)),
     INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($D2, InventoryItems, 0))
   )
  )
)
</code></pre>

<p><code>ArrayFormula</code> is necessary in order to create arrays on the fly without printing intermediate results in the spreadsheet. <code>InventoryItems</code> and <code>InventoryCategories</code> are named ranges referring to item names and categories in the inventory sheet. <code>MATCH</code> finds an index of a first occurrence of the item name in the sheet, and retrieves corresponding category name. An item weight is retrieved by the exact same principle.</p>

<p>Trying to find the container weight took a lot more time, and resulted in a lot more headache. Solution for handling indentation in Google Spreadsheets wasn’t as elegant as I would have hoped for, but it got the job done:</p>

<pre><code>=ArrayFormula(
     SUM(
       $I2:INDIRECT(
         CONCATENATE(
           "$I",
           ROW() + IF(
             NOT(ISBLANK($B2)),
             MATCH(FALSE, ISBLANK($B3:$B), 0),
             MATCH(FALSE, ISBLANK($C3:$C), 0)
           ) - 1
         )
       )
     )
</code></pre>

<p>The formula above finds the first non-empty cell in a column. It starts searching from the next row (for example, for an item on a second row, we look at the third row and below). After it knows which row first non-empty cell is in, the formula turns it into a string (column $I contains item weights) and use it as an upper bound of a sum of the weights. Finished formula is a bit longer (it adds sugar to only display the number when needed), and if you’re interested - you can look it up in the spreadsheet.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-indentation.png" title="A screenshot used for explaining indentation logic." ></p>

<p>For example, in the screenshot above, the formula will start looking at cells in a column right after the &ldquo;Packing cube&rdquo;. As soon as it finds a non-empty cell (&ldquo;Nintendo Switch case&rdquo;), the formula will determine this row to be an upper boundary. The formula then will sum weights starting with a &ldquo;Packing cube&rdquo; row, and up to but not including &ldquo;Nintendo Switch case&rdquo; row.</p>

<p>The rest involved many small tweaks, adding pretty colors, hiding N/A errors and zeroes, and trying to find the perfect shade for column borders.</p>

<p>And, since you made it this far, here’s how the numbers above look in the real world:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/cleveland-trip-backpack-on-off.png" title="Side by side pictures of a packed backpack: open and closed." ></p>

<p>Hopefully you found this useful, or at least somewhat entertaining. There’s a lot of room for improvement, and I aimed to provide a framework and a few basic ideas for building a spreadsheet to accommodate one’s twisted ultralight needs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A trip to Salt Lake City]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/a-trip-to-salt-lake-city/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-13T07:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/a-trip-to-salt-lake-city</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This article is a collaboration between my partner and I.</em></p>

<p>Since moving into a studio, I have missed the freedom of taking off randomly, getting to know a different city or state and overall not being tied down to a routine or a location. I love the idea of trivializing travel, so it was only natural to have a random trip at the end of the week.</p>

<p>My partner watches <a href="http://www.thebucketlistfamily.com/">The Bucket List Family</a> on a weekly basis and caught the traveling bug as well. Unfortunately, we are not yet at the level where we can afford a 5 star trip to international locals or have companies pay for our travels (one day!). Our goal was to spend a few days going out of state to break the work week and avoid living for the weekend.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-ready-for-trip-to-slc.jpg" title="Ready for the trip to Salt Lake City." ></p>

<p>We decided to leave Northern California on Thursday afternoon for Salt Lake City, Utah as soon as we were done with work. Roughly 800 miles each way, if one counts exits and driving around sightseeing. Inspired by an acquaintance who travels the world with a folding bike, my partner and we took our bikes with us: a borrowed Brompton folding bike for my partner in the back seat, and my <a href="http://amzn.to/2xT6xT7">ZycleFix Prime</a> mounted on the rack in the rear.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/brompton-bike-in-the-backseat.jpg" title="Brompton bike in the backseat." ></p>

<p>Driving through California, Nevada, and Utah on I-80 was always one of my favorites - and it was nice to share the wonders of the world with my partner. She clocked in a lot more international travel than I did, but only been to a handful of states. It was her first time in Utah and each stop on the way to the Salt Flats exposed us to all kinds of people, different from the type of individuals we typically see inside the Silicon Valley tech bubble. We saw people with different lives, habits, hobbies, and worldviews, which to be perfectly honest, was refreshing.</p>

<p>Throughout the trip, we made it a point not to make any plans and go with the flow &ndash; be it our driving pace, entertainment or food options, or cities we decided to stay the night in. Traveling that way removed the stress associated with finding the perfect location and planning a fun trip. Don’t like the town we stopped at? Let’s keep driving. Enjoy a specific city? Let’s spend the night there. Having issues at a hotel? Back on the road we go.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/beautiful-sky-on-our-way.jpg" title="Beautiful sky as we’re driving on I-80." ></p>

<p>We found a hotel while driving on the I-80 and settled there for the night. Unfortunately the place did not have a strong enough WiFi, which led us to drive to the next town over for coffee and internet to work remotely. We ended up spending 6 hours in the coffee shop making sure that we kept ourselves well caffeinated and the servers well tipped. After a somewhat productive day, we decided to explore the city’s downtown and save the Salt Flats drive for the daytime.</p>

<p>Our Super 8 Motel in Wendover cost us around $70 for the night and was more comfortable than expected. We ended up passing out as soon as we got to the room, exhausted from the day. We tried to stay at cheaper hotels/motels, while avoiding shady looking places. We would most often pick the 2nd or 3rd cheapest option. We never stayed in one place for more than a night and lucked out every time we got ourselves a room. Every room we slept in was clean and we even managed to squeeze in a daily workout before the start of each day.</p>

<p>Keeping a healthy diet on the other hand was a whole other challenge. Between cafes, restaurants and late night cravings, we failed at maintaining proper eating habits and saving on food. We spent around $300 on food alone. Eating is definitely one area for improvement, especially as we decide to travel more. Dieting is hard and dieting on the road is even harder.</p>

<p>On Saturday, we finally headed to Utah and stopped at a rest stop by the Salt Flats. The view was marvelous and cold for an October day. We left the Salt Flats for a mall, City Creek Center, in Salt Lake City where we had another amazingly delicious and unhealthy lunch. To feel better about our life choices, we used our bikes to get some cardio and discover the city on two-wheels. We biked through Memory Grove Park, crashed a wedding, and biked almost to the Capitol. Almost. Due to Salt Lake’s incredible, deadly hills. Next time, SLC, next time we shall conquer you.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/salt-flats-are-gorgeous.jpg" title="Beautiful Salt Flats." ></p>

<p>After a day of biking and testing each other&rsquo;s patience, we decided to go for a date night and talk through our attempts at making life on the road work. Traveling solo is a very different experience than traveling with a partner. We chatted over Brazilian BBQ, another unhealthy choice, and agreed that we needed to include time alone as part of our travel routine and constantly check in with each other.</p>

<p>We headed to the hotel and decided to leave back for California after breakfast on Sunday. Oh, and on the topic of car, the subject of staying in the Prius or camping came up a few times. We even prepared our tents in that event but the cold weather and the thought of a hot shower took priority&hellip; Oh well, hotel Prius will get more use some other time.</p>

<p>In one day, we drove from Utah back to Northern California. We have different memories of the road back. For her, it was long and slow. For me as a driver, it passed within a blink of an eye. Overall, our trip to Utah was a success and we learned a lot:</p>

<ol>
<li>Nothing can replace the freedom associated with the absence of a plan. When there&rsquo;s no agenda or times to be at specific places - you&rsquo;re never late, never in a hurry, and you&rsquo;ve always seen more than you planned for. It allowed us to be surprised and delighted by places we encountered without imposing our pace on said locations.</li>
<li>Taking time for oneself is a necessity when traveling with someone else. Time alone does not always mean actually being alone. It can be whatever works for you as a couple. For us, it’s spending time on our devices while sitting next to each other.</li>
<li>Approaching each location with an open mind. You are not always going to get to travel to exotic <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/him-and-her-whats-inside-the-bag/">places like the Bahamas</a>, but the opportunity to fall in love with a place or its people is always there.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Him and her: what's inside the bag?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/him-and-her-whats-inside-the-bag/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-15T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/him-and-her-whats-inside-the-bag</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Living in a car for nearly a year made me pick up number of travel-related skills, here and there. Having limited available space forced &ldquo;less is more&rdquo; philosophy on me, and it&rsquo;s something I carried over into more stationary life. Right now I&rsquo;m taking a break from car dwelling and living in a small apartment in Bay Area. It didn&rsquo;t stop my love for travel though, as I&rsquo;m writing this entry on my flight to Nassau, Bahamas. 5 days at the destination, leisure. One of the many weekends I&rsquo;m not home.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/two-backpacks-on-a-bed.jpg" title="Both of our backpacks, bigger is hers." ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not traveling alone this time, and my traveling partner has a similar outlook on travel.</p>

<h2>Him</h2>

<p>Less is more. Every trip starts with packing. I use my <a href="http://amzn.to/2xHIV2F">eBags Motherlode Weekender backpack</a>, which is about the perfect size for me when it&rsquo;s compressed tightly. I can probably fit in double the stuff I packed in the backpack, but I love having room in case I pick something up at the destination.</p>

<p>I never have to check in my bag, and it&rsquo;s light enough to carry on my back without any strain. I can explore my destination as soon as I arrive, without the need to find arrangement for my bags.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/his-opened-backpack.jpg" title="My backpack, open." ></p>

<p>I pack minimally, only having two-three sets of each type of clothing. I hand-wash the clothes I wear before I go to bed. I cycle through a total of 3 pairs of undergarments - most dry overnight as I sleep.</p>

<p>Furthermore, all my outfits can be mixed and matched together, so I don&rsquo;t have to worry about pairing tops, bottoms, and shoes. I like to think I have some sense of style to, for those wondering. Most people I meet won&rsquo;t likely see me for more then one-two days in a row, and those who do are not likely to pay attention to my small wardrobe - as long as it looks clean and sharp.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s what the clothing items for this trip look like:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/his-stuff-inside-the-backpack.jpg" title="Clothing items inside the backpack." ></p>

<ul>
<li>Business-casual dress-shirt.</li>
<li>Two T-shirts.</li>
<li>Pair of shorts.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/2zpE3Bf">Icebreaker merino underwear</a>, 2 pairs.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/2xHk92J">Darn Tough socks</a>, 2 pairs.</li>
<li>Jacket.</li>
<li>Swimming trunks.</li>
<li>Travel towel, for the beach.</li>
<li>Flip flops.</li>
<li>Workout outfit:

<ul>
<li>Tank top.</li>
<li>Shorts.</li>
<li>Sports underwear.</li>
<li>Running sneakers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>All of the above is contained within a single <a href="http://amzn.to/2yLgwxz">packing cube</a> and a travel shoe bag.</p>

<p>Doesn&rsquo;t sound like a lot, but it&rsquo;s plenty (add the outfit I&rsquo;m wearing on the plane - pants, T-shirt, sweater, shoes, pair of underwear, socks). The above lets me have outfits for all kinds of events, activities, and anticipated weather at the destination.</p>

<p>My personal hygiene stuff fits in a dettachable bag which comes with the backpack. Not much special here:</p>

<ul>
<li>Toothbrushes.</li>
<li>Toothpaste.</li>
<li>Floss.</li>
<li>Deodorant.</li>
<li>Hairbrush.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/2zrcN5t">Quick dry scrub net</a>.</li>
<li>Contact lenses.</li>
</ul>


<p>For entertainment and downtime I have my trusty Google Pixel C (with attached keyboard) and a pair of cheap apple ear buds. Bonus point for USB C standard - I only need to use a single charger for my tablet and a phone.</p>

<h2>Her</h2>

<p>Traveling with a space obsessed partner <em>(him: Hey!)</em> has forced me to look at packing in a different way. I first experimented with the idea of minimalism after watching The BucketList Family and avoiding airline fees is always a bonus. With every trips, I refined my set up. While I am not as lightweight and nimble as my partner, I have made significant improvements to my travel routine and picked up a few tips and tricks from him.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/her-opened-backpack.jpg" title="Her backpack, open." ></p>

<p>For example, the <a href="http://amzn.to/2zbhUG2">eBag Weekender</a> was my first real travel purchase, which I made sure to always have ready for use, meaning that it&rsquo;s always stocked with toiletries, travel documents and packing cubes. Given my propensity for sweating, I upgraded to a <a href="http://amzn.to/2yLgwxz">clean/dirty packing cube</a> and a <a href="http://amzn.to/2hJibsQ">charcoal odor remover</a> for my workout outfit.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/her-packing-cubes.jpg" title="Her packing cubes in a backpack." ></p>

<p>For this trip, this is what is inside my bag including the clothes I am wearing to travel:</p>

<p>On me:</p>

<ul>
<li>A tank top.</li>
<li>A hoodie.</li>
<li>A denim jacket.</li>
<li>Lululemon leggings.</li>
<li>Bra and underwear.</li>
<li>Sandals</li>
</ul>


<p>In my luggage:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/her-stuff-inside-the-backpack.jpg" title="What&rsquo;s in her luggage." ></p>

<ul>
<li>Button on shirt.</li>
<li>Tank top.</li>
<li>T-shirt.</li>
<li>Pair of pants.</li>
<li>Pair of shorts.</li>
<li>Rain jacket.</li>
<li>5 pairs of underwear (one is never too prepared in terms of underwear, and this is where I refuse to become a minimalist).</li>
<li>Workout oufit:

<ul>
<li>Leggings.</li>
<li>Dry fit T-shirt.</li>
<li>One pair of socks.</li>
<li>Workout bra.</li>
<li>Sports sneakers.</li>
<li>Bikini</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>Toiletries:</p>

<ul>
<li>Foundation.</li>
<li>Makeup brush.</li>
<li>Travel-friendly lotion.</li>
<li>Natural oil for face washing purposes.</li>
<li>Feminine hygiene soap</li>
<li>Ingrown hair serum.</li>
<li>L&#8217;Instant de Guerlain perfume (while the current bottle takes a lot of space and adds weight, I have yet to find a travel friendly way to carry it).</li>
</ul>


<p>If you haven&rsquo;t noticed, my backpack is bigger, and my setup is a bit heavier. To be perfectly honest, I am not yet fully on board with this whole minimalistic travel but I have got to say, my shoulders are thankful.</p>

<h2>Making Yourself at Home</h2>

<p>We&rsquo;ve learned from <a href="http://thebucketlistfamily.com">the bucket list family</a> that it&rsquo;s really important to unpack as soon as we get to a hotel. Especially since it&rsquo;s easy to do when there&rsquo;s little clothing in the bags. This way we feel at home whenever we go, even if we&rsquo;re just staying at a hotel for a single night. Every item is in it&rsquo;s place, and there&rsquo;s no digging through the bags for clothes or gadgets.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/our-hotel-in-nassau-bahamas.jpg" title="Our hotel in Nassau, Bahamas." ></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve also found that we really value downtime, every day we travel. Taking time to unwind (however long it needs to be) in the hotel room, a coffee shop, or anywhere else helps take the edge off flying and booking accommodations and the subconscious pressure to have fun as a pair.</p>

<p>We&rsquo;ve learned this the hard way on our first trip together. Our days were packed with activities and sightseeing stops, and we were at each other&rsquo;s throats by the end of the trip. Lesson learned.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Journey of a friend]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/journey-of-a-friend/"/>
    <updated>2017-05-09T01:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/journey-of-a-friend</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>A close friend of mine has a story similar to mine. She wanted to share it for a while now, and I&rsquo;m humbled she chose my blog as a medium for telling her inspiring story to the strangers on the Internet:</em></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/friends-trip-plane.jpg" title="At Narita Airport, Japan." ></p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t count the number of times I have attempted to tell this story on paper. It all started 8 months ago when my then-husband, let&rsquo;s call him Carl, told me that he no longer loved me and was in love with someone else. There are a few moments in life that seem to happen in slow motion and this was one of them. Until then, my life had been being Carl&rsquo;s wife and in the blink of an eye, I had to figure out who I was in a world without Carl. I forced myself to write every thoughts I had, dark, depressed, once a day but it didn&rsquo;t stick. I bought various domain names hoping that it would give me the final push to start writing all this down but all the sites remained &ldquo;under construction&rdquo;. So here is my final attempt to write this up, organize my thoughts and hopefully let someone going through this know that they are not alone. How did I get here? Well funny you should ask, pull up a chair and listen to my tale.</p>

<p>Carl and I met when we were 22 and 18 respectively. It was far from love at first sight but he intrigued me. I had just got out of an unhealthy relationship and wanted something different and Carl was that, unapologetically himself. Up until then, I had always felt pressure to conform to the idea of who others wanted me to be and meeting Carl, who let&rsquo;s be honest was a straight nerd, was surprisingly refreshing and attractive. We dated for 5 years before getting married. We struggled with money throughout the first years of our relationship so when the opportunity to make more at a job I was unqualified for presented itself, we jumped at the chance. We packed our bags and moved for my job. Thus started the beginning of the end. I was so focused on keeping said job that I overworked, became a ball of nerves and lost all desires to do anything outside of work. While I struggled with the demand of the job, Carl found refuge with his younger, funner coworkers. We started living separate lives, which eventually led up to the fateful day when my husband told me that he loved someone else.</p>

<p>I will not bore you with the details of my attempts to become a stable, contributing member of society. It included a lot of sleepless night, Nutella for dinner, and lies. I would smile everyday as I got to work, joked with co-workers and call family members and friends to discuss everything and anything when deep down all I wanted to do was to crawl in a dark place and wallow in my sadness. This period led to a lot of physical and mental changes. I lost 20 pounds in 2 months due to stress but the vain person in me was happy to see myself get skinny. Mentally, I had to come clean to my family and explain to them how I became the first divorced person in a deeply catholic family. I created a smaller, more dependable community of friends, most of them divorced or separated who could provide me with a different perspective. I had to admit to my manager that I could not continue work as is. Maintaining the lies became exhausting and emotionally draining. One had to give and after a heart to heart with my manager, I decided to cash out all my vacation hours and head out to Southeast Asia for a month.</p>

<p>Prior to Southeast Asia, I had never vacationed alone. For the first time in my life, I was in charge of my itinerary and my own entertainment. It was overwhelming. After discussing the trip with veteran solo travelers, I only purchased one ticket. All I knew was my departing and arrival date from and to the US. I arrived at my first stop, Ho Chi Minh City, at midnight on a blazing hot night. The bustle of the city took me aback and made me question the trip in its entirety. I was running away and I knew it. I have always thought of myself as a strong person but dealing with this separation made me feel like a scared kid. Just as I was going through this mental exercise, my cab driver hit a motorcyclist and the impact broke one of his side view mirrors. The driver angrily got out of the car and argued with the individual he had just hit. They spoke in Vietnamese for what felt like hours and came back without explanations. At that point, I was sure that this entire trip was a mistake and if I had spoken the language, I would have asked the driver to turn and drop me back at the airport.</p>

<p>The rest of the drive to the hotel was much calmer with the occasional surprise looks from locals seeing a black tourist through a taxi window at midnight. Blame it on stress, jet lag or even regret but for the first time in months I slept for more than 4 hours. Somewhat invigorated by the night of sleep, I decided to venture into the city to find food. After multiple failed attempts to cross one of the main traffic arteries, I gave up and sat down miserably looking at a bowl of pho from a restaurant located in the same block as my hotel. The Ho Chi Minh City traffic had won once again. I sat by a window seat, staring into the street, dreading the rest of this Southeast Asia trip. To travel Asia required an adventure spirit and it only took me 2 days to recognize that this was not one of my hidden talents. I told myself, only half believing it, that my second stop might be different but deep down, I knew I was on my way to yet another disappointing time.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/friends-trip-sleep.png" title="Screenshot of sleep activity during the trip." ></p>

<p>Bangkok was a life changing stop for my trip and myself as a person. I had contacted a Turkish-based traveler on CouchSurfing visiting Bangkok during the same time. I was excited to meet up with someone that could understand the struggles of being in an unfamiliar country. This guy learned English by watching American sitcoms but did not let his basic knowledge of English or his lack of Thai stop him. It led to some interesting conversations about the meaning of &ldquo;Netflix and Chill&rdquo; and other American colloquialisms. Seeing him tackle the challenges of navigating a foreign city showed me what my journey could look like. Not only did he help me see the wonders of being open to the world, but he also inadvertently started my process of self love. Let me explain. To avoid having to carry a heavy suitcase and pay airline fees, I limited my wardrobe to whatever could fit in a carry-on backpack. As a relatively fashion-focused person, this decision was uncomfortable. With that in mind and the unforgiving sun, I was either dripped in sweat or looking like a lost 1920s explorer. Having someone still think that I looked good in those conditions did wonders for my broken self esteem. We spend 4 adventures filled days and parted ways. We still talk to each other and I am grateful to have encountered him so early on during my trip. I finally embraced the lack of structure and decided to thrive through it. Remember this word &ldquo;Thrive&rdquo;, it will come back later on in this story.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/friends-trip-construction.jpg" title="Temple in Bangkok." ></p>

<p>After Bangkok, I headed to Chiang Mai for the Lantern Festival. Given my positive experience with CouchSurfing, I decided to continue using it  to meet locals and travelers throughout my stops. I used all the lessons learned in Bangkok and forced myself to open up to people. I had a heart wrenching conversation with an American girl trying to find herself in the world despite familial and societal pressures. We quickly bonded and within minutes were sharing our deepest darkest fears. In addition to looking differently at people, I started focusing on things that made me happy. I took a Thai cooking class, a skill I desperately lacked in, and learned Muay Thai. With each new activity I undertook, I felt a change inside of me. I was slowly starting to fall in love with myself.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/friends-trip-market.jpg" title="Cooking class in Chiang Mai." ></p>

<p>Next stop: Singapore. A few coworkers happened to be there around the same time and I had always been intrigued by the country. I experienced the country&rsquo;s renowned cleanliness, mix of cultures and wide array of food options. It was in Singapore that I learned another fact about myself: I loved meeting new people. I struck conversations with random people in elevators, buses or hotels. Not having an itinerary turned out to be a blessing. I ended up extending my time in Singapore and enjoyed some retail therapy from one of the cities&#8217; amazing malls.</p>

<p>My goal for this trip was not only self discovery but also to be fully emerged in each country’s history and culture. So that meant that I purposely landed in each new locations not knowing anything about religious beliefs, language and social norms. It worked in my favor up until I arrived in Kuala Lumpur. On my first day in the country, I had planned to follow my typical plan and visit the national and art museums to learn about Malaysian culture. Unfortunately, I arrived during yellow and red shirt protests. All local attractions were closed and I ended up smack in  a protest. While I am sure I was never in any real danger, being stuck in the middle of a screaming and upset group of people was scary. I took refuge in a nearby mall and ended up being stranded there for 4 hours. No taxis or Ubers wanted to come to my location due to road closures and fears of property damages. With each hour, I got more and more scared and worried. When I was finally able to get to my hotel, I made arrangements to leave the day after to go to Cambodia. I am hoping to go back to KL and get a chance to see all the city has to offer.</p>

<p>After my failure in Malaysia, I landed in Siem Reap defeated. Cambodia was breathtaking. It was the first time that I saw real poverty and luxury in the same location. It was in Siem Reap that I realized how small my problems really were. I saw and talked to people struggling to afford day to day life and here I was suffering from a broken heart. Siem Reap helped me refocus and gave me a different perspective. It wasn&rsquo;t about what my problems were but how I approached them. I was not as powerless as I thought I was. I could make the choice to not let my situations impact me and move forward. There, I met some of the most life-loving individuals. As we were exchanging travel stories and tips, we all realized that we were into the same type of music. One of the members of the group ran to his hotel room and brought back his turntables. We had an impromptu dance party in the middle of Siem Reap. I sang and danced my heart away to familiar songs in a an unfamiliar land with unfamiliar people. At that time, I realized that I was happy. For the first time in months, there were no hidden emotions behind my smile, it was pure happiness and I never wanted it to end.</p>

<p>I went to Angkor Wat at sunrise and felt lost and transported to a different world visiting all the cultural sites of the country. The Tuol Seng prison and the lives lost there forced me to put my life into perspective. I realized the following facts that I knew deep down but up until then was unwilling to accept: 1) I was getting divorced, 2) I was deeply hurt that I wasn&rsquo;t enough for my husband , 3) I still loved Carl and needed to respect his choice, 4) This was not the end for me. Weirdly, coming to these realizations made me calmer. I knew what I had to do. I had to use the remaining days of this trip to try to discover as much as I could about myself.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/friends-trip-skyline.jpg" title="Sunrise at Angkor Wat, Siem Reap." ></p>

<p>Along with self discovery and adventure-filled days came the not-so fun ones. Thanksgiving day landed while I was in Phnom Penh. As an immigrant, Thanksgiving meant spending time with Carl&rsquo;s family. Up until Thanksgiving day, I thought about Carl during my trip but never more than &ldquo;Carl would have loved eating this, or visiting this area or enjoyed talking with this individual&rdquo;. But as I was staring at my plate of mashed potatoes and turkey, I not only felt a overwhelming sense of loss but also felt shame. Only a few hours prior, I was reveling in the country&rsquo;s history and congratulating myself in having a fresh new perspective on life. I could not finish my plate and walked back to my hotel room beaten. For the first time since I started on this adventure, I was happy that I was traveling alone. I spent the rest of my day watching TV locked in my hotel room.</p>

<p>After 3 weeks on the road, I headed back to Vietnam for my last week abroad. For convenience, I reserved a room in the same hotel I had checked at the beginning of this trip. I suddenly realized that the person who checked in 3 weeks ago was not the person who was walking in. I couldn&rsquo;t put my finger on what it was specifically but I felt more confident and more at peace with myself. A former coworker traveling in Ho Chi Minh City at the same time reached out and we connected for dinner. His first words to me were &ldquo;&hellip; so, what is going on, where is your husband?&rdquo; We hadn&rsquo;t seen each other for 4 years and apparently, my social media accounts had become a &ldquo;Eat, Pray, Love&rdquo; tribute. I explained my current situation, no longer ashamed of the fact that I had a failed marriage, and we traded travel stories. He had not left his hotel room until our meeting because he was overwhelmed by the city, especially the traffic. I can&rsquo;t put into words how satisfying it was for me to be able to teach him how to cross the road. I fondly remembered my old self, seating defeated in front of a bowl of pho. I couldn&rsquo;t have engineered a better end to 4 wonderful weeks in paradise.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/friends-trip-boat.jpg" title="On the way to floating market in Can Tho, Vietnam." ></p>

<p>Of course I glanced over many more experiences, people and locations visited. It would take days to write it all. I came back to the US on a high that I knew would not last but I was determined to keep it as long as possible. I had felt true happiness and connected with new people for the first time in 7 months. I was accepted even after I showed my true, deeply flawed self, but most importantly, I met myself. I discovered the foundations of who I was, what made me smile, happy and tick. I realized that I could survive, not just survive, I could thrive in a foreign environment and to commemorate it, I tattooed “Thrive” on my shoulder to always remind myself of that feeling. Told you that word was going to come back.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prius adventures, a year later]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/prius-adventures-a-year-later/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-16T17:11:38-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/prius-adventures-a-year-later</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It&rsquo;s time to write more about my adventures. I&rsquo;ve been traveling and living in my car for nearly a year now, mostly full-time (excluding hotels on infrequent business trips, occasional friends&#8217; couches, or AirBnB a few times I was sick or wanted a home). I&rsquo;d love to share what I&rsquo;ve learned over the past year.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/camping-in-california.jpg" title="Camping in California." ></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how a typical conversation with someone who just learned I&rsquo;m living in my car goes:</p>

<h2>You live in <em>that?</em></h2>

<p>Yes I do. I think I need to start from the beginning.</p>

<p>About a year ago I wasn&rsquo;t in a very good place emotionally. I&rsquo;ve been going through a divorce, my dream company declined my job application (spoiler: I got the job this year, yay), and my landlord decided that 12 tiny houses on a property isn&rsquo;t enough and it&rsquo;s time to kick everyone out to build a more dense apartment complex. I didn&rsquo;t do much outside of going to work and sleeping.</p>

<p>I think I saw an opportunity to do something drastic with my life, and I decided to take a leap of faith. I gave away everything I couldn&rsquo;t fit in the back of the car, and set on a road trip across continental United States (after spending a month doing test drives and adjusting my setup dozens of times).</p>

<p>The experience turned out to be more enjoyable than having a house.</p>

<h2>How do you even fit in there?!</h2>

<p>Everyone I talk to thinks the space is really cramped up, and I have to sleep curled into a ball in the trunk (or something along those lines).</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/feet-under-blanket.jpg" title="Pictures make it look really cramped up, but it&rsquo;s rather spacious inside." ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m 5&#8217;11&#8221;, and I have a flat twin-width bed in that&rsquo;s around 7 feet long (it&rsquo;s been awhile since I measured). I sleep on an inflatable pad wrapped in a sleeping bag, on top of another sleeping bag all wrapped in a silk sleeping bag cover - my composite mattress is about 3 inches thick. I use regular blankets and pillows, adding or removing a few depending on the temperature outside.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s one of the most comfortable beds I&rsquo;ve ever slept on.</p>

<h2>Poor soul, want to crash on my couch?</h2>

<p>This is an offer I get as soon as somebody learns I&rsquo;m living in a car (it&rsquo;s right up there with &ldquo;You must be saving so much money not paying rent!&rdquo;). Most people are really nice, and offer a place to stay. I think it stems from an understandable notion that one probably would only live in a car because of being in a bad situation.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/inside-of-the-car-view-from-the-back.jpg" title="View of the bed from the back of the car." ></p>

<p>Oddly enough I really enjoy the lifestyle, and I always reject the offers (always appreciate them though). Sometimes I contemplate getting a small RV or a van, but I&rsquo;m way to attached to air conditioning on demand and 50 mpg on the highway. But I probably won&rsquo;t need to crash on your couch.</p>

<p>I think the TL;DR here is that majority of people are really nice, once you get out and get to interact with them enough.</p>

<h2>Why on Earth are you still living in a car?</h2>

<p>There&rsquo;s more than one reason at this point. Part of it is that it has become a habit now. The biggest reason is probably all the fun things it has forced me to do.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve met a lot of cool people, tried out so many things I would&rsquo;ve never considered trying, and found exciting hobbies I would&rsquo;ve never had otherwise. I&rsquo;m also now in a great shape physically since I usually have to hit up the gym to shower.</p>

<p>It also made me confront my inner demons, since car living tends to consistently provide me with time to be alone with my thoughts - be it driving somewhere, or falling asleep in an area where I wouldn&rsquo;t want to use electronics. I feel more in tune with myself, and I can close my eyes without being afraid of stream of thoughts keeping me awake at night.</p>

<h2>That&rsquo;s cool! What else is inside?</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/before-and-after-bike-rack.jpg" title="Bike rack: before and after." ></p>

<h3>The front</h3>

<p>I try to keep driver&rsquo;s seat and front passenger seat area clean and empty, with storing some low key items in passenger seat leg space &ndash; portable 12V vacuum, water jug, water boiler/thermos.</p>

<p>The front seats are separated from the back by a dark curtain. Unless you shine a (powerful) flashlight inside a car it&rsquo;s almost impossible to tell the curtain is there.</p>

<h3>The back</h3>

<p><img src="/images/posts/window-cutout-from-the-inside.jpg" title="In addition to curtains I also have custom-made window cutouts." ></p>

<p>One of the passenger seats is lowered to make a bed. The bed is extended with a wooden panel specifically made for this purpose which creates a flat surface about 7 foot long. A mattress with a blanket and some throws creates /a nice homey look.</p>

<p>Under the bed is &ldquo;the basement&rdquo; &ndash; large clear container where I store winter clothes and things I rarely use. If I&rsquo;m camping extra water jugs go here as well. And some bicycle maintenance stuff, and extra pairs of shoes.</p>

<p>I use the other rear passenger seat as my primary relaxing area when I&rsquo;m inside the car. There&rsquo;s a little trashcan stuck to the floor in between the seats.</p>

<h3>Cargo and the bike</h3>

<p>There&rsquo;s an old suitcase I use for organizing various cooking and camping supplies. It&rsquo;s split into nine compartments by some separators I&rsquo;ve put together. This is where I have some freeze dried veggies, spices, grains and pasta, cooking oils, camping pots and pans, equipment for cleaning the dishes, etc. On top of the suitcase is a backpack where I keep clothes. There&rsquo;s also a propane burner, camping table and a chair, as well as a toiletry kit. Dirty laundry goes in a dry bag.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/cooking-supplies-in-the-suitcase.jpg" title="Cooking supplies in a suitcase." ></p>

<p>I also have a bike strapped to the outside of the car, exploring places by bike after arriving to a new city is very rewarding!</p>

<h2>Isn&rsquo;t it dangerous?</h2>

<p>You often read stories of people suffocating in their own cars, and it&rsquo;s something to be aware of. There are a few rules I follow to be safe, and there are three main dangers here:</p>

<ol>
<li>Carbon monoxide poisoning.</li>
<li>Carbon dioxide poisoning.</li>
<li>Extreme temperatures.</li>
</ol>


<p>I sleep with carbon monoxide alarm not far from my head, and my car is a hybrid &ndash; meaning it only turns itself on once in a while when batteries need to be recharged. Sometimes I sleep with my car on, and sometimes not. The alarm never went off so far (it works, I check regularly).</p>

<p>Carbon dioxide (stuff you exhale) poisoning is not a silent killer (unlike carbon monoxide), humans are pretty good at detecting high concentration of CO2 &ndash; panic attack on par with a headache are a rather clear sign of this happening. I keep windows cracked open most of the time, plus my AC is often on.</p>

<p>I love sleeping at low temperatures (50-60F is my comfort zone for snuggling up under a blanket), but if local forecast suggests the temperature will drop below 50F at night - I make sure to sleep with AC on. If it&rsquo;s below freezing - I roll up the windows, otherwise I still keep them cracked open a little.</p>

<p>And if it&rsquo;s really cold and I don&rsquo;t want to run AC all night, or I just feel like I want to stay inside for a bit - I can just get AirBnB for a couple of nights. Speaking of, by pure chance I stayed at Gayle Laakmann McDowell&rsquo;s guest house few weeks ago, and I left with great memories and a signed copy of Cracking the Code Interview. Bonus point for meeting cool people.</p>

<h2>How does Prius AC work anyway?</h2>

<p>This question pops up often enough to address here (along with condensation concerns from seasoned vandwellers).</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a hybrid with two electric motors assisting the internal combustion engine. The electric motors power up from a ~1.3 kWh battery, which is recharged using the engine and regenerative brakes. That battery is connected to the 12V battery, and as long as there&rsquo;s gas in the car &ndash; both batteries will be charged. In practice, if the car isn&rsquo;t moving, engine turns on every half an hour or so for a little under a minute to recharge the batteries.</p>

<p>This allows one to keep the car on and use the AC throughout the night. AC also keeps the moisture level at bay, preventing condensation. I also noticed that when I don&rsquo;t use the AC cracked windows help with condensation (I have rain guards for stealth and keeping the rain out).</p>

<h2>Um, how do you do bathroom stuff?</h2>

<p>If we&rsquo;re talking about changing - there&rsquo;s plenty of space in the back of the car to change.</p>

<p>For hygiene - I use gym showers (I take quite a lot of classes), or wet wipes if I&rsquo;m out camping or shower is otherwise unavailable. I&rsquo;m now kind of an expert on all sorts of wipes. Any restroom works for brushing my teeth at night, and in US it&rsquo;s very difficult not to be within the vicinity of a public bathroom.</p>

<h2>Where do you park at night?</h2>

<p>Rest stops are the best when I travel, since everyone on a rest stop is just resting/sleeping in their car.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-lit-up-at-night.jpg" title="Christmas lights make inside more homey." ></p>

<p>There are so many places to park: since this is just a passenger car, anywhere where cars can park is good. Usually somewhere with either a lot of foot traffic (or the exact opposite). Parking lots of 24/7 business, residential areas, anywhere and anytime.</p>

<h2>What do your friends and coworkers say?</h2>

<p>Most colleagues and acquaintances don&rsquo;t know, since it&rsquo;s not really a topic that pops up during a normal conversation. I go to work and social events well groomed, with clean clothes, and (I&rsquo;d like to think) demonstrating a sense of style.</p>

<p>Few friends and colleagues that do know that I live in the car don&rsquo;t see it as anything out of the ordinary (past the initial shock of course). I can&rsquo;t remember the last time conversation got stirred towards car living with any of my close friends. A few are rather jealous but reluctant to make the move. I try not to preach.</p>

<p>My love life surprisingly didn&rsquo;t suffer. Maybe it&rsquo;s because I tend to pursue women just as odd as me, but me living in a car didn&rsquo;t have any negative effects, and even got me a date or two. If someone doesn&rsquo;t want to go out with you because of living arrangements - they would probably not make a good partner in a long run.</p>

<h2>Do strangers bother you?</h2>

<p>When you observe people you start noticing how much everyone&rsquo;s concerned with what people think of them. In fact, most people so concerned with themselves - that they don&rsquo;t look around. Encounters with people who notice I live in a car are nearly non-existent. Nobody cares to look inside one of the hundred cars in a parking lot or parked on the side of the street.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve had a few rather friendly encounters with parking lot security, with people usually just demonstrating concern. Until I share my setup that is, then concern is often replacement with mild jealousy.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/making-a-meal-at-a-rest-stop.jpg" title="I sometimes make meals at rest stops." ></p>

<p>Most encounters with strangers approaching me happen at rest stops, since I usually don&rsquo;t hide much &ndash; there are enough misfits and travelers. Every encounter like that I&rsquo;ve had was positive, with people commenting on how amazing my setup is, how they wished they could do a similar thing, or sharing a story about their own travels.</p>

<h2>How do you not go crazy?</h2>

<p>This is where the fun part starts. You see, the thing about living in the car is how boring it is. There&rsquo;s really not much you can do in a confined space. So I have to get out of my way to entertain myself.</p>

<p>I take a lot of classes like various martial arts or archery. I tried miniature painting, rock climbing, long distance cycling. There are numerous things I&rsquo;m &ldquo;forced&rdquo; to do in order to keep myself entertained.</p>

<p>There are a lot of things I do inside the car too. Writing or coding (even though I prefer coffee shops), rare indulgence in video games (I recently picked up a gaming laptop for this), guitalele (it&rsquo;s a ukulele-sized guitar), reading. Drawing, keeping a journal, or just relaxing.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/laptop-hooked-up-to-the-headrest.jpg" title="I setup laptop at an eye level and use external keyboard." ></p>

<p>And of course there are people. When I travel I end up meeting a lot of different people. I often get invited to join somebody at a campsite, and we&rsquo;d cook a meal together or share some stories. Or somebody sitting next to me in a coffee shop works in the same industry and we grab lunch to mingle and share interesting ideas. Wherever I go I get lucky enough to make friends for a couple of minutes, hours, days, and sometimes months.</p>

<h2>What&rsquo;s next for you?</h2>

<p>For now, I&rsquo;m used to living in a car. I sometimes pop by AirBnBs or friends&#8217; places for a couple of days, but I wouldn&rsquo;t say I enjoy being tied down to a single location for a long period of time.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/cycling-by-the-ocean.jpg" title="Cycling on the West Coast is the best." ></p>

<p>I&rsquo;m contemplating getting an RV to be able to stand up inside and have more room and privacy, but potential difficulties with air conditioning at night, atrocious gas mileage, and inefficient and noisy generators for my power usage are a concern of mine.</p>

<p>Once in a while I contemplate getting myself an apartment. Since it&rsquo;s now winter I end up staying in AirBnBs more often, but I feel like having a place to call home makes it harder for me to a fight a lazy person inside me. I like when that person is forced to learn, explore, and create.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
