<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: work | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/work/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-17T12:16:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Eisenhower matrix]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-eisenhower-matrix/"/>
    <updated>2023-07-10T08:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-eisenhower-matrix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Eisenhower matrix, sometimes known as the priority matrix, is an invaluable
planning tool, and something I have been consistently using for the better part
of the last decade.</p>

<p>As someone who has a short attention span and easily gets overwhelmed, I find
Eisenhower matrix to be an invaluable tool in allowing me to focus on what&rsquo;s
important, rather than what&rsquo;s right in front of me.</p>

<p>Oh, I still struggle to make sure that things that are important to me are
what matters to others, but that&rsquo;s a whole different battle - at the very least
I&rsquo;m able to keep my own head straight, and that&rsquo;s a win in my book.</p>

<p>Without any further ado, I present to you the decision making framework
developed and popularized by Dwight D. Eisenhower, the 34th president of the
United States (and clearly a notorious efficiency nut).</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/eisenhower-matrix.png" title="Picture of an Eisenhower matrix: vertical axis titled &ldquo;Importance&rdquo;, horizontal axis titled &ldquo;Urgency&rdquo;, and four quadrants titled &ldquo;Do now&rdquo;, &ldquo;Schedule&rdquo;, &ldquo;Delegate&rdquo;, and &ldquo;Eliminate&rdquo;." ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s pretty simple, really. Take everything from your long single-file To-Do
list, and place it on the matrix based on its urgency and importance. Work
through the matrix in the following order:</p>

<ul>
<li>Urgent and important: get these done, now.</li>
<li>Important, but not urgent: decide when you want to do these, actively make
time for yourself to work on those.</li>
<li>Urgent, but not important: delegate (read on below if you have no one to
delegate to).</li>
<li>Not urgent and not important: take time to eliminate these tasks.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Do now: a common pitfall</h2>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy to throw everything into the &ldquo;urgent and important&rdquo; pile. In reality,
that&rsquo;s not often the case. If you find yourself throwing everything in the first
quadrant - I implore you to think of your tasks in relative terms. Out of
everything on your mind, I&rsquo;m sure some things are more important than others.</p>

<p>I find that over time most of my work shifts into a single quadrant (usually the
&ldquo;important, but not urgent&rdquo;), and I find it helpful to redistribute those, or
populate the matrix from scratch.</p>

<h2>Schedule: mindful use of time</h2>

<p>One of the goals of the Eisenhower Matrix is to increase visibility into how you
spend your time. While it&rsquo;s easy to spend most of the time in the &ldquo;urgent and
important&rdquo; quadrant, the best work happens in the &ldquo;important, but not urgent&rdquo;
section of the matrix. That&rsquo;s where the best use of your time is, and that&rsquo;s
where most of the energy and attention should be spent.</p>

<p>Otherwise you&rsquo;re just running around like a chicken with its head cut off,
although I can sympathise with the difficulty of getting out of the urgency
trap. It&rsquo;s not trivial, and probably downright impossible in some cases.</p>

<p>This is where the biggest pitfall of the Eisenhower matrix lays in my
experience. You want to maximize amount of time spent in the &ldquo;schedule&rdquo;
quadrant, but you don&rsquo;t want to end up with a massive list that becomes a yet
another To Do list, because <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/why-i-threw-away-my-to-do-list/">one dimensional To-Do lists suck</a>.</p>

<h2>Delegate: to whom?</h2>

<p>Not everyone has someone to delegate work to. Or not everything can be
delegated. In these cases, I treat the &ldquo;delegate&rdquo; bucket the same as
&ldquo;eliminate&rdquo;. Hopefully that won&rsquo;t come back to bite me in the future.</p>

<h2>Eliminate: it&rsquo;s hard</h2>

<p>I really like following up on things, to a fault. I don&rsquo;t like leaving loose
ends, unanswered emails, or unspoken expectations. I find it helpful to schedule
time to explicitly eliminate certain work, and communicate explicit expectations
to everyone around me about that. Because of that, that&rsquo;s where the most of my
procrastination happens. Telling people &ldquo;no&rdquo; isn&rsquo;t always easy, and I still
don&rsquo;t have the best process for combing through the &ldquo;Eliminate&rdquo; quadrant.</p>

<p>I know many people are a lot more comfortable letting unimportant things quietly
fall through the cracks, and there&rsquo;s nothing wrong with that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[High stakes email checklist]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/high-stakes-email-checklist/"/>
    <updated>2023-07-06T13:05:13-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/high-stakes-email-checklist</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m making a little cheat sheet for myself. As I progress in my career, much of
my work revolves around communication, and I&rsquo;d be remiss if I don&rsquo;t share a
formal framework I use. I like checklists, spreadsheets, and anything else that
organizes the world around me, and it&rsquo;s fun to make one about communications.</p>

<h2>Checklist</h2>

<p>This is a checklist for high stakes emails, let&rsquo;s dig in:</p>

<ul>
<li><strong>Goals</strong>

<ul>
<li>What are you trying to accomplish? Why? (It could be worth asking why
multiple times.)</li>
<li>Will this email help you accomplish the goal?</li>
<li>Can the goal be summarized in a single sentence? If not, it&rsquo;s probably not
specific enough.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Audience</strong>

<ul>
<li>Who is the audience?</li>
<li>What does the audience care about? How can you connect the subject of your
email to things they care about?</li>
<li>Does every recipient need to be there? Who&rsquo;s missing?</li>
<li>What action do you want the reader to take? Is there a clear call for
action? For executive communications (who have notoriously short attention
span), you&rsquo;ll want to both start and end with the same call for action.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Content</strong>

<ul>
<li>Is there a nuance that would be lost in email that requires face to face
conversation? Does this need to be an email?</li>
<li>Does every sentence and paragraph support your goal?</li>
<li>Does this need a TL;DR?</li>
<li>Is the narrative structure in place? Is there a clear beginning, middle, and
end? No need to write a novel, but without this the content risks being
disjoined.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Impulse</strong>

<ul>
<li>Is now the best time to send it? Friday afternoon is almost always a no-no,
unless you purposely want the reader to pay less attention to the issue.</li>
<li>If this was shared broadly, would you rephrase it? If yes - you definitely
should.

<ul>
<li>To double down, if email is about someone, write as if that someone will
eventually see it. It&rsquo;s fine to be candid, it&rsquo;s not fine to be rude.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Are you angry? Upset? I get notoriously cranky in the late afternoon, and
avoid sending anything important until the next day - or, if time sensitive,
until taking a short break or a walk.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<h2>Example</h2>

<p>Let&rsquo;s apply this to an example. Say, I&rsquo;m writing a book, and the editor I&rsquo;m
working with hasn&rsquo;t been responsive. I&rsquo;ve tried talking to them about it, but
they&rsquo;re not responsive. I think it&rsquo;s the time to escalate to their supervisor.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the quick, dirty, and impulsive draft I would write:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hello X,</p>

<p>Y hasn&rsquo;t been responsive when reviewing the chapters, and it&rsquo;s really
difficult to get back to chapters after a whole week passes by. By then I
don&rsquo;t even have the context! I&rsquo;ve raised this multiple times and to no avail.
Can you please get Y to be more responsive or find another editor for me to
work with? I haven&rsquo;t been able to make meaningful progress in a month!</p></blockquote>

<p>Pretty brusque, isn&rsquo;t it? I don&rsquo;t normally dissect every email like this, but
sometimes it helps to take a closer look and formalize the decision making
behind each sentence. Thankfully, much of this becomes habitual over time.</p>

<h3>Goals</h3>

<p>First things first, I want the editor to be more responsive. Why? To have a
shorter feedback loop when it comes to making changes. Why? To make it easier
to write - it&rsquo;s difficult to come back to the chapter after a long amount of
time passed. Why? This pushes back timelines for each chapter.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t really care about how to achieve this goal: the same person can be
more responsive, or maybe I get a new point of contact to work with. Maybe
there are other options I haven&rsquo;t considered.</p>

<p>To summarize in a single sentence, the goal is to &ldquo;reduce the feedback loop&rdquo;.</p>

<h3>Audience</h3>

<p>The audience is the editor&rsquo;s supervisor, or maybe someone else from the
editorial team who&rsquo;ll have the incentive to escalate.</p>

<p>I know that the timelines are very important to this publisher, which is
something I can use. I can frame the concerns around impacts of the timeline -
even if it&rsquo;s not something I necessarily care about myself.</p>

<p>Since there are multiple ways to achieve my goal and I don&rsquo;t particularly care
about how, I can make the call for action open ended. I&rsquo;m doing this because I&rsquo;m
comfortable with either outcomes - like the editor not being to improve response
times, but the publisher providing more leniency around the schedule - which,
while isn&rsquo;t ideal, still helps.</p>

<h3>Content</h3>

<p>As multiple people can help me accomplish a goal, and I might not be aware of
all of relevant parties - email format works best.</p>

<p>Narrative structure here is simple - I have a problem (the beginning), here&rsquo;s why
it&rsquo;s bad (the middle), let&rsquo;s fix it (the end).</p>

<p>This email is short enough not to require a TL;DR.</p>

<h3>Impulse</h3>

<p>As my concern is about a particular person, I have to talk about them. I don&rsquo;t
want to avoid candor, but I can approach the situation with empathy and
assumption of best intentions something along the lines of: &ldquo;I understand X has
other commitments&rdquo;. Focusing on facts and leading with empathy would help here.</p>

<p>Having an unresponsive editor is definitely frustrating, so it&rsquo;s worth taking a
step back, and maybe paying extra attention - there&rsquo;s no use having frustration
show through.</p>

<h3>The result</h3>

<p>After running through the checklist, we end up with (what I hope is) a better,
more actionable, and less icky email:</p>

<blockquote><p>Hello X,</p>

<p>When working with Y, it takes up to a week for me to receive feedback on the
chapters I wrote. I understand Y is working with multiple engagements, but
I&rsquo;m concerned about the timelines for the book. If we continue as is, it&rsquo;s
likely we&rsquo;ll have to push publishing date by X months.</p>

<p>Could you help me find a resolution here?</p></blockquote>

<p>It&rsquo;s short, omits unnecessary details, and leaves the reader with a clear (but
open ended) call for action. Now, all that&rsquo;s left is to schedule send that
email in a morning, and wait for a response!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Journaling for work-life balance]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/journaling-for-work-life-balance/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-12T13:32:48-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/journaling-for-work-life-balance</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When writing about <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets/">snippets at Google</a> earlier this week, I omitted a fairly important bit: how lists and journaling help me create distance between work and life. This became especially <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-at-work/">relevant in the pandemic</a>, as I had to work with my therapist on being able to mentally disconnect.</p>

<p>I wrote about my strained relationship with ToDo lists <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/why-i-threw-away-my-to-do-list/">before</a>: all the way back in 2014. Back then I focused on moving away from a monolithic ToDo list, and focusing on just a few major things I&rsquo;d like to accomplish each day. I continued to do this, but with some changes to my philosophy.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m back to keeping a ToDo list, but it&rsquo;s a bit more complex than a single list I used to keep. I split things I care about by days, weeks, and months, and I review these lists regularly.</p>

<p>Last year I learned about <a href="https://bulletjournal.com/pages/learn">bullet journaling</a>, often shortened to &ldquo;BuJo&rdquo;. Akin to artisan coffee and avocado toast, this hipster friendly and highly marketable approach has a solid foundation. At its core bullet journaling consists of two parts. First is a consistent and simple notation for tasks, notes, and events: some simple guidelines on how to document what happened, what will happen, and what you need to remember. Second part is a rule set on organizing these lists: daily and monthly notes, custom logs, and so on.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/bullet-journal.png" title="Picture of a bullet journal with a few sample tasks, notes, and events." ></p>

<p>I rigorously keep daily notes about work, meeting annotations, records of important thoughts and ideas, and things I need to do (or have already done). This helps me leave work at work &ndash; or more precisely leave work in a journal. Once it&rsquo;s closed - I&rsquo;m done for the day. Everything I need to think about is written down, and there&rsquo;s no need for my mind to wonder back.</p>

<p>Some weeks I omit note taking, and the contrast in my well-being is jarring. My mind wonders back to the events of the week, and I even have trouble sleeping some days. And no one wants to dream about work &ndash; I&rsquo;m sure as hell not paid enough for that.</p>

<p>Another technique I picked up from the bullet journal keeps me from getting overwhelmed and keeping focus. BuJo advocates for regular migration of ToDo items &ndash; meaning that you should be crossing out and rewriting the same thing over and over again, day by day, week by week. At some point it becomes either to either do something about those ToDos, or choose not to do them altogether. Either way, it&rsquo;s a huge weight off my shoulders.</p>

<p>And this is where the <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets/">aforementioned snippets</a> come in. At the end of the week, all I have to do is go through the weekly set of notes, and transcribe noteworthy bullet points. That&rsquo;s the time I take to look back at my week, migrate tasks I choose to revisit at a later date, or cross off tasks I choose not to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Communicating via snippets]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets/"/>
    <updated>2021-06-07T16:15:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/communicating-via-snippets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve learned a lot of cool things during my tenure at Google.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/i-have-approximate-knowledge-of-many-things.gif" title="I have approximate knowledge of many things&hellip;" ></p>

<p>One of those things are snippets. Google (and from what I hear other Silicon Valley giants as well) utilizes a system of snippets: a transparent and widely accessible set of weekly notes. It&rsquo;s not mandatory, and some groups use it more often then others. Sounds ordinary, but I think it&rsquo;s a lot more interesting then that.</p>

<p>Communication and visibility is one of the major challenges in any paid creative work, but it&rsquo;s especially important in software engineering. Engineers often settle on tasks they know nothing about: tasks are hard to measure and estimate. This makes it even harder to communicate progress broadly.</p>

<p>There are ways around this communication barrier &ndash; regular standups or periodic reviews come to mind. But there&rsquo;s a better (although not necessarily exclusive), more asynchronous way to communicate and increase visibility. Enter snippets - a condensed list of what happened with you and your colleagues last week, delivered straight to your inbox.</p>

<p>Every Friday, an email notification reminds you to fill in weekly snippets. These snippets might look something like this:</p>

<ul>
<li>Project X

<ul>
<li>Authored a design doc (link), sent for a review</li>
<li>Discussed roadmap with stakeholders A and B (notes)</li>
<li>Debugged issue Z, to no avail (link)</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Project Y

<ul>
<li>Cleared backlog for the past 6 months</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Attended a summit about G</li>
<li>Had 1:1s with C, D, E, and F</li>
</ul>


<p>On Monday, an email goes out compiling our team&rsquo;s snippets in a single digest. Skimming through snippets covers any communication gaps from the past week, and raises visibility on what everyone is working on.</p>

<p>This system has many benefits:</p>

<ul>
<li>Transparency: you know what everyone around you (including higher ups) is up to.</li>
<li>You actually remember what you&rsquo;ve done a month from now.</li>
<li>All the important documents, events, and notes are linked from snippets. Snippets are are time bound, which makes these documents easy to find.</li>
<li>Teammates and managers can always check snippets to get an idea of progress on certain efforts.</li>
<li>You manager (who&rsquo;s hopefully your biggest ally when it comes to career development) has a great idea of what you&rsquo;re up to.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s easy to find artifacts and proof during performance reviews.</li>
<li>Higher visibility of glue work (all the little things you do to keep the place running).</li>
</ul>


<p>This doesn&rsquo;t have to be a particularly complex system. A running doc with notes could suffice, although email notifications remove a lot of the overhead needed. Even if the organization doesn&rsquo;t follow the model, I find it worthwhile to keep snippets, and to share them with my manager and team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Living at work]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-at-work/"/>
    <updated>2021-04-13T09:34:18-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/living-at-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My first remote work experience coincided with my self-employment as a contractor. I was building a copyright enforcement service for a client in a year 2013. I lived in a one bedroom apartment in Philadelphia with my now ex-wife &ndash; a few blocks away from the city hall. I worked at a small standing desk (trendy!) in a corner of our little bedroom - by the closet.</p>

<p>I worked from the early morning and deep into the night at that desk. Sometimes I would look out of the window behind me. I would see an uninspired urban picture of roof tops of other four story colonial homes. And after a moment of respite it was back to work for me.</p>

<p>This was my first major foray into the world of self-accountability: I meticulously tracked the time spent working, billed the client per hour, provided in-depth breakdowns. The more I worked, the more I could bill the client &ndash; I had the incentive to put in as much time into work as possible.</p>

<p>So I did. I clocked in 80 to 90 hours of billable time a week. The checks with a before unheard of hourly rate kept coming, so I kept putting in the hours. Neither I nor my significant other had major professional experience. (To be completely honest we didn&rsquo;t have much in the realm of like experience either). We kept on keeping on.</p>

<p>I thought about work during lunch. I was agonizing over the details when walking through the neighboring Rittenhouse Square. I would jump into late night coding sessions. As a young professional, I didn&rsquo;t see the need to draw lines between my work and my life &ndash; my life was my work. There was no &ldquo;me&rdquo; without work.</p>

<p>That is until I burnt out. I woke up one morning, and something inside me snapped. I realized that I couldn&rsquo;t spend another minute in front of the screen. I took a day off, and the feeling wouldn&rsquo;t pass. I felt numb and overwhelmed at the same time. A day filled with my favorite video games - and I still felt that way. A day at a museum - nothing. I didn&rsquo;t get better.</p>

<p>I invoked a force majeure clause in my contract. I transferred all the materials, sent the final invoice, and stepped away from the project.</p>

<p>I won&rsquo;t talk here about the ways to fight burnout, because I didn&rsquo;t know how to. I quit, took a break, and eventually moved onto another job. By the virtue of this happening early in my career, and me being rather young - I managed to &ldquo;snap out of it&rdquo; between jobs.</p>

<p>I wish I could share &ldquo;the one thing&rdquo; I did that helped - but there wasn&rsquo;t one. I don&rsquo;t remember how I took care of myself, and how I managed to get my head straight. All I remember that I felt discombobulated for weeks. And at some point the feeling went away. I couldn&rsquo;t work during that time.</p>

<p>Time passed. I moved across the country to the San Francisco Bay area for a job with Google. My now ex-wife and I split up &ndash; it was a civil, but nonetheless a difficult divorce.</p>

<p>Around that time, I spent a year traveling across the United States. I lived out of my car and stayed in hotels while working remotely on my own terms. I established strict working hours and routines.</p>

<p>I would start my work around 8 am, without paying mind to the timezone I&rsquo;d be in. I&rsquo;d work out of coffee shops, coworking spaces, or even campgrounds. I&rsquo;d always take a break for lunch. I&rsquo;d wrap up work at 4 pm, and not a minute longer. Constant travel and change of scenery encouraged me to keep to my work hours. I had to weigh in staying past my end of workday versus going out and sight seeing a new city. The wanderlust always won.</p>

<p>The work was out of my mind after 4 pm. That was easy to do with an adventure afoot, but years later and the habit stuck with me. I don&rsquo;t let thoughts about work slip into my day to day. My mind is my own outside of work.</p>

<p>That was a transformative experience, and it changed the way I see work. I know it&rsquo;s trendy to say this, but I don&rsquo;t live to work: I work to live.</p>

<p>Today, I work with some people who have never worked remotely before the pandemic. And I often hear a similar sounding sentiment: &ldquo;never again&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It makes me think about the time I was self-employed for the first time. Putting in 80 hour work weeks, and not having the awareness to understand how I was affecting myself and people around me. It created distance between me and my partner. I let the work spill into the time I had. In a way it made me less of an employee and less of person.</p>

<p>When the pandemic started I looked back to these memories. Google moved to continuous work from home model in March 2020. And I made a conscious effort not to slip into my early remote work days. I established a strict routine. Breakfast and lunch with my significant other (here&rsquo;s some closure to my divorce). No deviation from &ldquo;9 to 5&rdquo;.</p>

<p>I established an area for myself to work in &ndash; I bought a sturdy desk and a chair from a used office furniture reseller. I make an effort to create not only mental, but physical separation from work. I wear office clothes during the day, and change once I&rsquo;m done with work. I cook to distress after a long day. My partner and I adhere to scheduled date nights (we do leave room for spontaneity too).</p>

<p>That isn&rsquo;t to say I didn&rsquo;t slip over the past year: many times I stayed past an established time. I often started earlier than planned. And some days I would let work occupy my mind space as I&rsquo;m relaxing with my better half. We&rsquo;ve spent the past year working out of a one bedroom apartment. A bigger one than I worked out of 7 years ago, but still a one bedroom. It was difficult, and some days it still is.</p>

<p>But time and time again, I corrected the course and resumed my routine. During my soul searching adventure remote work was fun. Because this time working remotely is much harder. There are no sights to see. No new places to stay in. No novelty to look towards at the end of the day. Working from home in the middle of a pandemic is oh-so-difficult.</p>

<p>To be honest I can&rsquo;t wait to be back in the office. But I&rsquo;m also excited to work from home on my own terms. Because this isn&rsquo;t what remote work is like.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
