<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: notes and rants | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/notes-and-rants/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-10-01T18:16:52-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lessons learned: engineering productivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/lessons-learned-engineering-productivity/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-08T14:03:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/lessons-learned-engineering-productivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I enjoy optimizing the way I work: the less time I can spend on something
without sacrificing quality - the better. Below are few ideas on the subject of
engineering productivity I&rsquo;ve successfully applied in my career.</p>

<h2>Don&rsquo;t work long hours</h2>

<p>A fascinating paper was released in 2011 by a group of Israeli researchers, who
studied the factors which affect if prisoners were given a parole or not
(source: <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/108/17/6889.abstract">Extraneous factors in judicial decisions</a>.</p>

<p>First prisoner in a morning has approximately 65% chance of being released. With
every next case, the chance dropped significantly, reaching nearly 0% starting
with the third case. After returning from a lunch break, odds of a prisoner
being released went back up to 65%. And once again, with each new prisoner the
odds decline rapidly.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/israeli-parole-study.gif" title="A graph of favorable parole decisions given by the judges." ></p>

<p>Authors of the paper suggest that making decisions depletes a limited mental
facility. People start looking for shortcuts and making mistakes.</p>

<p>Working long hours is something we&rsquo;ve all done more than once. Be it an upcoming
deadline, fascinating problem, or a personal project. The problem with working
too long is that you&rsquo;re doing a poor job without realizing it.</p>

<p>I try to avoid working more than 7 hours a day, and there are people who get an
incredible amount of work done under an even shorter amount of time.</p>

<p>This is probably explained by a phenomenon called &ldquo;ego depletion&rdquo;: the idea that
self-control or willpower draw upon a pool of limited mental resources that can
be used up. When the energy for mental activity is low, self-control is
typically impaired, which is what is considered to be a state of ego depletion.</p>

<h2>Dangers of burning out</h2>

<p>Another problem with working too long - is a possibility of a burnout.</p>

<p>A while back I worked as a freelancer for a client of mine. I worked long hours
from home office. This was my first time working from home for such a long
period of time, and I made a number of mistakes in the beginning. One of which
was working too much.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve put in a number of 12-hour marathons in order to get more work done. I was
on call most of the time. I became overwhelmed with all the work I had to get
done. I started losing interest in work and feeling like things are getting out
of my control. Every day felt like a bad day.</p>

<p>Those are the symptoms of a burnout. Feeling of life spinning out of control
and feeling like nothing you do makes any impact.</p>

<p>I broke out of a mental prison of a burnout by getting a better work-life
balance, enforcing exercise routine, and never working more than 8 hours a day.
7 in most cases.</p>

<h2>Work-life balance</h2>

<p>Another thing I learned from working from home is how to keep a work-life
balance. Not having a separate office and living in a 1-bedroom apartment with
my wife, I had to barricade myself in a far corner of a bedroom and turn it into
a physically separated office space. That was the space I worked in, and it
remained empty after I was done and until I started the next work day.</p>

<p>Work-life balance deserves a special say: it&rsquo;s the difference between doing an
amazing job and going insane. Set aside time and place for work, and never allow
a bleed-through. Don&rsquo;t be on call if you can avoid it. Don&rsquo;t open or reply to
work-related emails at your spare time. Office is for work and home is for
family.</p>

<h2>Distraction-free environment</h2>

<p>Everybody is aware that interruptions hamper productivity, but not everyone
actively avoids interruptions during work. Replying to a text message, quickly
checking your social network notifications, or looking up that one thing you&rsquo;ve
been forgetting to look up for days - all of this impairs your mental ability to
complete the task within a desired time frame and, more importantly, with high
quality.</p>

<p>According to various studies it takes from 20 to 30 minutes to get regain the
same level of concentration and productivity after a single act of disruption. A
<a href="http://hfs.sagepub.com/content/56/7/1262">2014 study from George Mason University</a> found that students composed lower
quality essays when interrupted only a few times throughout both planning and
writing phases. Distracted students performed considerably worse, even though
they were given additional time to complete an assignment in order to make up
for the interruptions.</p>

<h2>Know your tools</h2>

<blockquote><p>Use a single editor well</p></blockquote>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1B1PWw8">Pragmatic Programmer</a>, Tip #22.</li>
</ul>


<p>This is lower level tip than the rest, but something I find utterly important in
my daily work. We, the software engineers, spend at least half the time editing
some sort of text - code, email, documentation. Taking time to improve the
knowledge of the software you use every day pays off.</p>

<ul>
<li>Using Gmail? Learn the keyboard shortcuts.</li>
<li>Use Eclispe? Do the same. Search for plugins which can make your everyday work
faster and easier.</li>
<li>Use command shell for daily work? Practice your shell scripting skills, find
the tools that let you do more work with lesser amount of typing.</li>
<li>Pick up touch typing. It&rsquo;s also a part of your toolbox. Why think about keying
words in? Lower error rate while typing - you need to go back less.</li>
</ul>


<p>For instance, I do all my work in shell. I use <a href="http://tmux.sourceforge.net">Tmux</a> for creating and
navigating multiple sessions. I use Vim for all my editing needs - code,
documentation, blogging, composing long emails (via <a href="http://www.mutt.org">Mutt</a>). I touch type, so
working in a text mode is easy.</p>

<p>Over the years I accumulated aliases for all the frequently used shell commands.
All the Vim and Tmux shortcuts are a part of a muscle memory. Jumping from file
to file or from one place to another within a file doesn&rsquo;t take any mental
effort and is accomplished with only a couple of keystrokes.</p>

<p>By eliminating the need to think about or spend too much time working with low
level concepts - you free up the mental bandwidth for higher level reasoning and
problem solving.</p>

<h2>Read, don&rsquo;t stop learning</h2>

<p>As per DeMarco and Lister, authors of
<a href="http://amzn.to/1D2csza">&ldquo;Peopleware: Productive Projects and Teams&rdquo;</a> - one book is more than most
programmers read each year. This is the same point Steve McConnell&rsquo;s
<a href="http://amzn.to/1D2cB5K">&ldquo;Code Complete&rdquo;</a> emphasizes.</p>

<p>A lot of programmers don&rsquo;t read books. A few even don&rsquo;t follow relevant blogs
or websites. Don&rsquo;t do what software engineers had to do in the olden days:
coding by error in isolation from the rest of the industry. Read a book, learn
something you don&rsquo;t know about. A single book read from beginning to end
contains wider array of information compared to disjointed articles some
programmers limit themselves to.</p>

<p>As Jeff Atwood suggests in his article
<a href="http://blog.codinghorror.com/programmers-dont-read-books-but-you-should/">&ldquo;Programmers Don&rsquo;t Read Books - But You Should&rdquo;</a>, pick up one of the
timeless books - not affected by changing technologies and processes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Impact-driven development]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/impact-driven-development/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-25T17:19:58-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/impact-driven-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is my fifth year working as a professional software engineer, and I think
it&rsquo;s a good time for me to share a few tips, dos, and don&#8217;ts I learned
throughout past four years. This is the first article in a series of three,
and it focuses on development process.</p>

<p>Moving towards becoming a senior engineer, I noticed paying more attention to
the impact my work produces. These days I would much rather compile a number of
small simple changes to &ldquo;wow&rdquo; the users, as opposed to building unnecessarily
complex nice-to-haves. This sounds simple and straight-forward, and some reader
might even say &ldquo;That&rsquo;s silly, everybody knows that&rdquo;. However significant number
of engineers I meet don&rsquo;t concentrate on how much impact they produce.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s easy to get caught up in a daily routine: you close an issue after issue,
there&rsquo;s a stable flow of requirements from the business meetings. It&rsquo;s not
always easy to know when to stop and think &ldquo;Do I really need to do this?&rdquo;.</p>

<h2>Get the priorities right</h2>

<p>Divide amount of impact task produces by amount of effort you&rsquo;ll have to put
into completing it. Arrange the tasks by this factor.</p>

<p>More often then not you can drop items with low impact/effort ratio.</p>

<h2>Separate what is needed from what is asked</h2>

<p>Know who the stakeholders are for each task, feature, or a project you work
on.  Understand their underlying motives. Anyone can fall a victim of an
<a href="http://meta.stackexchange.com/q/66377/184108">XY problem</a>, it is your responsibility as an engineer to make sure that
stakeholders ask for what they actually need.</p>

<h2>Know when to say &ldquo;No&rdquo;</h2>

<p>In the very beginning of my career I gladly took every single task thrown at me.
It soon became an issue: work that actually needs to get done is not getting
done quickly enough. Knowing when to say &ldquo;No&rdquo; is an art that takes practice.</p>

<h2>Think about your work</h2>

<p>Beware of routines, repeating the same workflow time after time is damaging when
it comes to building software. Stop each time before you proceed to the next
step, and ask yourself if you&rsquo;re performing the task in the best way possible.
Be mindful about your work.</p>

<h2>Be a catalyst for change</h2>

<p>Be the first to promote the change. Did you notice a poor practice on a
project? Begin a more efficient practice (if it&rsquo;s appropriate based on your
role in a team of course). Don&rsquo;t go on telling people how wrong what they use
is. Show everyone how the new way is better on practice, and your colleagues
will adopt successful trend.</p>

<p>Don&rsquo;t fall a victim of deferring responsibility: be aware that when multiple
people are involved, every member of a group relies on other people to get
things done. Be the one to take on responsibility when it&rsquo;s unclear who should.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Power of the command line]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/power-of-the-command-line/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-06T13:13:49-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/power-of-the-command-line</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Disclaimer: I am not advocating any specific tools or methodologies, but
sharing a workflow I find to be efficient and pleasant.</em></p>

<p>I am a huge fan of working with CLI applications. I use Vim for editing code,
composing emails, and various kinds of writing. When I have to manipulate huge
amounts of email, I use Mutt: it&rsquo;s intuitive tagging and regular expression
engine are extremely useful for the task. I employ <code>ack</code>, <code>awk</code>, <code>grep</code>, and
<code>sed</code> - Linux utilities which allow for precise and fast text manipulation.</p>

<p>However, I would not use CLI browsers like <code>elinks</code> or <code>w3m</code>, and the idea of
reading every email in Mutt gives me the creeps. I love the visualization web
browser offers, something text-based prompt is not able to provide. And it
doesn&rsquo;t have to.</p>

<p>There are two components to most of the tasks performed on a computer: analyzing
output and entering input. Certain tasks employ one component more than the
other. In most modern applications it&rsquo;s rare to have both solid control from
the user perspective and a pleasant informative UI. With increased visual
component, it&rsquo;s more time consuming to make the application do what you need,
especially if your needs are esoteric. With more editing power, visual display
becomes less complex in order to make editing tasks easier.</p>

<h2>Where visual tools fall short</h2>

<p>What is the alternative? Using multiple programs with different levels of
control to accomplish one task: to edit text. Each of the programs excels in
it&rsquo;s own field: word processing software allows for beautiful fonts and document
presentation, IDE lets you access aggregated meta information about your
application. But most of the IDEs and word processors lack the powerful tools
needed to manipulate the foundation of what user is working with - plain text.</p>

<h2>Ode to plain text</h2>

<p>I spend a lot of time writing and editing plain text. Be it source code, emails,
documentation, or even blog posts. These tasks take up significant amount of my
day, and it is only logical to substitute some of the visual presentation
capabilities for effectiveness.</p>

<p>It is hard to mentally process data which is not explicitly and unambiguously
visible: different levels of headings, hidden meta information. Unlike more
obscuring formats, plain text is all there is - it has nothing to hide. If you
don&rsquo;t see it - it&rsquo;s not there. If you do see it - you know exactly what it is.</p>

<p>One of my favorite tips from &ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1yRe6Th">Pragmatic Programmer</a>&rdquo; goes:</p>

<blockquote><p>Use a single editor well</p></blockquote>

<p>So I learned one editor well, and now I use it for all my writing and editing
needs. I don&rsquo;t have to jump between IDE, browser, and office software. Most of
the text I edit is manipulated with one editor. There is only one set of key
bindings to know, one skill to master and hone. Fast, without any additional
thought, using single text editor and all of it&rsquo;s powerful features is imprinted
in muscle memory. One less task to worry about.</p>

<p>I write my documents in Markdown format, and later convert them to the desired
output using <code>pandoc</code>: be it an HTML page, PDF, or a Microsoft Word document. I
use Vim, so I can rearrange paragraphs or manipulate lines within a couple of
keystrokes. Since I spend so much time editing text, I also touch type, which
makes me even more effective at the given task.</p>

<h2>Harness the power of the command line</h2>

<p>When it comes to bulk manipulating files or working with version control -
there is no better candidate then command line applications. There&rsquo;s no need to
go through a number of obscure menus, ticking and unticking checkboxes, and
hoping that your desired result can be achieved with a program&rsquo;s GUI.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s look at a few scenarios some users face in their daily workflow.</p>

<h3>Creating a backup</h3>

<p>With GUI, you&rsquo;d have to take multiple steps:</p>

<ol>
<li>Right click <code>file</code>.</li>
<li>Left click on &ldquo;Copy&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Right click on some empty space.</li>
<li>Left click on &ldquo;Paste&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Right click on a newly created copy.</li>
<li>Left click on &ldquo;Rename&rdquo;.</li>
<li>Switch to a keyboard.</li>
<li>Type <code>file.bak</code>.</li>
</ol>


<p>The above steps can be sped up using shortcuts like <code>C-c</code> or <code>C-v</code>, but not by
much. Here&rsquo;s an alternative in bash:</p>

<pre><code>cp file{,.bak}
</code></pre>

<p>While first variant would do great for a novice or a casual user - the second
method would be much more preferred by an experienced user whose concern is
speed.</p>

<h3>Recursively bulk replacing text in a directory</h3>

<p>Let&rsquo;s assume we want to do a bulk replace text in a directory and all it&rsquo;s
subdirectories. We have our trusted IDE, let&rsquo;s assume this IDE is already
configured to work with a desired directory.</p>

<ol>
<li>Open your IDE.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Edit&rdquo; menu.</li>
<li>Select &ldquo;Find and Replace&rdquo; submenu.</li>
<li>Click on a &ldquo;Find&rdquo; input field.</li>
<li>Switch to a keyboard.</li>
<li>Type <code>function_to_replace</code>.</li>
<li>Switch to a mouse.</li>
<li>Click on &ldquo;Replace&rdquo; input field.</li>
<li>Switch to a keyboard.</li>
<li>Type <code>new_function_name</code>.</li>
<li>Switch to a mouse.</li>
<li>Enable &ldquo;Search in subdirectories&rdquo; checkbox.</li>
<li>Click &ldquo;OK&rdquo;.</li>
</ol>


<p>Again, this can be shortened a bit with some keyboard shortcuts, but not by
much. You still have to switch between keyboard and a mouse a total of 4 times,
and you still have to click through all the menus. This does get time consuming
if you do this often. Now let&rsquo;s try to perform the same task in command line:</p>

<pre><code>find . -type f | xargs sed -i 's/function_to_replace/new_function_name/g'
</code></pre>

<p>Much faster, if you&rsquo;re able to memorize the structure. And remembering what the
commands do is much easier than it looks. Especially with the help of <code>man</code> or,
even better, <code>bro</code> (see <a href="http://bropages.org">http://bropages.org</a> for latter).</p>

<p>The above example demonstrates one of the biggest advantages of command line
interfaces: an ability to redirect an output of one program into another,
chaining the tools together. In this example, we first get a list of all files
use <code>find</code> tool, and then run <code>sed</code> tool on each of those files in order to
replace the text.</p>

<p>An output from any CLI tool can be fed into any other CLI tool. This allows for
countless possibilities and high adaptability to unscripted scenarios.</p>

<h2>Is it worth learning CLI tools over their GUI counterparts?</h2>

<p>This depends on what your intentions are. If you&rsquo;re a power user who writes and
edits a lot of text or manipulates bulk amounts of text on a daily basis - than
it&rsquo;s definitely worth it. Time spent learning these tools will pay off. But if
you&rsquo;re a casual user whose needs end with writing an occasional email or two -
then you probably don&rsquo;t need to worry about this.</p>

<p>Hell, if you&rsquo;ve read this far - this means you&rsquo;re the former case. I can
practically guarantee that you will benefit from employing command line tools
and modal editors over their GUI counterparts.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve put together a table for comparison between two. Indeed, there are
different times when either GUI or CLI tools excel:</p>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> Factor                            </th>
<th> CLI </th>
<th> GUI </th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td> Ability to combine/chain tools    </td>
<td> Yes </td>
<td> No  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Easy to learn                     </td>
<td> No  </td>
<td> Yes </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Efficient for a novice user       </td>
<td> No  </td>
<td> Yes </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Efficient for an experienced user </td>
<td> Yes </td>
<td> No  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Good for occasional use           </td>
<td> No  </td>
<td> Yes </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Good for repetitive tasks         </td>
<td> Yes </td>
<td> No  </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td> Presents visual information well  </td>
<td> No  </td>
<td> Yes </td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>As you can see - both CLI and GUI programs have their pluses and minuses. CLI
tools seem to appeal to experienced users, while GUI tools are great for novice
users and do excel in representing visual information. No matter what kind of
interface you prefer, it&rsquo;s crucially important to use the right tool for the job.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[750 words a day]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/750-words-a-day/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T10:51:35-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/750-words-a-day</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve had increased interest in writing throughout this year. In addition to
being a pleasant and fulfilling activity, it shown a number of benefits in my
everyday life and career:</p>

<ul>
<li>Composing emails became faster and easier. When you have to reply to a couple
of dozen emails a day, speed and attention to details matters. Writing more
taught me to write more concise emails which are easy to read.</li>
<li>Writing a lot isn&rsquo;t a problem anymore. If I have to write documentation,
comment code, or just put together a very long email - I&rsquo;m not put off by the
idea. I&rsquo;m excited about it.</li>
<li>Typing speed went up. <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/why-should-you-learn-to-touch-type/">I already touch type</a>, and constant writing practice
increases the acquired speed. Fast typing makes life easier, speeding up
mundane tasks, freeing up brain power for more costly activities.</li>
<li>It&rsquo;s easy to keep a condensed work log to highlight the issues of the day.
Tough programming issues, &ldquo;Eureka!&rdquo; moments, meeting notes - this historical
data saved me hours or even days of repeating my mistakes.</li>
</ul>


<p>A while ago, I&rsquo;ve heard of a thing called <a href="http://750words.com/">&ldquo;750 words&rdquo;</a>, a site built around
a challenge to write 750 words a day in order to improve writing skills and
unleash creativity. This looked like a great idea, and I decided to give it a
shot. I prefer to keep my personal entries offline, and I decided not to use the
provided service, but to keep a set of plain text files on my local machine.
Which worked out just fine. It&rsquo;s all just text after all.</p>

<p>I lasted for 10 days in a row, which I am proud of (filling up approximately 3
pages a day was no easy task for me). I started of with silly entries about not
knowing what to write about, and finished with a piece of a fiction story.
That&rsquo;s a considerable improvement.</p>

<p>By the end of the challenge I was mentally exhausted. But it taught me a very
important lesson: the more you write, the better you become. And that&rsquo;s one of
the main reasons I keep crafting new entries for this blog.</p>

<p>This happened half a year ago, I just never got around to writing about it. I
will go ahead and start another 750 words spree today. Maybe this time I&rsquo;ll be
able to make it last for the whole month.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[One more argument for 80 character limit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/one-more-argument-for-80-character-limit/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-29T23:00:04-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/one-more-argument-for-80-character-limit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Limiting code to 80 (or 100 or 120) characters per line. It&rsquo;s a well-known
topic, and there&rsquo;s an overall consensus on the subject, not counting occasional
questions by newbies and odd cases. Most established tech companies have their
own line length guidelines. These are often dependent on a language, such as in
the case of Google with their 80 character Python and 100 character Java limits.</p>

<p>In this article, I won&rsquo;t be advocating all the usual arguments, such as easier
diff with version control software, or the ability to stack windows side by side
on wide screens. No, I believe that battle to be won quite a long time ago, the
topic is now closed. But something I didn&rsquo;t find mentioned in any of the
discussions is an interesting point from the world of writers and designers.</p>

<p>Ever since I started being interested in improving my writing skills, I found
article after article mention the importance of line length in reading.
Interestingly enough, this issue was raised in a world of literature. It had
been resolved long before programmers were fascinated with the desire to use up
rapidly expanding screen real estate.</p>

<p>I am talking about something known as &ldquo;measure&rdquo; in typography. It seems to be
the reason newspapers use narrow columns, or books leave such vast margins
around the text on a page. Here&rsquo;s an exempt from the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Measure_(typography)">Wikipedia article</a>:</p>

<blockquote><p>Measure (or sometimes &ldquo;The Measure&rdquo;) in typography is the length of a line of
text. For a single-column design measure should ideally lie between 40 &amp; 80
characters. Many typographers consider the perfect measure to be 65
characters. If the lines are too short then the text becomes disjointed, if
they are too long the content loses rhythm as the reader searches for the
start of each line. Punctuation should preferably hang outside the measure.</p></blockquote>

<p>Most programming languages use special operators and keywords, which can be
considered &ldquo;punctuation&rdquo;. Some languages are more verbose (use more
punctuation), and some aren&rsquo;t. If you remove punctuation, the 80/100/120
character limit perfectly fits the standard time-honed &ldquo;measure&rdquo;.</p>

<p>Maybe I can use this as an additional argument the next time I have to explain
to a junior new hire why the character limits are so strictly enforced.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
