<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: vim | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/vim/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-04T18:41:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DidYouMean plugin for Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/didyoumean-plugin-for-vim/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-10T20:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/didyoumean-plugin-for-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/EinfachToll/DidYouMean">DidYouMean</a> Vim plugin is very simple: it asks you if the file you are
trying to open is indeed the right file. How is this useful? Here&rsquo;s how:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/vim-plugin-didyoumean.png" title="DidYouMean plugin in action." ></p>

<p>Say you have two files with a similarly starting names: <code>model.py</code> and
<code>model_test.py</code>. You type <code>vim mo</code>, you hit tab to autocomplete the name, you
hit enter. In vanilla Vim, you&rsquo;d be opening a new file: <code>model</code>, since that&rsquo;s
where shell&rsquo;s tab-completion stopped. DidYouMean detects such a nuance and asks
you if you wanted to open <code>model</code>, <code>model.py</code>, or <code>model_test.py</code>.</p>

<p>Simple idea, and instantly after trying this out, I would really expect this
feature to be included in vanilla Vim.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gundo tree for Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/gundo-tree-for-vim/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-07T20:10:15+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/gundo-tree-for-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>One of the obscure, but tremendously useful features of Vim is an undo tree.
You would expect Vim to have a simple stack for undo and redo actions, but it&rsquo;s
much more complex than that: Vim keeps track of every change you made in the
current session, making it possible to access change history beyond basic <code>u</code>
and <code>C-r</code> commands.</p>

<p>Default interface for accessing far out branches of the undo tree leaves to be
desired, but that&rsquo;s where <a href="http://sjl.bitbucket.org/gundo.vim/">Gundo</a> comes in.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/vim-gundo-tree.png" title="Gundo tree in Vim." ></p>

<p>Gundo provides an easy to use interface for navigating history branches. In the
screenshot above, I am previewing a diff in one of the undo tree branches
inaccessible via <code>u</code> command.</p>

<p>As per author&rsquo;s recommendation, I mapped the plugin to <code>F5</code>, which seems quite
convenient to me:</p>

<pre><code>nnoremap &lt;F5&gt; :GundoToggle&lt;CR&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Usage is quite easy. <code>F5</code> opens or closes the undo tree, <code>j</code> and <code>k</code> are used
to travel through changes. Enter key applies the changes.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My experience switching to buffers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-experience-switching-to-buffers/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-01T13:28:42+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-experience-switching-to-buffers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>About a year ago I stumbled upon an article explaining the difference between
Vim tabs and buffers. The author emphasized that tabs are merely window
layouts, and therefore one-file-per-tab idea I was used to at the moment just
wasn&rsquo;t proper. Instead, author suggested the use of buffer commands to switch
between multiple files. I decided to give it a shot, and here are some ideas I
would like to share after switching to the use of buffers.</p>

<p>Buffers are open files (they also may not be associated with any files), but
they&rsquo;re not necessarily visible at any given moment. In Vim, windows are not
linked to any particular buffer, so you can easily cycle through buffers from
within any window.</p>

<p>First and foremost, you probably want to add <code>set hidden</code> to your <code>.vimrc</code>.
This option lets you switch between buffers without having to save files.</p>

<p>At it&rsquo;s basics, you only need few commands for operating buffers:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use <code>:ls</code> to list all buffers for this session.</li>
<li>To move between next and previous buffers use <code>:bn</code> and <code>:bp</code> respectively.</li>
<li>Use <code>:b partial_buffer_name</code> for navigating to the buffer of your choice.
Buffer name auto-complete is supported.</li>
<li>You can also use <code>:bN</code>, where <code>N</code> is a buffer number to jump to a specific
buffer.</li>
<li>Get in a habit of closing buffers you will not use with <code>:bd</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p><img src="/images/posts/vim-list-buffers.png" title="A list of open buffers in Vim." ></p>

<p>The hardest thing about stopping to use tabs and switching to buffers instead
is not having the visual aid: I was used to having a list of files always
available at a glance, at the top of my screen. To check what files I&rsquo;m working
on now - I have to hit four keys: <code>:ls</code> (fourth being &ldquo;Enter&rdquo;).</p>

<p>Not surprisingly, this taught me to be more mindful about my editing
experience. I usually have a clear structure of the files I&rsquo;m working on in my
head. And if the list is getting to long to easily remember, then I&rsquo;m probably
doing something wrong: time to take a break and reset my Vim session.</p>

<p>The experience overall reminded me of my recent switch to blank keyboard key
caps: with no inscriptions to aid you, I first felt a bit at loss, especially
with they keys I couldn&rsquo;t find without looking: like function keys or special
symbols. But after some time with the blank key caps, I improved my typing
skill, and know where even the most obscure characters hide. The switch helped
me to improve my typing experience overall.</p>

<p>With Vim, it&rsquo;s a similar story. After getting past the initial confusion, I
achieved high level of awareness about my editing sessions. It didn&rsquo;t make the
editing process any faster, but instead much more satisfying.</p>

<p>But you already new that, since Vim isn&rsquo;t really about speed.</p>

<p>UPDATE: Made a few corrections and added a <code>:b partial_buffer_name</code> command
thanks to <a href="http://www.reddit.com/user/___violet___">/u/___violet___</a>&rsquo;s <a href="http://www.reddit.com/r/vim/comments/382v6q/my_experience_switching_to_buffers/crrunni">Reddit comment</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Custom templates in vimwiki]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/custom-templates-in-vimwiki/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-05T18:40:33+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/custom-templates-in-vimwiki</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I got myself into a habit of using vimwiki for the past year: it helps me to
keep track of random bits of information, work and project notes, as well as
daily goals and achievements. You can read more about vimwiki in an article I
wrote a while back: &ldquo;<a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/personal-wiki-with-vimwiki/">Personal wiki with vimwiki</a>&rdquo;.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/vimwiki-workflow-habits.png" title="HTML page generated by vimwiki with a custom navigation bar." ></p>

<p>One of vimwiki&rsquo;s features I really like is an ability to convert whole wiki to
HTML with a single command: <code>:VimwikiAll2HTML</code>. There is one annoyance though:
HTML vimwiki pages don&rsquo;t have any navigation elements: the only way to navigate
between pages is by clicking through links within a page or using browser&rsquo;s
&ldquo;back&rdquo; button.</p>

<p>Luckily, vimwiki has a setting which allows using custom templates for
generating HTML. Assuming your wiki is in <code>$HOME/Dropbox/wiki</code> (can be anywhere
else though), make following changes to your <code>.vimrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code>let g:vimwiki_list = [{
  \ 'path': '$HOME/Dropbox/wiki',
  \ 'template_path': '$HOME/Dropbox/wiki/templates',
  \ 'template_default': 'default',
  \ 'template_ext': '.html'}]
</code></pre>

<p>After that, create a <code>$HOME/Dropbox/wiki/templates/default.html</code> using
<code>vimwiki/autoload/vimwiki/default.tpl</code> as a base. I added simple navigation bar
to my default template:</p>

<pre><code>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;head&gt;
    &lt;link rel="Stylesheet" type="text/css" href="%root_path%style.css" /&gt;
    &lt;title&gt;%title%&lt;/title&gt;
    &lt;meta http-equiv="Content-Type" content="text/html; charset=utf-8" /&gt;
&lt;/head&gt;
&lt;body&gt;
    &lt;a href="%root_path%index.html"&gt;Index&lt;/a&gt; |
    &lt;a href="%root_path%diary/diary.html"&gt;Diary&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;hr&gt;
    &lt;div class="content"&gt;
    %content%
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/body&gt;
&lt;/html&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Now it&rsquo;s much easier to jump between wiki entries. Of course, customization
doesn&rsquo;t end there: you can change styles, add JavaScript and make your wiki all
fancy and advanced.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Distraction-free writing with VimRoom]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/distraction-free-writing-with-vimroom/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-23T21:46:20+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/distraction-free-writing-with-vimroom</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently I&rsquo;ve been writing much more than I used to: long emails, software
documentation, personal Wiki, keeping work journal, blogging, writing
challenges&hellip; Luckily enough, I do all of this writing in Vim. But sometimes
writing prose in Vim might feel a bit unnatural, especially if you have a wide
screen: text will be on the very left side of the screen, or (if <code>textwrap</code> is
not enabled) you&rsquo;ll end up with lines hundreds of characters long. And overall,
editing text in Vim sometimes might feel a bit clunky - with all the extra
information and high-tech (or low-tech, depending on your perspective) look.</p>

<p>I found a simple, yet sufficient solution for this issue: <a href="http://projects.mikewest.org/vimroom/">VimRoom</a>. It&rsquo;s a
Vim plugin which enters distraction-free writing mode, by centering the
80-character block of text on your screen. It&rsquo;s highly configurable, and I
found it to look especially pleasing on vertical monitors (which I prefer to
use for writing). It looks presentable even on smaller screens though, here&rsquo;s a
screenshot:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/vimroom-screenshot.png" title="VimRoom plugin in use." ></p>

<p>Install the plugin (use a package manager like Vundle or <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/vim-pathogen-and-git-submodules/">Pathogen</a> to
simplify the task) and add a following line to your <code>.vimrc</code>:</p>

<pre><code>nnoremap &lt;Leader&gt;vr :VimroomToggle&lt;CR&gt;
</code></pre>

<p>Now, hit <code>&lt;Leader&gt;vr</code> to drop in/out of the VimRoom mode (<code>&lt;Leader</code> is a
backslash <code>\</code> character by default).</p>

<p>GitHub link: <a href="https://github.com/mikewest/vimroom">https://github.com/mikewest/vimroom</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
