<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2020-09-20T18:32:27+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adjusting to working from home]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/adjusting-to-wfh/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-04T17:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/adjusting-to-wfh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many, I moved to working from home during the COVID-19 pandemic. Parts of California enacted shelter-in-place order back in March, and it&rsquo;s been over a month and a half since then. I briefly worked from home back in 2013 as a freelancer - and I really got the whole work/life balance thing wrong. So this time around I&rsquo;ve decided to approach remote work with a plan.</p>

<p>My day begins around 7 or 8 am, without too much deviation from schedule. I used to bike to work before the pandemic, and I try to head out for a 30 minute ride in a morning a few days a week. There aren&rsquo;t a lot of people out early, and I love starting my day with some light cardio.</p>

<p>I share breakfast and coffee with my partner, often while catching up on our favorite morning TV show. At the moment I&rsquo;m being educated on Avatar: The Last Airbender. Ugh, Azula!</p>

<p>Breakfast is followed by a calendar sync. We check if either of us have overlapping or sensitive meetings. That way we know which calls either of us needs to take in another room - and which are okay to have in our workspace. Both of our desks are in the living room, and we use <a href="https://amzn.to/3ferNbP">noise cancelling headphones</a> throughout the day to help with focus. During the day we convert our bedroom to an ad hoc conference room.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/wfh-setup.jpg" title="A picture of my work-from-home setup." ></p>

<p>By 9 am, I have my desk set up: I replace my personal laptop with its corporate-issued counterpart. An <a href="https://amzn.to/2SwMCpc">external webcam</a> helps with the image quality, and a dedicated <a href="https://amzn.to/2W0vREV">display</a>, keyboard (<a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/vortex2_2.asp?kind=47&amp;kind2=220&amp;kind3=&amp;kind4=999">Vortex Pok3r</a> with <a href="https://drop.com/buy/91600">Matt3o Nerd DSA</a> key cap set), and a mouse (<a href="https://amzn.to/2SwNWbE">Glorious Model O-</a>) alleviate the cramped feeling I get when using a laptop.</p>

<p>Most importantly, I&rsquo;m showered, groomed, and dressed by this time. While working in whatever I slept in has worked well for occasional remote Fridays, it proved to be unsustainable for prolonged remote work. Whenever I wasn&rsquo;t dressed for work, I found myself slowly drifting towards the couch, and trading a laptop for my phone. In fact, some days I dress up even more than I used to when going to the office!</p>

<p>This is where the clear separation between home and work is established. I&rsquo;m fully dressed and have my workstation set up: it&rsquo;s work time!</p>

<p>I spend the next few hours busy with heads down work, usually working on a design, writing some code, or doing anything which requires concentration. Playing something like a <a href="https://rainycafe.com/">Rainy Cafe</a> in the background helps me stay in the zone.</p>

<p>Back in the office, 11 am used to be my workout time: a gym buddy of mine would consistency exercise at 11 am, and I adopted the habit of joining him over the past few years. I decided not to move the time slot: at 11 am I change into my workout clothes and exercise: 30 to 45 minutes of bodyweight exercises or online classes use up the remainder of my morning willpower. I&rsquo;m so glad there are thousands of YouTube videos to keep me company!</p>

<p>My partner and I alternate cooking, and the next hour or so is reserved for cooking, lunch together, and cleanup. Remember the noise cancelling headphones? We haven&rsquo;t heard (and often seen) each other since morning! Getting to share lunch daily has definitely been the highlight of staying at home for me.</p>

<p>After that - back to work: design reviews, meetings, busywork.</p>

<p>I wrap up around 5 pm, and make a point not to work past that. I swap out my work laptop for my own (even if I&rsquo;m not planning to use it), and stow it away for the night. Disassembling my setup paired with showering and changing into house clothes creates a solid dividing line between work and home.</p>

<p>Cooking dinner together and evening activities follow, but that&rsquo;s a story for another time. Stay healthy and productive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My book has been published!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-book-has-been-published/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-25T04:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-book-has-been-published</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past six to nine months I&rsquo;ve been working on a book - <a href="https://amzn.to/2EfGaN5">Mastering Vim</a>. Mastering Vim is a passion project which is meant to take the reader (you) from zero to a hero (future you): from knowing nothing about Vim, to becoming a power user. I cover many of Vim&rsquo;s mysterious commands, philosophy behind the beloved editor, configuration tips, a plethora of community created plugins, as well as creating your own plugins.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/mastering-vim.png" title="A picture of a &ldquo;Mastering Vim&rdquo; cover." ></p>

<p>Mastering Vim was written with support from Packt Publishing and was kindly reviewed by Bram Moolenaar (<a href="https://moolenaar.net">website</a>) - the creator of Vim. Many people made this book possible, including <a href="https://vimconf.org">VimConf Japan</a> crew, who kindly hosted me earlier this year. Thank you to everyone for making Mastering Vim happen!</p>

<p>Give it a read and let me know what you think, <a href="https://amzn.to/2EfGaN5">Mastering Vim is available on Amazon</a>!</p>

<p>P.S: This post, like many others, is written in Vim.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist phone launcher]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/minimalist-phone-launcher/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/minimalist-phone-launcher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few years I&rsquo;ve been trying to focus on having more mindful experiences in my life. I find it rewarding to be present in the moment, without my thoughts rushing onto whatever awaits me next.</p>

<p>I present to you the biggest distraction: my phone.</p>

<p>I use to get in touch with people I love. I&rsquo;m more productive at work because I have access to information on the go. I also use my phone to browse Reddit, YouTube, and every other media outlet imaginable. Even worse, sometimes I just waste time tinkering with the settings or mindlessly browsing through the apps I have installed.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an attention sink.</p>

<p>Nearly a year ago as I was browsing the Google Play Store I bumped into a new launcher: KISS. The tag line caught my attention: &ldquo;Keep It Simple, Stupid&rdquo;. I went ahead and downloaded the launcher. I haven&rsquo;t changed to another launcher since.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how my home screen looks today:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kiss-launcher-home-screen.png" title="A screenshot of a KISS launcher home screen." ></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing besides a single search bar. The search bar takes me to the apps I need, web searches I&rsquo;m interested in, or people I&rsquo;m trying to reach out to.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s simple to use. Start typing an app or a contact name, and the results show up above the search bar:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kiss-launcher-search-results.png" title="A screenshot of searching for an app with a KISS launcher." ></p>

<p>This simple concept has been responsible for cutting hours upon hours from my phone usage. Opening an app becomes a more deliberate experience, I open my phone with a purpose (granted this purpose might be to kill hours looking at cat videos). There&rsquo;s no more scrolling through everything I have installed just to find something to stimulate my attention for a few more seconds.</p>

<p>You can download the KISS Launcher for Android from <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=fr.neamar.kiss">Google Play Store</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Making a packing spreadsheet]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/making-a-packing-spreadsheet/"/>
    <updated>2018-03-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/making-a-packing-spreadsheet</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being the unique person I am, I love traveling. Oftentimes I end up getting deep into trying to optimize my packing methods. There are dozens of tools online designed to help with this exact thing (services like <a href="http://lighterpack.com">Lighterpack</a> or <a href="http://geargrams.com">GearGrams</a>). But, being handy with code, I decided to dabble in the subject on my own.</p>

<p>One of the most important things in packing is the overall weight of the pack, and I always want to know what type of things are the heaviest. I also want to be able to run random queries on my data, whatever it is that I&rsquo;m trying to learn. I want to have an inventory of items (backpacks, clothes, storage solutions) which I can plug in and out of a spreadsheet to see how the resulting picture changes on the go. Working with software as my day job, I’d also like for the solution to be automated whenever possible.</p>

<p>Google Spreadsheets turned out to be the perfect solution, providing the ability to quickly sum up the weight of my things and output insights about the data.</p>

<h2>Final Result</h2>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a <a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1qDhMoVmmTroM-eN0MZIU2PzE5YucsyPhbuPZPDGhemM/edit#">link to the spreadsheet</a>, I encourage the reader to copy and play around with in anyway you see fit.</p>

<p>Here’s the final result for a multi-day trip I will have for this year. As you can see, my pack weighs around 3 kilograms or a bit over 6 freedom units (not including water). My recently purchased Nintendo Switch is the heaviest item (and it’s worth every gram as it makes flying tolerable), but clothes take up most of the weight:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet.png" title="A screenshot of a packing spreadsheet." ></p>

<p>I use indentation levels to show that some items are contained within other items. This also lets me calculate the absolute and relative weights of a whole container with everything inside of it (see fields labeled “Container” and “Percentage”).</p>

<p>The “Weight” and the “Breakdown” fields indicate absolute and relative item weight respectively, which accounts for quantity of the item (quantity defaults to 1 if not explicitly set). Weight-related fields are color coded from lightest items in green to heaviest items in red.</p>

<p>Categories are used to group items and execute queries on the data and learn insights like these:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-weight-chart.png" title="A chart representing the weight of each category of items relative to a weight of the whole pack." ></p>

<p>There’s a separate sheet where I enter item names, categories, and weights, which I then use to automatically populate values above and autofill item names in the primary sheet:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-inventory.png" title="A screenshot of an inventory tab of the packing spreadsheet." ></p>

<h2>The Technical Details</h2>

<p>I haven’t worked with Google Spreadsheets (or Excel for that matter) a lot in the past, but with an access to clear documentation (and a hundred of web searches later) it was straightforward to get the hang of the it.</p>

<p>I started off by manually populating the final result sheet, manually adjusting formulas for Container/Percentage cells, as I had no idea how I would detect the indentation yet. I like when things look pretty, so I applied conditional formatting rules right away, and the looks of the sheet really haven’t changed throughout the process.</p>

<p>Next, I created an inventory sheet, which I wanted to use as a source of data in the resulting sheet. A few Google searches and some trial &amp; error resulted in a lookup formula:</p>

<pre><code>=ArrayFormula(
 IF(
   NOT(ISBLANK($B2)),
   INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($B2, InventoryItems, 0)),
   IF(
     NOT(ISBLANK($C2)),
     INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($C2, InventoryItems, 0)),
     INDEX(InventoryCategories, MATCH($D2, InventoryItems, 0))
   )
  )
)
</code></pre>

<p><code>ArrayFormula</code> is necessary in order to create arrays on the fly without printing intermediate results in the spreadsheet. <code>InventoryItems</code> and <code>InventoryCategories</code> are named ranges referring to item names and categories in the inventory sheet. <code>MATCH</code> finds an index of a first occurrence of the item name in the sheet, and retrieves corresponding category name. An item weight is retrieved by the exact same principle.</p>

<p>Trying to find the container weight took a lot more time, and resulted in a lot more headache. Solution for handling indentation in Google Spreadsheets wasn’t as elegant as I would have hoped for, but it got the job done:</p>

<pre><code>=ArrayFormula(
     SUM(
       $I2:INDIRECT(
         CONCATENATE(
           "$I",
           ROW() + IF(
             NOT(ISBLANK($B2)),
             MATCH(FALSE, ISBLANK($B3:$B), 0),
             MATCH(FALSE, ISBLANK($C3:$C), 0)
           ) - 1
         )
       )
     )
</code></pre>

<p>The formula above finds the first non-empty cell in a column. It starts searching from the next row (for example, for an item on a second row, we look at the third row and below). After it knows which row first non-empty cell is in, the formula turns it into a string (column $I contains item weights) and use it as an upper bound of a sum of the weights. Finished formula is a bit longer (it adds sugar to only display the number when needed), and if you’re interested - you can look it up in the spreadsheet.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/packing-spreadsheet-indentation.png" title="A screenshot used for explaining indentation logic." ></p>

<p>For example, in the screenshot above, the formula will start looking at cells in a column right after the &ldquo;Packing cube&rdquo;. As soon as it finds a non-empty cell (&ldquo;Nintendo Switch case&rdquo;), the formula will determine this row to be an upper boundary. The formula then will sum weights starting with a &ldquo;Packing cube&rdquo; row, and up to but not including &ldquo;Nintendo Switch case&rdquo; row.</p>

<p>The rest involved many small tweaks, adding pretty colors, hiding N/A errors and zeroes, and trying to find the perfect shade for column borders.</p>

<p>And, since you made it this far, here’s how the numbers above look in the real world:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/cleveland-trip-backpack-on-off.png" title="Side by side pictures of a packed backpack: open and closed." ></p>

<p>Hopefully you found this useful, or at least somewhat entertaining. There’s a lot of room for improvement, and I aimed to provide a framework and a few basic ideas for building a spreadsheet to accommodate one’s twisted ultralight needs.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A trip to Salt Lake City]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/a-trip-to-salt-lake-city/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-13T15:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/a-trip-to-salt-lake-city</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>This article is a collaboration between my partner and I.</em></p>

<p>Since moving into a studio, I have missed the freedom of taking off randomly, getting to know a different city or state and overall not being tied down to a routine or a location. I love the idea of trivializing travel, so it was only natural to have a random trip at the end of the week.</p>

<p>My partner watches <a href="http://www.thebucketlistfamily.com/">The Bucket List Family</a> on a weekly basis and caught the traveling bug as well. Unfortunately, we are not yet at the level where we can afford a 5 star trip to international locals or have companies pay for our travels (one day!). Our goal was to spend a few days going out of state to break the work week and avoid living for the weekend.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-ready-for-trip-to-slc.jpg" title="Ready for the trip to Salt Lake City." ></p>

<p>We decided to leave Northern California on Thursday afternoon for Salt Lake City, Utah as soon as we were done with work. Roughly 800 miles each way, if one counts exits and driving around sightseeing. Inspired by an acquaintance who travels the world with a folding bike, my partner and we took our bikes with us: a borrowed Brompton folding bike for my partner in the back seat, and my <a href="http://amzn.to/2xT6xT7">ZycleFix Prime</a> mounted on the rack in the rear.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/brompton-bike-in-the-backseat.jpg" title="Brompton bike in the backseat." ></p>

<p>Driving through California, Nevada, and Utah on I-80 was always one of my favorites - and it was nice to share the wonders of the world with my partner. She clocked in a lot more international travel than I did, but only been to a handful of states. It was her first time in Utah and each stop on the way to the Salt Flats exposed us to all kinds of people, different from the type of individuals we typically see inside the Silicon Valley tech bubble. We saw people with different lives, habits, hobbies, and worldviews, which to be perfectly honest, was refreshing.</p>

<p>Throughout the trip, we made it a point not to make any plans and go with the flow &ndash; be it our driving pace, entertainment or food options, or cities we decided to stay the night in. Traveling that way removed the stress associated with finding the perfect location and planning a fun trip. Don’t like the town we stopped at? Let’s keep driving. Enjoy a specific city? Let’s spend the night there. Having issues at a hotel? Back on the road we go.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/beautiful-sky-on-our-way.jpg" title="Beautiful sky as we’re driving on I-80." ></p>

<p>We found a hotel while driving on the I-80 and settled there for the night. Unfortunately the place did not have a strong enough WiFi, which led us to drive to the next town over for coffee and internet to work remotely. We ended up spending 6 hours in the coffee shop making sure that we kept ourselves well caffeinated and the servers well tipped. After a somewhat productive day, we decided to explore the city’s downtown and save the Salt Flats drive for the daytime.</p>

<p>Our Super 8 Motel in Wendover cost us around $70 for the night and was more comfortable than expected. We ended up passing out as soon as we got to the room, exhausted from the day. We tried to stay at cheaper hotels/motels, while avoiding shady looking places. We would most often pick the 2nd or 3rd cheapest option. We never stayed in one place for more than a night and lucked out every time we got ourselves a room. Every room we slept in was clean and we even managed to squeeze in a daily workout before the start of each day.</p>

<p>Keeping a healthy diet on the other hand was a whole other challenge. Between cafes, restaurants and late night cravings, we failed at maintaining proper eating habits and saving on food. We spent around $300 on food alone. Eating is definitely one area for improvement, especially as we decide to travel more. Dieting is hard and dieting on the road is even harder.</p>

<p>On Saturday, we finally headed to Utah and stopped at a rest stop by the Salt Flats. The view was marvelous and cold for an October day. We left the Salt Flats for a mall, City Creek Center, in Salt Lake City where we had another amazingly delicious and unhealthy lunch. To feel better about our life choices, we used our bikes to get some cardio and discover the city on two-wheels. We biked through Memory Grove Park, crashed a wedding, and biked almost to the Capitol. Almost. Due to Salt Lake’s incredible, deadly hills. Next time, SLC, next time we shall conquer you.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/salt-flats-are-gorgeous.jpg" title="Beautiful Salt Flats." ></p>

<p>After a day of biking and testing each other&rsquo;s patience, we decided to go for a date night and talk through our attempts at making life on the road work. Traveling solo is a very different experience than traveling with a partner. We chatted over Brazilian BBQ, another unhealthy choice, and agreed that we needed to include time alone as part of our travel routine and constantly check in with each other.</p>

<p>We headed to the hotel and decided to leave back for California after breakfast on Sunday. Oh, and on the topic of car, the subject of staying in the Prius or camping came up a few times. We even prepared our tents in that event but the cold weather and the thought of a hot shower took priority&hellip; Oh well, hotel Prius will get more use some other time.</p>

<p>In one day, we drove from Utah back to Northern California. We have different memories of the road back. For her, it was long and slow. For me as a driver, it passed within a blink of an eye. Overall, our trip to Utah was a success and we learned a lot:</p>

<ol>
<li>Nothing can replace the freedom associated with the absence of a plan. When there&rsquo;s no agenda or times to be at specific places - you&rsquo;re never late, never in a hurry, and you&rsquo;ve always seen more than you planned for. It allowed us to be surprised and delighted by places we encountered without imposing our pace on said locations.</li>
<li>Taking time for oneself is a necessity when traveling with someone else. Time alone does not always mean actually being alone. It can be whatever works for you as a couple. For us, it’s spending time on our devices while sitting next to each other.</li>
<li>Approaching each location with an open mind. You are not always going to get to travel to exotic <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/him-and-her-whats-inside-the-bag/">places like the Bahamas</a>, but the opportunity to fall in love with a place or its people is always there.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
