<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2016-01-21T07:43:43-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prius camper conversion]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/prius-camper-conversion/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-19T12:50:01-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/prius-camper-conversion</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As requested, I took some detailed pictures of the
<a href="http://amzn.to/1NvY78S">Prius Camper Conversion Kit</a> I mentioned in my <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/urban-prius-living">previous article</a>. It
adds valuable space to the back of the car when the seats are down, and helps to
push down the seats all the way in order to achieve a level surface. This
particular kit works for third generation of Prius, but can be slightly
modified to fit other models. In theory, something like this can work with any
car, as long as the rear seats can be forced down all the way to create a flat
surface (170 pounds of my bodyweight was enough to flatten out the seat back).</p>

<p>This is how the final conversion looks, with a mat cut to a custom shape on top
of it:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-final.jpg" title="This is how the final conversion looks." ></p>

<p>A wooden platform which is used to fill up rear leg space. Notice the blue
strap on the rear seat, that&rsquo;s what pushes down the seat to create a level
surface:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-with-the-mat-up.jpg" title="Wooden surface underneath the mat." ></p>

<p>The lid can be removed for storage space access:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-with-the-lid-off.jpg" title="Wooden platform with the lid off." ></p>

<p>It&rsquo;s a relatively thin wooden platform. Top (on the picture) side of it is a
bit slanted to fit on a rear seat back:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-wooden-platform-top.jpg" title="Top view of the wooden platform." ></p>

<p>View from the bottom: metal pieces are there to hold platform legs when the
platform is not in use, but I don&rsquo;t find them necessary. Additional (darker)
piece of wood is what the lid rests on:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-wooden-platform-bottom.jpg" title="Bottom view of the wooden platform." ></p>

<p>View from the side:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-wooden-platform-side.jpg" title="Side view of the wooden platform." ></p>

<p>With passenger front seat pushed all the way forward (and seat back in further
possible forward position), wooden supports are inserted into exposed seat
railing. I added some duct tape layers at the bottom of each leg so that they
don&rsquo;t wobble when the wooden platform is removed.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-wooden-legs.jpg" title="Wooden supports for the platform." ></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a right leg:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-wooden-legs-right.jpg" title="Right wooden support." ></p>

<p>I noticed that the left leg needed to be approximately 5 mm longer in order for
the platform not to wobble, so I extended it with whatever I had on hand:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-wooden-legs-left.jpg" title="Left wooden support." ></p>

<p>Adjustable belt with a hook on one side and a strap tie on the other:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-belt-with-a-hook.jpg" title="Belt with a hook." ></p>

<p>On the back side of rear seats there are places to secure a baby seat. I removed
the plastic covers (use some force), and attached a strap there. I added a piece
of cloth to (hopefully) prevent damage to seat fabric:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-belt-on-the-rear-seat.jpg" title="Belt on the rear seat." ></p>

<p>Tricky part is getting the bottom hook in the right place. Rear seats are held
in place by two metal locks. If you grab a rear seat from the bottom (when the
back is not folded) and pull up with approximately 50-100 pounds of force, the
seat will snap out of the place exposing the lock. Attach a hook to the exposed
part of the locking mechanism. Jump down on a seat to snap the rear seat back in
place. Exercise caution while you make your way through this, took me nearly an
hour to figure out how to properly attach a hook and snap the seat back in
place:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-camper-bottom-hook.jpg" title="Bottom hook on the belt." ></p>

<p>When both sides of the belt are in place, fold the rear seat, push in down with
your body weight, and tighten the belt.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Urban Prius living]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/urban-prius-living/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-18T12:55:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/urban-prius-living</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Not so long ago I stumbled upon a blog titled <a href="https://chrissawey.wordpress.com/">&ldquo;Hotel Prius&rdquo;</a>, and I loved
the idea. Being a Prius owner myself, I decided to give Prius living a test run.
Being cautious person I am, I decided to give it a test run for a week in a
familiar area.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-in-a-corporate-area.jpg" title="A Prius." ></p>

<h2>Preparing for the journey</h2>

<p>First, I decided to tint my windows. In addition to making a Prius look much
more pleasant, it keeps the car cooler throughout the day, and most importantly
makes it hard to peek inside the car. Especially at night.</p>

<p>Next, I ordered a <a href="http://amzn.to/1NvY78S">Prius Gen III Camping Sleeper Conversion Kit</a>. It&rsquo;s just a
fancy name for two belts to push down the rear seats, and two wooden platforms
with detachable feet to cover leg space. And two custom cut carpet runners to
cover up the panels. Nothing one can&rsquo;t make in their own garage, if the money is
tight.</p>

<p>The kit requires front seats to be locked in the furthest possible position,
rendering them unusable. So I only installed a panel behind a passenger seat.
With the panel installed, I have nearly 7 feet of level surface to sleep on.</p>

<p>Another problem with the kit is that it blocks the console from being opened
(arm rest storage between driver and passenger seat). I stopped using console as
a quick access box, and it doesn&rsquo;t feel like a big loss.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-sleeping-platform.jpg" title="Sleeping platform. Laundry bag at the bottom." ></p>

<p>I packed all my clothes in a duffle bag, bought a small toiletries kit, and put
the rest of my belongings in a backpack. Queen-sized sleeping bag I had came in
handy as a bed (with a couple of travel pillows).</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-duffle-bag-and-a-sleeping-bag.jpg" title="Duffle bag with clothes and a sleeping bag." ></p>

<p>After a second night I swapped my sleeping bag with a lighter and more compact
summer sleeping bag. That&rsquo;s also when I added a 1.5 inch sleeping pad to my
inventory.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-in-a-sleeping-position.jpg" title="Prius in a sleeping position, with toiletries kit and a duffle bag on the left, sleeping bag on the right." ></p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-bed-view-from-drivers-seat.jpg" title="View of a bed from the driver&rsquo;s seat." ></p>

<p>My backpack/briefcase is on the passenger&rsquo;s seat, I always take it with me.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-backpack-on-the-front-seat.jpg" title="Backpack on the passenger seat." ></p>

<p>In addition to all of the above, I took my guitar - even though it&rsquo;s bigger than
anything else I had to take with me, it&rsquo;s a great source of entertainment.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-guitar-and-bed-view.jpg" title="Guitar with a travel pillow on top, old backpack (now replaced)." ></p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re feeling impatient, links to all the items are at the bottom of the
post.</p>

<h2>Sleeping in a Prius</h2>

<h3>Night one</h3>

<p>First night in a Prius left me with mixed feelings. I parked in one of the
corporate areas of the city at about 9 pm. I picked a well lit parking lot with
some (but not much) evening traffic. I parked in one of the slightly darker
areas of the parking lot (approximately one out of twenty parking spots was
taken, and large number of cars made me feel safer).</p>

<p>It was 74F outside, slowly cooling after a 100F day. I left my car in accessory
mode (spoiler: bad idea), turned on the AC, locked the doors, and hopped on my
bedding arrangement to the back of the car. I didn&rsquo;t want to keep the windows
open since I just got them tinted. And sleeping with windows rolled down felt a
bit eerie.</p>

<p>First thing I noticed was how obnoxiously bright instrument panel and GPS are.
It was the opposite of stealthy, and it was plain annoying to sleep with those
bright lights on. I reached out for my duffle bag, and pulled out a couple of
towels to cover up both the instrument panel and GPS, as well as few AC control
LEDs. This made me feel at ease, and I tried to doze off into sleep.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-towels-on-instrument-panel.jpg" title="Towels covering an instrument panel and a GPS." ></p>

<p>The parking lot lights were a minor annoyance, mostly filtered out by a 20% rear
window tint. I&rsquo;ve heard some people pass somewhere within 20 feet of my car a
few times, but other than that it was quiet. Still, unfamiliar situation made it
hard to fall asleep.</p>

<p>And then a few voices and an engine noise disturbed my peace, pretty close to my
car. I waited for about 10 minutes, and the noise didn&rsquo;t go away. I raised my
head to see what&rsquo;s happening - turns out someone had a tire blowout a 2 parking
spots away from me, and a pickup truck pulled in next to them to help with
changing the tire. There were anywhere between 3 and 5 people walking around and
talking.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s when I quickly got dressed, climbed to a driver&rsquo;s seat, and drove off to
look for a quieter spot. It was 9:55 pm.</p>

<p>I went to a more secluded, but still well lit parking lot behind one of the
offices. Concentration of cars was about the same, but it looked like those cars
were left there overnight. I picked a spot within 50 feet of other parked cars,
where a tree was covering my car from the harsh street light.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-parking-spot-by-the-tree.jpg" title="Parking spot by the tree." ></p>

<p>Accessory mode, AC, lock the doors. Climbed in the back, and after some
restlessness (a fairly normal thing for me), I fell asleep. I woke up sometime
around 11:30 pm. It was fairly hot in the car, and it was hard to breathe. Turns
out accessory mode turned itself off at some point. Maybe the battery ran low,
or maybe there&rsquo;s a time limit of sort. I opened all the doors to air out a car
for a couple of minutes while I walked around and stretched.</p>

<p>In the meantime, I also noticed that because of the tinted windows, it&rsquo;s nearly
impossible to see what&rsquo;s inside the car while only standing a few feet away
from it. That was comforting.</p>

<p>Second attempt, this time I turned on the car the usual way (by depressing the
pedal). I used a foot brake for a peace of mind, set the AC to 68 degrees (with
external air flow setting), locked the car, covered the instrument panel and a
GPS, and climbed in the back.</p>

<p>AC was blowing on my neck, but I was too tired to worry about it. The car cooled
down and I climbed inside a sleeping bag (it was too hot before, and I was just
lying on top of it). I&rsquo;m used to sleeping on hard surfaces, so the setup felt
comfortable enough. The light from surrounding light poles was a bit too harsh,
so I covered my eyes with a T-shirt. I fell asleep.</p>

<p>I woke up a few times throughout the night, but I feel like I&rsquo;ve had enough
sleep. I woke up with the sun at about 6:30 am, got dressed, opened all doors to
ventilate the car, packed away a sleeping bag, and drove to work. I felt well
rested, even though my throat and neck felt a bit sore from the AC directed at
me.</p>

<p>Oh, and it cost me $1.40 to have an AC running through the night. The car would
turn on for about a minute every once in a while (30 minutes?) to recharge the
battery.</p>

<h3>Night two</h3>

<p>This time, I found a perfect spot in a small parking lot behind an office. Less
crowded than the previous time, but still well lit. I got lucky and found a
space with no direct street light being visible when laying down.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-parked-in-a-small-lot.jpg" title="Prius parked in a small parking lot." ></p>

<p>Turn the car on, AC to 68 degrees, lock the doors, hop to the back seat.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve slept well for the first couple of hours, but I ended up waking up well
rested at midnight. I stopped by my office and worked for a couple of hours.
Back to the car to get 4 more hours of sleep.</p>

<p>It cost me $1.38 to camp through the night with AC on.</p>

<h3>Night three</h3>

<p>My sleeping bag was too hot to use at room temperature, so I swapped it with a
summer down filled bag. I also purchased a self-inflating sleeping pad for more
comfort.</p>

<p>Things are getting better from now on.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-on-top-of-a-parking-garage.jpg" title="Prius on top of a parking garage." ></p>

<p>Feeling more confident, I found a four-story corporate parking lot and drove to
the top level. I parked at a well-lit spot without any direct lights coming
through the windows. I easily fell asleep a tad bit past nine, and woke up at 6
am refreshed and well rested. Secluded spot, comfortable sleeping pad, summer
sleeping bag, and increased confidence - all contributed to making sleeping in a
Prius a delightful experience.</p>

<p>This was also the night I learned a neat trick: if you recline the driver&rsquo;s seat
all the way, it becomes really easy to move between front seat and a sleeping
area.</p>

<p>Cost of running the car through the night: $1.63.</p>

<h3>Night four</h3>

<p>I decided to camp out in the same multi-level parking garage I did yesterday (it
has high enough number of cars so that I don&rsquo;t stand out - about one per fifty
parking spots; and the foot traffic is very low to non-existent). I found
another part of the garage with a roof access on a second level and pulled in
there. After getting situated, I realized I didn&rsquo;t account for all the lights -
bright parking lot lights from other levels ended up shining right in my face.
And even though I knew I couldn&rsquo;t be seen behind the tinted windows, it did
leave me feeling exposed.</p>

<p>I slid to the driver&rsquo;s seat and drove up a few levels to the previous spot.
Doors are locked, AC is set to 68F, instrument panel is covered, driver&rsquo;s seat
is reclined. I climbed to the back, and fell asleep.</p>

<p>It was a warm night, temperature outside was at 73F. It was hot enough for me to
wake up two times through the night, but that was a minor inconvenience.</p>

<p>Cost: $1.73.</p>

<h3>Night five</h3>

<p>It was one of the chillier nights, so sleeping was a very pleasant experience. I
picked the same spot I used on the third night. Absence of direct lights visible
from the car windows plays a huge role in making you feel safe.</p>

<p>Cost: $1.53 while also bringing Nexus 6 to a full charge.</p>

<h3>Night six</h3>

<p>Picked another spot in a similar area, I parked under a broken street light in a
well lit parking lot. I&rsquo;ve slept well. Mostly due to this being a cooler night
(65F).</p>

<p>Cost: $1.29 while also bringing Nexus 6 to a full charge.</p>

<h3>Night seven</h3>

<p>I was stuck in traffic in the evening, and I fiddled with the GPS for a while.
Turns out you can disable the obnoxiously bright screen by going into &ldquo;Setup&rdquo;
-> &ldquo;Display&rdquo; -> &ldquo;Screen off&rdquo;. Pushing any button on the GPS turns the screen
back on. I&rsquo;m still using the towels to cover up the instrument panel and AC
controls though.</p>

<p>Another fairly cold night, which made sleeping more comfortable. I went back to
the top of the parking garage. Night was a delight.</p>

<p>Cost: $1.39, with full Nexus 6 charging.</p>

<h3>Impressions</h3>

<p>Stealthy living in a Prius is very comfortable. With tinted windows there&rsquo;s just
enough privacy, it&rsquo;s safe and cheap to run AC through the night (cost averages
to about $1.48 per night). There&rsquo;s more than enough space for someone of my
height (5&#8217;11&#8221;). It took me a couple of days to get used to feeling relatively
exposed in public, but once I did - it was a breeze. Last five nights I have
slept without any problems.</p>

<p>Surprisingly, I&rsquo;ve slept better in a Prius than I did in my own bed. Here I
should probably note that I&rsquo;ve been having troubles sleeping on an off for some
time lately, and sleeping through the night in a car was a step up from where I
was before.</p>

<h3>Lessons learned</h3>

<p>Some things I didn&rsquo;t know before trying out sleeping in a Prius:</p>

<ul>
<li>Pick a well lit parking lot, ideally with some cars of similar value parked
overnight. Make sure there&rsquo;s not too much foot traffic.</li>
<li>Park in an area without direct light source near you. Also account for lights
visible from inside the car (light nearly a hundred feet away can still be
bother).</li>
<li>If you&rsquo;re using the AC, turn Prius engine on instead of leaving it in
accessory mode.</li>
<li>Proper AC vent direction is important. Fiddle with those until there are no
drafts in the sleeping area.</li>
<li>Use a sleeping mask to avoid being bothered by the lights if you couldn&rsquo;t find
area without visible light sources shining directly through the windows.</li>
<li>Since the temperature inside the car is regulated, summer sleeping bag is a
must.</li>
<li>Sleeping pad is very helpful in making the surface softer. 1.5 inches made a
huge difference in comfort.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Items I used</h2>

<p><img src="/images/posts/prius-storage-compartment.jpg" title="Storage compartment. Left to right, top to bottom: a travel pillow, miscellaneous items storage box, sleeping pad, sleeping bag, a book (I&rsquo;m not an avid reader these days), emergency supplies backpack, 10000 mAh power bank, paper towels." ></p>

<p>Here are the items directly related to the trip which I either purchased or
already owned.</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1NvY78S">Prius Gen III Camping Sleeper Conversion Kit</a>. While not as good of a fit
as something one can make with a garage and a set of tools, it&rsquo;s a quick (but
rather expensive, depending on your situation) solution.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1NvXpbA">eBags TLS Mother Lode Weekender Convertible Junior</a>.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1iFj0Sb">Kelty Cosmic 550 Dridown Sleeping Bag, Regular/41-Degree</a>. I started a
journey with a sleeping bag I already had around - winter
<a href="http://amzn.to/1Nw0clb">Coleman Calgary Cold-Weather Scoop Sleeping Bag</a>. Needless to say, Kelty
Cosmic 41 is lighter, and by far more compact.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1imaIyz">Therm-a-Rest ProLite Plus Sleeping Pad</a>. It&rsquo;s a 1.5 inch tall matress, I
found it to be extremely comfortable.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rei.com/product/870768/rei-roadtripper-duffel-medium">REI Roadtripper Duffel - Medium</a>. I don&rsquo;t have too many clothes (and I
live in California, taking winter clothing is out of the picture), so
everything fits in a duffel bag.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1K5CQPv">Eagle Creek Pack-It Clean/Dirty Cube</a>. Holds underwear and socks, also
doubles as a sealed laundry bag for both.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1imbiMJ">Therm-a-Rest Compressible Travel Pillow, Medium</a>. A comfortable pillow
which goes under a sleeping bag.</li>
<li><a href="http://www.rei.com/product/878299/rei-grande-shower-kit-black">REI Grande Shower Kit</a>. It&rsquo;s fairly big and holds all my toiletries.</li>
<li><a href="http://amzn.to/1iFkJqF">Ready America Emergency Kit, 2-Person, 3-Day Backpack</a>. Something I always
have in a car for the peace of mind.</li>
</ul>


<h2>Future improvement ideas</h2>

<p>I have a great stealthy setup, but having more privacy would&rsquo;ve been a nice
bonus. I&rsquo;ll probably look for some inconspicuous looking shades or curtains,
provided that the setup doesn&rsquo;t look too obvious.</p>

<h2>Philosophical implications</h2>

<p>This was an interesting experience. Inability to retreat to the safety of my
house got me out of my comfort zone. Initial discomfort passed quickly, and a
world of possibilities opened up to me.</p>

<p>Not having access to a house made me, well, feel bored. And that&rsquo;s amazing.
Without having an ability to default to a TV, gaming platform, or even a laptop
(it&rsquo;s really not that comfortable to work on a laptop in a car) - I had to get
creative. I got to play a guitar, a piano, sing, practice with a drum set. I
worked on my blog (this article took multiple revisions and hours upon hours of
time to look the way it does now). I went to Mozzart&rsquo;s Don Giovanni publicly
hosted in a nearby town.</p>

<p>And I finished this article, which took me about 8 days of revisions and
additions to finish.</p>

<p>Now, thanks to self-imposed restrictions, I&rsquo;m doing all the things I wanted to
do.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m a perpetual planner. And that sometimes becomes a problem, since I&rsquo;m always
looking forward to the next thing that&rsquo;s going to happen, sometimes not paying
attention to life right in front of me. With everything I have packed in a car,
there&rsquo;s nothing on the horizon. Nothing is far away. There&rsquo;s no home to go back
to, so I don&rsquo;t rush anywhere. I savor every moment I have.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My experience with minimalism]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-experience-with-minimalism/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-18T12:54:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-experience-with-minimalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Minimalism was always appealing to me. The philosophy of not having more than
one would need is close to my heart. Over the past few years, I&rsquo;ve been
&ldquo;trimming the fat&rdquo; off various parts of my life.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t recall when I started being drawn to a minimalistic lifestyle. I think
my passion for minimalism originates in my desire for organization and order.
It&rsquo;s comforting to know that a world around me has a certain structure.</p>

<p>I remember the time when I started living on my own. I just moved to United
States, away from my family. All my life fit in a half-empty suitcase at that
time. Few sets of clothes, a blanket, a pillow, some hygiene products, a small
laptop. Moving to a new place was as easy as throwing few things in that
suitcase.</p>

<p>After some time, I started accumulating more things. A guitar. More variations
of clothing. Cheap coffee table and a shoe rack from a dollar store. At that
time I rented a room in one of the shady areas of the city. Adding a few pieces
of furniture made a place feel like home.</p>

<p>Time has passed, and I moved again. Left the furniture behind, took the rest.
Still light, but I did have to make a few trips to move everything I needed. I
got even more comfortable. A gaming PC. Significantly more junk here and there.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s when I did my first big cleanup. I went through every item I owned, and
tossed it a trash bag if I didn&rsquo;t use it in the past 6 month. Old clothes, some
action figures, other useless junk I accumulated. As a result, I tossed two big
bags of stuff I didn&rsquo;t need. I still remember the liberating feeling. Knowing
that everything I own serves a purpose.</p>

<p>It felt like I could breathe again.</p>

<p>Years pass. I don&rsquo;t rent rooms anymore, but apartments, houses. This comes with
having to own more things. Real furniture. A TV. More musical instruments.
Having to accommodate guests. Cooking supplies. A bike. Outdoor furniture.</p>

<p>But I&rsquo;ve kept the minimalistic mindset, and I still do periodical clean outs.
Tossing almost everything I haven&rsquo;t used in a past six months. Reducing what I
own only to things that I need to have comfortable and enjoyable living.</p>

<p>Today, I don&rsquo;t think I can fit everything I own in that single suitcase. Hell, I
most certainly will need to hire a truck for my next move. But that&rsquo;s not
important. Minimalism isn&rsquo;t about the absence of things. If you feel like you
don&rsquo;t have enough - you&rsquo;re probably doing something wrong. Minimalism is about
not being excessive.</p>

<p>For me, knowing that my belongings serve a purpose makes me feel content,
clear-headed. It&rsquo;s comforting. It feels right.</p>

<p>Sometimes, I forget and start accumulating stuff. And that&rsquo;s when I go back to
reducing again. It&rsquo;s not an obsession, but a healthy periodical maintenance.
Often it takes months, or even years to get rid of certain things.</p>

<p>Replace a queen sized bed with a Japanese futon mat. Digitalize the growing
paper trail I keep. Travel the world for with a single suitcase.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
