<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2023-07-17T12:16:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Exercising online privacy rights]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/exercising-online-privacy-rights/"/>
    <updated>2021-07-19T14:19:41-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/exercising-online-privacy-rights</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Following Europe&rsquo;s 2016 General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR), California passed its own California Consumer Privacy Act (CCPA) in 2020. I won&rsquo;t pretend to understand the intricacies of the law or the differences between the two, but from what I understand this gives you the right to know exactly what data of yours do businesses use, and request that this information is to not be sold or to be deleted.</p>

<p>As a California resident, I decided to dedicate a long weekend to exercising my privacy rights. The long weekend turned into a week worth of back and forth with a dozen-or-so companies, and me having a much better idea of what information about me is out there.</p>

<p>Turned out many large websites provide privacy dashboards where you&rsquo;re able to review and see information collected or inferred about you. But most of this data is hidden behind a formal request process which takes a few days to a week.</p>

<hr />

<p>First, I decided to stroll through Google&rsquo;s privacy settings. There are two ways forward: privacy dashboard, or full-on Google Takeout. Google Takeout allows you to download an archive of <strong>everything</strong> Google has on you, which took a few days to process, and is near impossible to go through while keeping your sanity. So I decided to play with the privacy dashboard instead.</p>

<p>Google Maps has location history of most places I&rsquo;ve visited for the past ten or so years (creepy, but I found it useful on more than one occasion), and YouTube and Search history stores thousands of searches. I already had Assistant history disabled, since storing audio recordings is apparently where I draw the line when it comes to privacy. Targeted ad profile was an interesting thing to look at, accurately summing up my lifestyle in 50 words or less. I ended up disabling targeted ads from Google (and all other services as I went about on my privacy crusade).</p>

<p>Google had some of the finest privacy controls compared to other services, with actionable privacy-leaning suggestions. Google&rsquo;s not known for its services playing well together, but privacy is where Google feels closer to Apple experience - everything is in a single place, surfaced in the same format, easy to control, and plays well together. Given the amount of transparency and fine grained control, I feel pretty good staying in the Google ecosystem.</p>

<hr />

<p>Next I looked at LinkedIn. Outside of the expected things &ndash; emails, phone numbers, messages, invitations, and a history of just about everything I&rsquo;ve ever clicked on, a file labeled &ldquo;inferences&rdquo; stood out. Whether LinkedIn thinks you&rsquo;re open to job seeking opportunities, or what stage of career you are in, or if you travel for businesses, or if you&rsquo;re a recruiter or maybe a senior leader in your company.</p>

<p>Since LinkedIn is a professional network, all information I share is well curated and is meant as public by default &ndash; and I found LinkedIn privacy settings in line with my expectations.</p>

<hr />

<p>As an avid gamer, I went through Steam, Good Old Games, Ubisoft, Epic Games, and Origin privacy details. Unsurprisingly, the services tracked every time I launched every game, shopping preferences, and so on. Thankfully the data seemed confined to the world of gaming &ndash; which made this level of being creepy somewhat okay in my book.</p>

<p>I also looked at random websites I use somewhat frequently &ndash; Reddit, StackOverflow, PayPal, Venmo, AirBnB, and some others &ndash; not too many surprises there, although I did end up tightening privacy settings and opting out of personal data sharing and ad tracking for every service.</p>

<p>Last year I requested deletion of all my data on Mint, Personal Capital, and YNAB (You Need a Budget), and to be honest I&rsquo;m a little relived that I didn&rsquo;t have to look at the data these companies had on me.</p>

<hr />

<p>Amazon data sharing turned out to be the scariest finding. Until now I didn&rsquo;t really self-identify as a heavy Amazon user, but that turned out to be a lie: Prime shopping, Kindle, Audible, Prime Video.</p>

<p>The amount of data Amazon kept on me was overwhelming: Kindle and Audible track every time I read, play, or pause books, the Amazon website keeps full track of browsing habits, and Prime Video has detailed watch times and history. Most of this data ties back into real world &ndash; including nearly every address I ever lived at or phone numbers I had.</p>

<p>Even scarier, despite never using Alexa, I found numerous recordings of my voice from close to a decade ago &ndash; me checking status of the packages, but a few of me just breathing and walking around. I found no way of deleting these, as they didn&rsquo;t show up in any privacy settings (including me installing an Alexa app just to get into privacy settings).</p>

<p>All of this gave me pause. It feels like the privacy controls are either lacking, hidden, or spread out thin across Amazon&rsquo;s various apps. And I&rsquo;ve only briefly scanned through the data Amazon had on me.</p>

<hr />

<p>That&rsquo;s where I had to take a break.</p>

<p>I have accounts with hundreds of services, and I have no idea how my personal data is used, and what it&rsquo;s joined with. As I&rsquo;m go on about my daily life, I&rsquo;ll start tightening privacy controls, and maybe deleting services and their data where possible.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s just too creepy for my taste.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Writing for fun]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/writing-for-fun/"/>
    <updated>2020-11-11T02:13:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/writing-for-fun</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve had this blog since 2012, and I&rsquo;m only now getting close to my 100th post. All because I&rsquo;m a perfectionist, which sure as hell didn&rsquo;t make me a better writer.</p>

<p>I love writing, and I feel like I&rsquo;m getting better after every piece I write - be it publishing blog posts, journaling, countless design docs, navigating email politics, or writing a book. I write a lot, about many different topics - if I&rsquo;m interested in the topic for at least a few hours - you can bet I&rsquo;ll write about it.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/journal.jpg" title="A picture of journal on a table." ></p>

<p>Then how come this blog barely gets one post per month?</p>

<p>I meticulously research and edit, generously discard drafts, and it often takes me days strung across weeks to put something together. Something that I feel is worthy of being displayed next to my name. Perfectionism at its core, attached to hobbyist web content.</p>

<p>I struggled with this when writing <a href="https://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-book-has-been-published/">Mastering Vim</a> too - the first edition was rushed out by the publisher long before it was ready, with various errors and inconsistencies in it, and a few downright unfinished bits. It took over a year of me avoiding even thinking about the book and two more editions to become comfortable with merely sharing that I published a book.</p>

<p>And all of this sucks the joy out of writing. I&rsquo;m not a for-profit writer. It&rsquo;s not part of my career path, and I obviously didn&rsquo;t go to school for it (not that I went to school for anything else). And it sure as hell shouldn&rsquo;t be grueling to have to come up with what to write.</p>

<p>This blog has a rather modest following - it brings in around 3,000 readers a month, with a few regulars sprinkled here and there (honestly - I would love to meet at least one of you weirdos someday). I don&rsquo;t target a particular market niche, I don&rsquo;t have a content or SEO strategy, and I opportunistically monetize to cover the website running costs.</p>

<p>What&rsquo;s crazy is that nearly half of that traffic is organic search for a quick note I jotted down back in 2013! I could spend weeks putting together a literary love child and not even get a fraction of attention this back of the napkin screenshot received.</p>

<p>Back in 2012 I used this blog as a way to categorize my discoveries about developing software, and later what I&rsquo;ve learned about working with people. Over the years I gradually expanded to travel (including that time I lived in my car for a year), and general things I like - like keyboards or tabletop role playing games.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m putting this together to remind myself that I love writing and why I started this blog. That not every piece of content requires hours of research, or even have a clear audience in mind for that matter.</p>

<p>I wouldn&rsquo;t have blinked an eye flooding this blog with unfiltered thoughts, perspectives, and experiences if it wasn&rsquo;t attached to my real world persona. It&rsquo;s easy to throw out something I perceive as &ldquo;unworthy&rdquo; anonymously. It&rsquo;s mortifying to publish such a piece at my-first-name-last-name-dot-com.</p>

<p>So here it is, the first post I wrote purely for fun! I&rsquo;m still taking a light editing pass on it, and drastically cutting it down in size - I&rsquo;m not a savage! But unlike in my usual writing, there&rsquo;s no clear value I&rsquo;m providing or a skill I&rsquo;m trying to teach - and that&rsquo;s a huge step for me. Feels good!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adjusting to working from home]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/adjusting-to-wfh/"/>
    <updated>2020-05-04T09:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/adjusting-to-wfh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Like many, I moved to working from home during the COVID-19 pandemic. Parts of California enacted shelter-in-place order back in March, and it&rsquo;s been over a month and a half since then. I briefly worked from home back in 2013 as a freelancer - and I really got the whole work/life balance thing wrong. So this time around I&rsquo;ve decided to approach remote work with a plan.</p>

<p>My day begins around 7 or 8 am, without too much deviation from schedule. I used to bike to work before the pandemic, and I try to head out for a 30 minute ride in a morning a few days a week. There aren&rsquo;t a lot of people out early, and I love starting my day with some light cardio.</p>

<p>I share breakfast and coffee with my partner, often while catching up on our favorite morning TV show. At the moment I&rsquo;m being educated on Avatar: The Last Airbender. Ugh, Azula!</p>

<p>Breakfast is followed by a calendar sync. We check if either of us have overlapping or sensitive meetings. That way we know which calls either of us needs to take in another room - and which are okay to have in our workspace. Both of our desks are in the living room, and we use <a href="https://amzn.to/3ferNbP">noise cancelling headphones</a> throughout the day to help with focus. During the day we convert our bedroom to an ad hoc conference room.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/wfh-setup.jpg" title="A picture of my work-from-home setup." ></p>

<p>By 9 am, I have my desk set up: I replace my personal laptop with its corporate-issued counterpart. An <a href="https://amzn.to/2SwMCpc">external webcam</a> helps with the image quality, and a dedicated <a href="https://amzn.to/2W0vREV">display</a>, keyboard (<a href="http://www.vortexgear.tw/vortex2_2.asp?kind=47&amp;kind2=220&amp;kind3=&amp;kind4=999">Vortex Pok3r</a> with <a href="https://drop.com/buy/91600">Matt3o Nerd DSA</a> key cap set), and a mouse (<a href="https://amzn.to/2SwNWbE">Glorious Model O-</a>) alleviate the cramped feeling I get when using a laptop.</p>

<p>Most importantly, I&rsquo;m showered, groomed, and dressed by this time. While working in whatever I slept in has worked well for occasional remote Fridays, it proved to be unsustainable for prolonged remote work. Whenever I wasn&rsquo;t dressed for work, I found myself slowly drifting towards the couch, and trading a laptop for my phone. In fact, some days I dress up even more than I used to when going to the office!</p>

<p>This is where the clear separation between home and work is established. I&rsquo;m fully dressed and have my workstation set up: it&rsquo;s work time!</p>

<p>I spend the next few hours busy with heads down work, usually working on a design, writing some code, or doing anything which requires concentration. Playing something like a <a href="https://rainycafe.com/">Rainy Cafe</a> in the background helps me stay in the zone.</p>

<p>Back in the office, 11 am used to be my workout time: a gym buddy of mine would consistency exercise at 11 am, and I adopted the habit of joining him over the past few years. I decided not to move the time slot: at 11 am I change into my workout clothes and exercise: 30 to 45 minutes of bodyweight exercises or online classes use up the remainder of my morning willpower. I&rsquo;m so glad there are thousands of YouTube videos to keep me company!</p>

<p>My partner and I alternate cooking, and the next hour or so is reserved for cooking, lunch together, and cleanup. Remember the noise cancelling headphones? We haven&rsquo;t heard (and often seen) each other since morning! Getting to share lunch daily has definitely been the highlight of staying at home for me.</p>

<p>After that - back to work: design reviews, meetings, busywork.</p>

<p>I wrap up around 5 pm, and make a point not to work past that. I swap out my work laptop for my own (even if I&rsquo;m not planning to use it), and stow it away for the night. Disassembling my setup paired with showering and changing into house clothes creates a solid dividing line between work and home.</p>

<p>Cooking dinner together and evening activities follow, but that&rsquo;s a story for another time. Stay healthy and productive!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My book has been published!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-book-has-been-published/"/>
    <updated>2018-12-25T12:00:00+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-book-has-been-published</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past six to nine months I&rsquo;ve been working on a book - <a href="https://amzn.to/2EfGaN5">Mastering Vim</a>. Mastering Vim is a passion project which is meant to take the reader (you) from zero to a hero (future you): from knowing nothing about Vim, to becoming a power user. I cover many of Vim&rsquo;s mysterious commands, philosophy behind the beloved editor, configuration tips, a plethora of community created plugins, as well as creating your own plugins.</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/mastering-vim.png" title="A picture of a &ldquo;Mastering Vim&rdquo; cover." ></p>

<p>Mastering Vim was written with support from Packt Publishing and was kindly reviewed by Bram Moolenaar (<a href="https://moolenaar.net">website</a>) - the creator of Vim. Many people made this book possible, including <a href="https://vimconf.org">VimConf Japan</a> crew, who kindly hosted me earlier this year. Thank you to everyone for making Mastering Vim happen!</p>

<p>Give it a read and let me know what you think, <a href="https://amzn.to/2EfGaN5">Mastering Vim is available on Amazon</a>!</p>

<p>P.S: This post, like many others, is written in Vim.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Minimalist phone launcher]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/minimalist-phone-launcher/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/minimalist-phone-launcher</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the past few years I&rsquo;ve been trying to focus on having more mindful experiences in my life. I find it rewarding to be present in the moment, without my thoughts rushing onto whatever awaits me next.</p>

<p>I present to you the biggest distraction: my phone.</p>

<p>I use to get in touch with people I love. I&rsquo;m more productive at work because I have access to information on the go. I also use my phone to browse Reddit, YouTube, and every other media outlet imaginable. Even worse, sometimes I just waste time tinkering with the settings or mindlessly browsing through the apps I have installed.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an attention sink.</p>

<p>Nearly a year ago as I was browsing the Google Play Store I bumped into a new launcher: KISS. The tag line caught my attention: &ldquo;Keep It Simple, Stupid&rdquo;. I went ahead and downloaded the launcher. I haven&rsquo;t changed to another launcher since.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s how my home screen looks today:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kiss-launcher-home-screen.png" title="A screenshot of a KISS launcher home screen." ></p>

<p>There&rsquo;s nothing besides a single search bar. The search bar takes me to the apps I need, web searches I&rsquo;m interested in, or people I&rsquo;m trying to reach out to.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s simple to use. Start typing an app or a contact name, and the results show up above the search bar:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/kiss-launcher-search-results.png" title="A screenshot of searching for an app with a KISS launcher." ></p>

<p>This simple concept has been responsible for cutting hours upon hours from my phone usage. Opening an app becomes a more deliberate experience, I open my phone with a purpose (granted this purpose might be to kill hours looking at cat videos). There&rsquo;s no more scrolling through everything I have installed just to find something to stimulate my attention for a few more seconds.</p>

<p>You can download the KISS Launcher for Android from <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=fr.neamar.kiss">Google Play Store</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
