<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: life | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/life/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-18T17:34:07-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My experience with minimalism]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-experience-with-minimalism/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-18T12:54:36-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/my-experience-with-minimalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Minimalism was always appealing to me. The philosophy of not having more than
one would need is close to my heart. Over the past few years, I&rsquo;ve been
&ldquo;trimming the fat&rdquo; off various parts of my life.</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t recall when I started being drawn to a minimalistic lifestyle. I think
my passion for minimalism originates in my desire for organization and order.
It&rsquo;s comforting to know that a world around me has a certain structure.</p>

<p>I remember the time when I started living on my own. I just moved to United
States, away from my family. All my life fit in a half-empty suitcase at that
time. Few sets of clothes, a blanket, a pillow, some hygiene products, a small
laptop. Moving to a new place was as easy as throwing few things in that
suitcase.</p>

<p>After some time, I started accumulating more things. A guitar. More variations
of clothing. Cheap coffee table and a shoe rack from a dollar store. At that
time I rented a room in one of the shady areas of the city. Adding a few pieces
of furniture made a place feel like home.</p>

<p>Time has passed, and I moved again. Left the furniture behind, took the rest.
Still light, but I did have to make a few trips to move everything I needed. I
got even more comfortable. A gaming PC. Significantly more junk here and there.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s when I did my first big cleanup. I went through every item I owned, and
tossed it a trash bag if I didn&rsquo;t use it in the past 6 month. Old clothes, some
action figures, other useless junk I accumulated. As a result, I tossed two big
bags of stuff I didn&rsquo;t need. I still remember the liberating feeling. Knowing
that everything I own serves a purpose.</p>

<p>It felt like I could breathe again.</p>

<p>Years pass. I don&rsquo;t rent rooms anymore, but apartments, houses. This comes with
having to own more things. Real furniture. A TV. More musical instruments.
Having to accommodate guests. Cooking supplies. A bike. Outdoor furniture.</p>

<p>But I&rsquo;ve kept the minimalistic mindset, and I still do periodical clean outs.
Tossing almost everything I haven&rsquo;t used in a past six months. Reducing what I
own only to things that I need to have comfortable and enjoyable living.</p>

<p>Today, I don&rsquo;t think I can fit everything I own in that single suitcase. Hell, I
most certainly will need to hire a truck for my next move. But that&rsquo;s not
important. Minimalism isn&rsquo;t about the absence of things. If you feel like you
don&rsquo;t have enough - you&rsquo;re probably doing something wrong. Minimalism is about
not being excessive.</p>

<p>For me, knowing that my belongings serve a purpose makes me feel content,
clear-headed. It&rsquo;s comforting. It feels right.</p>

<p>Sometimes, I forget and start accumulating stuff. And that&rsquo;s when I go back to
reducing again. It&rsquo;s not an obsession, but a healthy periodical maintenance.
Often it takes months, or even years to get rid of certain things.</p>

<p>Replace a queen sized bed with a Japanese futon mat. Digitalize the growing
paper trail I keep. Travel the world for with a single suitcase.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
