<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: book reviews | Ruslan Osipov]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/categories/book-reviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-20T16:56:57-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.rosipov.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Ruslan Osipov]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[ruslan@rosipov.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["The Pragmatic Programmer"]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-pragmatic-programmer/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-14T18:43:26-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-pragmatic-programmer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just finished reading &ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1zXtlQx">The Pragmatic Programmer</a>&rdquo; by Andrew Hunt and
David Thomas - two consultants behind Pragmatic Programmers, LLC. This book
might as well be a fantastic marketing trick for their consulting agency, but
the value it brings to the reader is hard to underestimate.</p>

<p>Hunt and Thomas cover a wide variety of topics, briefly glancing over every
major aspect of developing software: be it the choice of a text editor,
calculating time complexity, or working effectively on a team.</p>

<p>If you read thematic books and actively follow programming blogs and podcasts -
you may find yourself cheerfully nodding while reading sections of this book.
You may have read about some of the tips online, heard from colleagues, or
simply discovered them yourself. You will finish this book with a wide smile of
approval, and a sense of validation in regards to your daily work flow or
actions.</p>

<p>If you are less lucky (say, you don&rsquo;t read as much), you will find 70 tips you
can utilize right away, right now, at your workplace. This is what &ldquo;The
Pragmatic Programmer&rdquo; essentially is: a collection of practical things
regarding getting things done.</p>

<p>It&rsquo;s an essential read, and I&rsquo;ve seen this book in every single recommended
reading list out there. And for a solid reason. This is the kind of book you
want to re-read every couple of years to absorb every piece of knowledge
presented within it. The latest edition of the book even contains a printout
with all the tips listed in the book.</p>

<p>You should read it after being in the field for a few years. After making
mistakes, and figuring some things out on your own. Beginners might not
understand some pieces, but will still be able to comprehend a major portion of
knowledge contained within this book.</p>

<p>I enthusiastically recommend this book to every software engineer I get to work
with. It&rsquo;s easy to read (as opposed to monstrosities like &ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1zGLlv1">Code Complete</a>&rdquo;
or &ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1zGLnDl">Art of Computer Programming</a>&rdquo;) and it teaches you how to get things
done, the pragmatic way.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["The Elements Of Style"]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-elements-of-style/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-20T10:58:35-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-elements-of-style</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>You might wonder what an English language style guide from 1918 is doing in a
software engineering blog. You might even get angry at me for pointing this
book in your face. But I have a strong affection towards this guide; I believe
everyone who has to write more than a sentence in English should read it. I
like to emphasize the communication aspects of a software engineering career as
much as coding or management skills.</p>

<p>English is not my native language, and I often struggle with the writing style.
I found a number of style tips online and in the books I read, but lately I
noticed a pattern: most of those tips referenced &ldquo;The Elements Of Style&rdquo;. The
book is available online free of charge (copyright has expired; it is now in
public domain) and takes only an evening to read.</p>

<p>What the book gives you is invaluable writing advice. The author provides
concrete style rules targeted at increasing the appeal and comprehension rates
of your text. Here&rsquo;s my favorite piece of advice:</p>

<blockquote><p>13. Omit needless words.</p>

<p>Vigorous writing is concise. A sentence should contain no unnecessary
words, a paragraph no unnecessary sentences, for the same reason that a
drawing should have no unnecessary lines and a machine no unnecessary
parts. This requires not that the writer make all his sentences short, or
that he avoid all detail and treat his subjects only in outline, but that
he make every word tell.</p></blockquote>

<p>&ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1v6keFG">The Elements Of Style</a>&rdquo; is a timeless classic; it should be mandatory
reading for every speaker or learner of English out there. I immediately
applied the rules to technical documentation, email communication, and even
this very blog entry. I will probably have to read through the guide multiple
times over the course of the following months in order to ensure maximum
retention. If you care about being understood by another human being, you
should read it too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["Expert Python Programming" by Tarek Ziade]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/expert-python-programming-by-tarek-ziade/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-19T19:33:38-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/expert-python-programming-by-tarek-ziade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently, I&rsquo;ve been trying to read at least one book every week, and this
week&rsquo;s pick was &ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1yRw7AZ">Expert Python Programming</a>&rdquo; by Tarek Ziade. Besides its
few shortcomings, I found it to be useful - Python is a language of choice for
me, and I found some valuable tips I could add to my arsenal.</p>

<p>The best thing about this book is that it covers a very wide range of topics:
syntax recommendations and code profiling, testing practices and project
management, technical writing and design patterns, package distribution and
version control&hellip; My favorite chapter covered writing technical documentation:
I am very interested in writing in general, and the tips Ziade provided turned
out to be very useful for documenting code, writing design documents, and even
posting to this blog. Not much else caught my eye, but I had a number of &ldquo;Aha!&rdquo;
moments such as, &ldquo;Oh, I never used that!&rdquo; and &ldquo;That&rsquo;s an interesting topic to
look into!&rdquo; scattered throughout the book. This book is very useful for filling
in little gaps in knowledge which programmers can have: the author covers an
extremely wide variety of Python development aspects.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, I found the book to be poorly written. Weak writing style, typos
in the text and code examples - it looked like the book was put together
sloppily, in haste. Reviewers did not do a very good job evaluating this book.
&ldquo;Expert Python Programming&rdquo; gives you the feeling that the author tried to fit
in as much content (and code) as possible in his book, with no consistent
style. Many chapters go into unnecessary details, and the author has tendency
to paste completely useless chunks of code, such as a page-long output of an
installer. As I have mentioned, the book hops from one topic to another, and
covers a wide variety of subjects: this is both a key strength and the biggest
weakness of the book. There is just &ldquo;too much stuff&rdquo; and it&rsquo;s too scattered
across the topics.</p>

<p>&ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1yRw7AZ">Expert Python Programming</a>&rdquo; will be of best use to, you guessed it, an
expert. I found it best to scan through the content and seek out interesting
bits of information. Beginners, however, might be completely overwhelmed. While
advanced and intermediate Pythonistas will get the most out of this book, it
will probably be too hard (and painful) to read to be of real value.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Steve Krug's "Don't Make Me Think"]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/steve-krugs-dont-make-me-think/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-16T20:42:51-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/steve-krugs-dont-make-me-think</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I received in the mail a copy of Steve Krug&rsquo;s
&ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/1xCNOm4">Don&rsquo;t Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common Sense Approach To Web And Mobile Usability</a>&rdquo;
(oh, that&rsquo;s a long name). I went through the whole book only in under a few
hours, and I am so glad I&rsquo;ve read it. It&rsquo;s a very quick read, but the book is
full of concrete and valuable tips and advice about usability.</p>

<p>&ldquo;Don&rsquo;t Make Me Think&rdquo; contains practical advice on a large number of topics:
web and mobile usability, design, and writing for the web. The advice can be
easily used and incorporated into your daily workflow; and the author provides
concrete guidelines for applying his tips in the real world.</p>

<p>The biggest thing I&rsquo;ve learned from this book (and want to apply in practice)
is individual usability testing. I actually performed my first usability test
just three days ago, just before reading &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t Make Me Think&rdquo;, after I found
that Donald Norman&rsquo;s masterpiece mentioned observing user interactions with
your product (I&rsquo;ll get to the similarities between two of these books in a
moment).</p>

<p>I asked two of my colleagues, one after another, to visit a website I was
working on, and I silently watched them navigate through it. They had never
seen the website before, and the results were very shocking to me: they ignored
the things most obvious to me, but attempted to click through things which are
not even meant to be clicked. I carefully wrote down all of my findings, and
delivered the patches with enhancements to improve the biggest areas of
struggle these particular users had faced.</p>

<p>Usability testing turned out to be invaluable: it pointed out actions that I,
as a developer, did not anticipate, and highlighted parts of the system ignored
by the users. I now plan to run usability tests regularly, grabbing colleagues
from the hallway, and asking them to use my application for a few minutes.</p>

<p>Steve Krug&rsquo;s book is very much like <a href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-design-of-everyday-things/">&ldquo;The Design Of Everyday Things&rdquo;</a>, but
stripped from the extended theoretical part. The book references Norman&rsquo;s work
quite a lot, and seems to be heavily influenced by it. It focuses on practical
aspects of designing easy to use and understandable user interfaces. It
successfully explains why you should be thoughtful of user experience,
accessibility, and understanding the way users think. I would recommend reading
this book after reading Donald Norman&rsquo;s masterpiece first, since it provides
you with the reasoning behind many decisions Steve Krug makes throughout his
book.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA["The Design of Everyday Things"]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-design-of-everyday-things/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-15T14:23:50-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.rosipov.com/blog/the-design-of-everyday-things</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Unfortunately, I have not been reading as much as I would love to lately. In
the past year I have only read two books, one of which was a technical manual.
Don&rsquo;t get me wrong, I still had a lot of personal and professional growth going
on: reading blogs, articles, guides, watching keynote talks&hellip; But I did miss
the feeling of holding a good book in my hands, turning the pages with the tips
of my fingers, seeing the texture of the paper under the print. A few weeks ago
I went ahead and ordered one of the books on my reading list: &ldquo;The Design of
Everyday Things&rdquo; by Donald A. Norman. I just finished reading it a few hours
ago and am eager to share my impressions of the book.</p>

<p>&ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/16ORgF9">The Design of Everyday Things</a>&rdquo; turned out to be one of the most
eye-opening books about design I have ever read (alright, alright, I haven&rsquo;t
read any design books before). It&rsquo;s mind blowing to think that I have never
considered the points brought up by the authors. Hell, (and I will probably
have rotten tomatoes thrown at me for this statement) but I didn&rsquo;t even think
design was a &ldquo;real&rdquo; job. Oh dear, how wrong I was.</p>

<p>Norman&rsquo;s masterpiece talks about the psychology of everyday things (which was
actually the initial title of the book, but was changed to &ldquo;Design&rdquo; after the
first release). The author explains how users make decisions, use objects, make
errors - and so many other factors which should go into the design process.
Norman explains fundamental basics of the psychology of human-object
interaction, something most people never think about. How hard could it be to
design a door? Turns out the answer is - very hard. And every time you see
someone pulling the door instead of pushing and vice versa - it&rsquo;s a result of a
poor design. So many everyday frustrations could have been avoided if designers
would have put more thought into usability of their product.</p>

<p>I build software for living, and I was skeptical if I even needed to know
anything about good design. I mean, how hard could it be to put together a few
pages and forms? &ldquo;I tackle complex software problems, I don&rsquo;t need any of this
liberal arts bullshit!&rdquo; - I thought that way, and I know many people who still
do. Well, Norman&rsquo;s book is a great starter for people like me: he does a great
job explaining why the design process so important. By the time I finished
reading it, I had a pretty solid set of ideas why there are so many things
wrong with our industry, and how good, thoughtful design is a way out. The
funniest part is - the book itself is published in the year 1988, over
twenty-five years ago. It doesn&rsquo;t talk much about computers, concentrating on
objects more common at the time: cars, telephone systems, even stoves and dish
washing machines. And here I am, reading this book in the year 2014 - and the
situation did not change at all. Expensive laundry machines are as hard to
operate, computer programs are as clunky.</p>

<p>&ldquo;<a href="http://amzn.to/16ORgF9">The Design of Everyday Things</a>&rdquo; compels the reader to become a part of the
solution to this enormous and bulky design problem the world is stuck with. In
the everyday world, for every good case of design out there, you will face a
hundred faulty, frustrating, and downright insulting design attempts.</p>

<p>The book is very easy and pleasant to read, and I went through it in under a
week. Most of it is a set of rants about poor design decisions, with suggested
improvements and solutions. Throughout the reading process, I had to revisit
the systems I built at work and rearrange the components, add more feedback to
user&rsquo;s actions, and do many other little and big improvements in order to make
make the system image much more transparent to the user. Norman taught me the
most obvious truth: a designer is not your typical user of the system. This
changes so many things, makes you doubt and rethink a number of design
decisions you made along the way - all in order to build a product that is easy
and pleasant to use.</p>

<p>I now consider myself to be blessed with an understanding of the importance of
good design, and admitting there is a problem is the first step to fixing it.
And believe me, there is a problem. I will now continue learning about the best
practices in building systems that are easy to understand and pleasant to
operate for the user. My next stop is &ldquo;Don&rsquo;t Make Me Think, Revisited: A Common
Sense Approach to Web Usability&rdquo; by Steve Krug. I&rsquo;ve heard a lot about this
book, and I will be sure to share my impressions here.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
